<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<similar>
	<info>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Johann Sebastian Bach]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Johann Sebastian Bach</b> (31 March 1685 &ndash; 28 July 1750) was a German composer and organist whose sacred and secular works for choir, orchestra, and solo instruments drew together the strands of the Baroque period and brought it to its ultimate maturity. Although he introduced no new forms, he enriched the prevailing German style with a robust contrapuntal technique, an unrivalled control of harmonic and motivic organisation in composition for diverse instrumentation, and the adaptation of rhythms and textures from abroad, particularly Italy and France.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J.S.Bach]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA['Air' from Suite No.3 in D major - Johann Sebastian Bach]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/CyLo9-Voy5s&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Amadeus]]></name>
			<type>movie</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b><i>Amadeus</b></i> is a 1984 drama directed by Miloš Forman and written by Peter Shaffer. Based on Shaffer's stage play <i>Amadeus</i>, the film is based loosely on the lives of Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart and Antonio Salieri, two composers who lived in Vienna, Austria, during the later half of the 18th century.<br />The film was nominated for 53 awards and received 40, including 8 Academy Awards (including Best Picture), 4 BAFTA Awards, 4 Golden Globes, and a DGA Award. In 1998, <i>Amadeus</i> was ranked the 53rd best American movie by the American Film Institute on its <i>AFI's 100 Years... 100 Movies</i> list; however, the movie dropped off the AFI's 10th anniversary edition of the list in 2007.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amadeus_(film)]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Amadeus Trailer]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/Du-rD2QL1Pc&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Star Trek]]></name>
			<type>book</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[This is a list of the various <i>Star Trek</i> novels, novelisations, short story collections that have been published since 1968. Through this time, three main companies have published <i>Star Trek</i> fiction: Bantam Books (from 1967 to 1981), Ballantine Books (from 1974 to 1978), and since 1979 Pocket Books.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Star_Trek_novels]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
	</info>
	<results>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Immortal Beloved]]></name>
			<type>movie</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b><i>Immortal Beloved</b></i> is a 1994 film about the life of composer Ludwig van Beethoven.<br /><br><b>Historical Background and Content</b><br />The film &mdash; a biopic &mdash; treats the identity of the \"Immortal Beloved\" (<i>Unsterbliche Geliebte</i>) of composer Ludwig Van Beethoven as a mystery to be solved by his secretary and first biographer, Anton Schindler. The search for a solution leads to a journey of discovery which takes Schindler to all corners of the Austrian Empire to interview the women who might have some claim to candidacy. <br />The core of fact upon which the film's speculations are built is as follows:<br />After Beethoven's death in 1827, three short letters were found among his private papers addressed to a woman whom he calls \"immortal beloved\".]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immortal_Beloved_(film)]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Immortal Beloved Trailer]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/a5P5pZFB0fI&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[George Frideric Handel]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>George Frideric Handel</b> (23 February 1685 – 14 April 1759) was an English Baroque composer of German birth who is famous for his operas, oratorios, and concerti grossi. His life and music may justly be described as \"cosmopolitan\": he was born in Germany, trained in Italy, and spent most of his life in England. Born as <b>Georg Friedrich Händel</b> (ˈhɛndəl) in Halle in Saxony-Anhalt, he settled in England in 1712, becoming a naturalized subject of the British crown on 22 January 1727. His works include <i>Messiah</i>, <i>Water Music</i>, and <i>Music for the Royal Fireworks</i>.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Frideric_Handel]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[George Frideric Handel - Messiah &quot;Hallelujah!&quot;]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/3uOabPZScQs&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Franz Schubert]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Franz Peter Schubert</b> (January 31, 1797 – November 19, 1828) was an Austrian composer. He wrote some 600 lieder, nine symphonies (including the famous \"Unfinished Symphony\"), liturgical music, operas, and a large body of chamber and solo piano music. He is particularly noted for his original melodic and harmonic writing.<br />Schubert was born into a musical family, and received formal musical training through much of his childhood.<br />While Schubert had a close circle of friends and associates who admired his work (amongst them the prominent singer Johann Michael Vogl), wide appreciation of his music during his lifetime was limited at best.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Schubert]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Franz Schubert - Piano Sonata D. 960 part 1-1]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/BkH0cPzg-IU&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Joseph Haydn]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>(Franz) Joseph Haydn</b> (March 31 1732 &ndash; May 31 1809) was an Austrian composer. He was one of the most prominent composers of the classical period, and is called by some the \"Father of the Symphony\" and \"Father of the String Quartet\". <br />A life-long citizen of Austria, Haydn spent much of his career as a court musician for the wealthy Hungarian Esterházy family on their remote estate. Isolated from other composers and trends in music until the later part of his long life, he was, as he put it, \"forced to become original\".<br />During his lifetime, the composer was always known as <b>Joseph Haydn</b>. The form \"Franz Joseph Haydn\" is avoided by modern scholars and historians.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Haydn]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Joseph Haydn - Piano Sonata in Eb]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/Vkse1g9ibnM&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Claudio Monteverdi]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Claudio Giovanni Antonio Monteverdi</b> (May 15, 1567 (baptized) &ndash; November 29, 1643), was an Italian composer, gambist, and singer.<br />Monteverdi's work, often regarded as revolutionary, marked the transition from the Renaissance style of music to that of the Baroque period. He developed two individual styles of composition: the new basso continuo technique of the Baroque and the heritage of Renaissance polyphony. Enjoying fame in his lifetime, he wrote one of the earliest operas, <i>L'Orfeo</i>, which is still regularly performed. <br /><br><b>Life</b><br />Claudio Monteverdi was born in 1567 in Cremona, a town in Northern Italy, to Baldassare Monteverdi, a doctor, apothecary and surgeon. He was the oldest of five children.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claudio_Monteverdi]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Claudio Monteverdi - Cantate Domino]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/YF5IL_m_-uU&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</b> (ˈvɔlfgaŋ amaˈdeus ˈmoːtsart, full name <b>Johann Chrysostom Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</b> (27 January 1756&nbsp;– 5 December 1791), was a prolific and influential composer of the Classical era. He composed over six hundred works, many acknowledged as pinnacles of symphonic, concertante, chamber, piano, operatic, and choral music; and he is among the most enduringly popular of classical composers.<br />Mozart showed prodigious ability from his earliest childhood in Salzburg.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfgang_Amadeus_Mozart]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart - Piano Concerto No. 21 - Andante]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/df-eLzao63I&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Henry Purcell]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Arcangelo Corelli]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Arcangelo Corelli</b> (February 17, 1653 &ndash; January 8, 1713) was an Italian violinist and composer of Baroque music. <br /><br><b>Biography</b><br />Arcangelo Corelli was born at Fusignano, Romagna, in the current-day province of Ravenna. Little is known about his early life. His master on the violin was Giovanni Battista Bassani. Matteo Simonelli, the well-known singer of the pope’s chapel, taught him composition. <br />His first major success was gained in Paris at the age of nineteen, and to this he owed his European reputation. From Paris, Corelli went to Germany.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arcangelo_Corelli]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Arcangelo Corelli - Concerto no. 8 in sol minore]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/BR6Swn4TfDs&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Johannes Brahms]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Johannes Brahms</b> (pronounced [joːˈhanəs ˈbʁaːms]) (May 7, 1833 &ndash; April 3, 1897), composer and pianist, was one of the leading musicians of the Romantic period. Born in Hamburg, Brahms spent much of his professional life in Vienna, Austria, where he was a leader of the musical scene. In his lifetime, Brahms's popularity and influence were considerable; following a comment by the nineteenth century conductor Hans von Bülow, he is sometimes grouped with Johann Sebastian Bach and Ludwig van Beethoven as one of the Three Bs.<br />Brahms composed for piano, for chamber ensembles, for symphony orchestra, and for voice and chorus.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Brahms]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Johannes Brahms- Waltz]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/TJcoaIeH3GI&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Händel]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Star Wars]]></name>
			<type>book</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Felix Mendelssohn]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Jakob Ludwig Felix Mendelssohn Bartholdy</b>, born, and generally known in English-speaking countries, as <b>Felix Mendelssohn</b> (February 3, 1809 &ndash; November 4, 1847) was a German composer, pianist, organist and conductor of the early Romantic period. <br />The grandson of the philosopher Moses Mendelssohn, he was born to a notable Jewish family which later converted to Christianity. He was recognised early as a prodigy, but his parents were cautious and did not seek to capitalise on his abilities. Indeed his father was disinclined to allow Felix to follow a musical career until it became clear that he intended to seriously dedicate himself to it.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felix_Mendelssohn]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Songs Without Words Op19 1 Felix Mendelssohn]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/kYEggRrIH50&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Palestrina]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Antonio Vivaldi]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Antonio Lucio Vivaldi</b> (March 4, 1678 – July 28, 1741), nicknamed <i>il Prete Rosso</i> (\"The Red Priest\"), was a Baroque music composer and Venetian priest, as well as a famous virtuoso violinist, born and raised in the Republic of Venice. <i>The Four Seasons</i>, a series of four violin concerti, is his best-known work and a highly popular Baroque piece.<br /><br><b>Biography</b><br /><br><b>Childhood</b><br />Antonio Lucio Vivaldi was born in Venice, the capital of the Republic of Venice. He was baptized immediately after his birth at his home by the midwife. It is not known how the life of the infant was in danger, but the immediate baptism was most likely due to his poor health or to an earthquake that shook the city that day.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_Vivaldi]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Antonio Vivaldi, Mandolin Concerto, 1st Movement]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/StNAG4gCIxY&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Ludwig Van Beethoven]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Farinelli]]></name>
			<type>movie</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Farinelli (trailer)]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/OOUXSe3fQgk&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Niccolò Paganini]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Gustav Mahler]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Gustav Mahler</b> (7 July 1860 &ndash; 18 May 1911) was a Bohemian-born Austrian composer and conductor. He was best known during his own lifetime as one of the leading orchestral and operatic conductors of the day. He has since come to be acknowledged as among the most important late-Romantic composers, although his music was never completely accepted by the musical establishment of Vienna while he was still alive. Mahler composed primarily symphonies and songs; however, his approach to genre often blurred the lines between orchestral Lied, symphony, and symphonic poem.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustav_Mahler]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Gustav Mahler Symphony no.2 &quot;Resurrection&quot; movement 5 part 1]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/z7sgq-UgWR4&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Doctor Who]]></name>
			<type>book</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[The <b>Doctor</b> is the central character in the long-running BBC television science-fiction series <i>Doctor Who</i>, and also features in a vast range of spin-off novels, audio dramas and comic strips connected to the series.<br />To date, ten actors have officially played the role in the television series (including the 1996 television film), with these changes being explained by his ability to regenerate. Several other actors have played the character on stage and film, in audio dramas, and in occasional special episodes of the series. The character's enduring popularity led the <i>Daily Telegraph</i> to dub him \"Britain's favourite alien\".]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctor_(Doctor_Who)]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Edvard Grieg]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Edvard Grieg</b> (15 June 1843 – 4 September 1907) was a Norwegian composer and pianist who composed in the Romantic period. He is best known for his Piano Concerto in A minor, for his incidental music to Henrik Ibsen's play <i>Peer Gynt</i> (which includes <i>Morning Mood</i> and <i>In the Hall of the Mountain King</i>), and for his collection of piano miniatures <i>Lyric Pieces</i>.<br /><br><b>Biography</b><br />Grieg was born in Bergen, Norway on 15 June 1843. The original family name was spelled Greig. After the Battle of Culloden in 1746, his great-grandfather traveled widely, settling in Norway around 1770, and establishing business interests in Bergen. Grieg was raised in a musical home. His mother, Gesine b.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edvard_Grieg]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[In the Hall of the Mountain King]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/fzyi3C4gNnE&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Giuseppe Verdi]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Giuseppe Fortunino Francesco Verdi</b> ( in Italian; October 9 or 10, 1813 &ndash; January 27, 1901) was an Italian Romantic composer, mainly of opera. He was one of the most influential composers in the 19th century. His works are frequently performed in opera houses throughout the world and, transcending the boundaries of the genre, some of his themes have long since taken root in popular culture - such as \"La donna è mobile\" from <i>Rigoletto</i>, \"Va, pensiero\" (The Chorus of the Hebrew Slaves) from <i>Nabucco</i>, and \"Libiamo ne' lieti calici\" (The Drinking Song) from <i>La traviata</i>.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giuseppe_Verdi]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Giuseppe Verdi Triumphant March]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/xrOrPTf_upQ&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Buxtehude]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Dieterich Buxtehude</b> (<i>Dietrich</i>, <i>Diderich</i>) (c. 1637 &ndash; 9 May 1707) was a German-Danish organist, lutenist and a highly regarded composer of the Baroque period. His organ works comprise a central part of the standard organ repertoire and are frequently performed at recitals and church services. He wrote in a wide variety of vocal and instrumental idioms, and his style strongly influenced many composers, including Johann Sebastian Bach and Gustav Mahler. Buxtehude, along with Heinrich Schütz, is considered today to be the most important German composer of the mid-Baroque.<br /><br><b>Life</b><br /><br><b>Early years in Denmark</b><br />He is thought to have been born with the name Diderich Buxtehude.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dieterich_Buxtehude]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[6. Buxtehude: Membra Jesu Nostri &quot;Ad cor&quot;]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/unI3aKtT64E&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Giacomo Puccini]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Giacomo Antonio Domenico Michele Secondo Maria Puccini</b> (December 22, 1858 &ndash; November 29, 1924) was an Italian composer whose operas, including <i>La bohème</i>, <i>Tosca</i>, <i>Madama Butterfly</i> and <i>Turandot</i>, are among the most frequently performed in the standard repertoire. Some of his arias, such as \"O mio babbino caro\" from <i>Gianni Schicchi</i>, \"Che gelida manina\" from <i>La&nbsp;bohème</i>, and \"Nessun dorma\" from <i>Turandot</i>, have become part of popular culture.<br /><br><b>Early life </b><br />Puccini was born in Lucca in Tuscany, into a family with five generations of musical history behind them, including composer Domenico Puccini.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giacomo_Puccini]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Giacomo Puccini - O mio babbino caro]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/zu5TkdcZA-M&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Albinoni]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Tomaso Giovanni Albinoni</b> (8 June 1671, Venice, Republic of Venice &ndash; 17 January 1751, Venice, Republic of Venice) was a Venetian Baroque composer. While famous in his day as an opera composer, he is mainly remembered today for his instrumental music, some of which is regularly recorded. The \"Adagio in G minor\" attributed to him is a 1958 composition entirely composed by Remo Giazotto, which Giazotto claimed to have based on fragments from a slow movement of an Albinoni trio sonata he had been sent by the Dresden State Library.<br /><br><b>Biography</b><br />Born to Antonio Albinoni, a wealthy paper merchant in Venice, he studied violin and singing.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tomaso_Albinoni]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Adagio in G minor by Albinoni]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/mz4dpbk8YBs&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Gioacchino Rossini]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Gioachino Antonio Rossini</b> (February 29, 1792 &ndash; November 13, 1868) was a popular Italian composer who created 39 operas as well as sacred music and chamber music. His best known works include <i>Il barbiere di Siviglia</i> (<i>The Barber of Seville</i>), <i>La Cenerentola</i> and <i>Guillaume Tell</i> (<i>William Tell</i>). A tendency for inspired, songlike melodies is evident throughout his scores, which led to the nickname \"The Italian Mozart.\" Until his retirement in 1829, Rossini had been the most popular opera composer in history. <i>The Barber of Seville</i> was the first Italian opera ever presented in the United States.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gioachino_Rossini]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Gioacchino Rossini - La Gazza ladra (ouverture)]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/QUj0TnFeXzs&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Frédéric Chopin]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Frédéric Chopin</b> (; ; surname pronunciation in English: ˈʃoʊpæn and French: ʃɔpɛ̃; 1 March 1810 &ndash; 17&nbsp;October 1849) was a Polish composer and virtuoso pianist of the Romantic period. He is widely regarded as one of the world's great composers for piano.<br />Chopin was born in the village of Żelazowa Wola, in the Duchy of Warsaw, to a French-expatriate father and a Polish mother, and in his early life was regarded as a child-prodigy pianist. In November 1830, at the age of twenty, he went abroad; following the suppression of the Polish November Uprising of 1830–1831, he became one of many expatriates of the Polish \"Great Emigration.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fr%C3%A9d%C3%A9ric_Chopin]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Frédéric Chopin - Prelude in E-Minor (op.28 no. 4)]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/ef-4Bv5Ng0w&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Richard Strauss]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Richard Georg Strauss</b> (11 June 1864 &ndash; 8 September 1949) was a German composer of the late Romantic and early modern eras, particularly of operas, Lieder and tone poems. Strauss was also a prominent conductor.<br /><br><b>Life and works</b><br /><br><b>Early life</b><br />Strauss was born on 11 June 1864, in Munich, the son of Franz Strauss, who was the principal horn player at the Court Opera in Munich. He received a thorough, but conservative, musical education from his father in his youth, writing his first music at the age of six. He continued to write music almost until his death.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Strauss]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Richard Strauss - Don Quixote (Fragment)]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/-eGHJAcImL4&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Béla Bartók]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Richard Wagner]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b> Wilhelm Richard Wagner</b> (ˈrɪtʃ.ərd ˈvɑɡ.nər, ˈʁi.çaʁt ˈvaɡ.nɐ; 22 May 1813, Leipzig, Germany &ndash; 13 February 1883, Venice, Italy) was a German composer, conductor, theatre director and essayist, primarily known for his operas (or \"music dramas\", as they were later called). Unlike most other great opera composers, Wagner wrote both the scenario and libretto for his works.<br />Wagner's compositions, particularly those of his later period, are notable for contrapuntal texture, rich chromaticism, harmonies and orchestration, and elaborate use of leitmotifs: musical themes associated with particular characters, locales or plot elements.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Wagner]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Richard Wagner. Tristan - Isolde Prelude]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/IYaGPAD8EiA&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Sergei Prokofiev]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Sergei Sergeyevich Prokofiev</b> (, sʲɪˈrgʲej sʲɪˈrgʲeɪvʲɪtɕ prɐˈkofʲjɪf, <i>Sergéj Sergéjevič Prokófjef</i>) ( - 5 March 1953) was a Russian composer who mastered numerous musical genres and came to be admired as one of the greatest composers of the 20th century. (Alternative transliterations of his name include <i>Sergey</i> or <i>Serge</i>, and <i>Prokofief</i>, <i>Prokofieff</i>, or <i>Prokofyev</i>.)<br /><br><b>Biography</b><br />Prokofiev was born in Sontsovka (now Krasnoye in Donetsk oblast), Ukraine, then part of the Russian Empire. He displayed unusual musical abilities by the age of five.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sergei_Prokofiev]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Dragon Lance]]></name>
			<type>book</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Igor Stravinsky]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Igor Fyodorovich Stravinsky</b> (, ) ( &ndash; 6 April 1971) was a Russian-born composer, considered by many to be the most influential composer of 20th century music. He was a quintessentially cosmopolitan Russian who was named by <i>Time</i> magazine as one of the 100 most influential people of the century. In addition to the recognition he received for his compositions, he also achieved fame as a pianist and a conductor, often at the premieres of his works.<br />Stravinsky's compositional career was notable for its stylistic diversity.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igor_Stravinsky]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Georges Bizet]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Georges Bizet</b> (25 October 1838 – 3 June 1875) was a French composer and pianist of the Romantic era. He is best known for the opera <i>Carmen</i>.<br /><br><b>Biography</b><br />Bizet was born at 28 rue de la Tour d'Auvergne in the 9th arrondissement of Paris in 1838. He was registered with the legal name <b>Alexandre César Léopold Bizet</b>, but he was baptised on 16 March 1840 with the first name Georges, and he was always known thereafter as <b>Georges Bizet</b>. His father Adolphe Armand Bizet (1810-86) was an amateur singer and composer, and his mother, Aimée Léopoldine Joséphine née Delsarte (1814-61), was the sister of the famous singing teacher François Delsarte. <br />He entered the Paris Conservatory of Music in 1848, a fortnight before his tenth birthday.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georges_Bizet]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Georges Bizet - Carmen - Habanera]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/xlGTz0pSLS8&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Sergei Rachmaninoff]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Sergei Rachmaninoff plays his Piano Concerto No. 2]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/x8l37utZxMQ&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Hector Berlioz]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Louis Hector Berlioz</b> (December 11, 1803 &ndash; March 8, 1869) was a French Romantic composer and guitarist, best known for his compositions <i>Symphonie fantastique</i> and <i>Grande Messe des morts (Requiem).</i> Berlioz made great contributions to the modern orchestra with his <i>Treatise on Instrumentation</i> and by utilizing huge orchestral forces for his works; as a conductor, he performed several concerts with over 1,000 musicians. At the other extreme, he also composed around 50 songs for voice and guitar. <br /><br><b>Biography</b><br /><br><b>Early years</b><br />Berlioz was born in France at La Côte-Saint-André in the <i>département</i> of Isère, near Lyon.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hector_Berlioz]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[John Axelrod conducts Symphony Fantastique by Hector Berlioz]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/B8p1aTIT21M&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Franz Liszt]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Franz Liszt</b> (; ) (October 22, 1811 &ndash; July 31, 1886) was a Hungarian composer, virtuoso pianist and teacher.<br />Liszt became renowned throughout Europe for his great skill as a performer during the 19th century. He is said to have been the most technically advanced and perhaps greatest pianist of all time. He was also an important and influential composer, a notable piano teacher, a conductor who contributed significantly to the modern development of the art, and a benefactor to other composers and performers, notably Richard Wagner, Hector Berlioz, Camille Saint-Saëns, Edvard Grieg and Alexander Borodin.<br />As a composer, Liszt was one of the most prominent representatives of the \"Neudeutsche Schule\" (\"New German School\").]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Liszt]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Evgeny Kissin plays Franz Liszt - Liebestraum]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/-kKoHqdImYE&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Maurice Ravel]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[<b>Joseph-Maurice Ravel</b> (March 7, 1875 &ndash; December 28, 1937) was a French composer and pianist of Impressionist music known especially for the subtlety, richness, and poignancy of his melodies, orchestral and instrumental textures and effects. Much of his piano music, chamber music, vocal music and orchestral music have become staples of the concert repertoire. <br />Ravel's piano compositions, such as <i>Jeux d'eau</i>, <i>Miroirs</i> and <i>Gaspard de la Nuit</i>, demand considerable virtuosity from the performer, and his orchestral music, including <i>Daphnis et Chloé</i> and his arrangement of Modest Mussorgsky's <i>Pictures at an Exhibition</i>, uses tonal color and variety of sound and instrumentation very effectively.]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_Ravel]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[Maurice Ravel - Bolero - Herbert von Karajan 1985 - Part I]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[http://www.youtube.com/v/b3J2_EOHBI4&f=videos&c=TasteKid&app=youtube_gdata]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Couperin]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
		<resource>
			<name><![CDATA[Telemann]]></name>
			<type>music</type>
						<wTeaser><![CDATA[]]></wTeaser>
			<wUrl><![CDATA[]]></wUrl>
			<yTitle><![CDATA[]]></yTitle>
			<yUrl><![CDATA[]]></yUrl>
					</resource>
	</results>
</similar>
