<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE corpus SYSTEM
  "lexical-sample.dtd">
  <corpus lang='english'>

    <lexelt item="art.n">

<instance id="art.40003" docsrc="bnc_A04_1181">
<context>
Whatever flickerings of potential this young tyro possesses, they cannot cover up the fact that he is a painter with the imagination of a retarded adolescent; no technical mastery; no intuitive feeling for pictorial space; no sensitivity towards, or grasp of, tradition; and a colour sense rather less than that of Congo, the chimpanzee who was taught (among other things) a crude responsiveness to colour harmonies by Desmond Morris in the late 1950s.
However, potentially educable as a painter Schnabel may or may not be, his work is just not worthy of serious attention by anyone with a developed taste in this particular art form. [/p] [/quote] [/p] [p]
Readers need also to be wary of the existence of special markets.
The explosive prices for Teddy Bears in the last few years indicate how a [pb] market can be created, in this case by a mix of merit and nostalgia.
What is clearly a dealers' market is often signalled by the invention of a brand name to group together a variety of material, perhaps rather disparate.
Pop <head>Art</head>is an example.
</context>
</instance>

<instance id="art.40006" docsrc="bnc_AM9_797">
<context>
Special provisions will also ensure that those on modest incomes most of which comes from investments, such as people who have been made redundant, do not pay this 9% on their savings. [/item] [/list] [/item] [/list] [/p] [/div2] [div2] [head]
Widening horizons: investing in the arts [/head] [p]
The arts benefit society in two ways.
First, access to the arts is intrinsic to a high quality of life.
Second, the cultural sector &mdash; the arts, crafts, design, and audiovisual industries &mdash; makes as great a net contribution to the economy as does the oil industry.
We will: [list] [item]
[hi]Create a new Ministry of Arts and Communications [/hi] headed by a minister in the Cabinet.
Liberal Democrats will raise investment in the arts to the EC average over five years. [/item] [item]
[hi]Reform and decentralise <head>arts</head>funding and organisation [/hi].
</context>
</instance>

<instance id="art.40010" docsrc="bnc_AHA_533">
<context>
It is fair to say that nothing Frank has achieved as a film-maker approaches the heights he scaled with The Americans. [/p] [p]
The 50-minute film he made for Arena suggests why: Last Supper &mdash; Frank on Frank looks like a parody of the excesses of Sixties avant-garde film-making.
On an empty lot between two Harlem streets, a group of people arrive for an outdoor party to celebrate the new publication of an unnamed author.
Initially they make respectful small-talk about him, but their comments grow increasingly resentful as it becomes apparent he will not show up. [/p] [p]
Some events in Last Supper appear roughly improvised.
Yet hefty chunks of dialogue are obviously &mdash; and rather archly &mdash; staged.
People say things like: &bquo;You ever notice how all <head>art</head>focuses on people in trouble?&equo;
</context>
</instance>

<instance id="art.40013" docsrc="bnc_CDT_516">
<context>
Therefore if we carry ourselves with pride, our self-esteem increases and others will notice. [/p] [p]
If someone does come looking for trouble, he or she will pick a victim who does not look capable of causing any real problem.
We need to make it clear by the way we stand and hold a gaze, and by the way we speak, that we cannot be so easily dismissed.
In fact we have to show that we are prepared, if necessary, to do whatever it takes to survive.
I'm not talking about aggression, but about asserting ourselves &mdash; firmly and resolutely.
We can still give our opponent the chance to back off, we can still use reason, but he or she must realize that the wrong person has been picked for breakfast.
He may win, but at what price?
Countless books and classes teach the <head>art</head>of asserting oneself and, if you want to know more, turn to page 120. [/p] [div2] [head]
</context>
</instance>

<instance id="art.40016" docsrc="bnc_CE4_431">
<context>
Naturally, the brighter the white, the more it will suit pictures with a modern style, so consider choosing at least [gap] [ptr][pb] an off-white, if not a cream, for pictures with an antique flavour.
However, as a general rule you cannot go wrong with the basic colours, and if you are in any doubt don't try to use a complicated mix of colours and textures.
Instead, keep your background uncluttered, for it's the simple pictures that often work the best. [/p] [caption]
Facing page: A selection of blue and pink fabrics for backings.
Below: Some backing fabrics in autumnal shades. [/caption] [p]
Although most people are aware of the tremendous selection of fabrics on the market, not everyone knows of the vast range of papers that are currently available.
Forsake your usual stationer, who probably won't have the room or the reason for stocking unusual papers or cards, and go to a specialist <head>art</head>or paper shop instead. [/p] [p]
</context>
</instance>

</lexelt>
</corpus>
