<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text>
<p id="1">
 <s id="s1.1">Statement of Government Policy by the Prime Minister, Mr Ingvar Carlsson, at the Opening of the Swedish Parliament on Tuesday, 4 October, 1988.</s>
</p>

<p id="2">
 <s id="s2.1">Your Majesties, Your Royal Highnesses, Mr Speaker, Members of the Swedish Parliament.</s>
</p>

<p id="3">
 <s id="s3.1">Sweden's policy of neutrality is of decisive importance for our peace and independence.</s> 
 <s id="s3.2">It also contributes to stability and détente in our part of the world.</s> 
 <s id="s3.3">There is wide popular support for this policy.</s> 
 <s id="s3.4">It will be pursued with firmness and consistency.</s>
</p>

<p id="4">
 <s id="s4.1">Our policy of neutrality is underpinned by a strong defence.</s> 
 <s id="s4.2">That safeguards our independence.</s> 
 <s id="s4.3">Violations of Swedish territory will never be accepted.</s> 
 <s id="s4.4">The army will be reorganized with the aim of making it more effective.</s> 
 <s id="s4.5">It is the Government's intention to seek broad solutions in issues that are of importance for our national security.</s>
</p>

<p id="5">
 <s id="s5.1">The Government welcomed the agreement between the United States and the Soviet Union on the elimination of land-based intermediate-range nuclear weapons.</s> 
 <s id="s5.2">Efforts must now, among other things, aim at reducing strategic arms and bringing about a comprehensive test ban treaty.</s> 
 <s id="s5.3">Sweden is acting in support of this inter alia within the framework of the Six Nation Initiative.</s>
</p>

<p id="6">
 <s id="s6.1">The Government will continue its active efforts on behalf of a nuclear-weapon-free zone in the Nordic area and of a corridor in Central Europe free of battlefield nuclear weapons.</s>
</p>

<p id="7">
 <s id="s7.1">By supporting economic and social progress in developing countries the Government wishes to contribute to reversing the economic decline in the poor countries and to alleviating the debt crisis.</s> 
 <s id="s7.2">Development assistance shall furthermore promote a sustainable use of natural resources and protection of the environment.</s>
</p>

<p id="8">
 <s id="s8.1">The Government will actively promote the convening in 1992 of a global United Nations conference on the environment and development.</s>
</p>

<p id="9">
 <s id="s9.1">In Central America the five Presidents have signed a peace plan which Sweden has given its wholehearted support.</s> 
 <s id="s9.2">Negotiations are in progress on peace between Iran and Iraq.</s> 
 <s id="s9.3">The Soviet troops are in the process of withdrawing from Afghanistan.</s>
</p>

<p id="10">
 <s id="s10.1">In the majority of the regional conflicts the United Nations has been able to make important contributions.</s> 
 <s id="s10.2">Sweden is participating in, among other things, the United Nations Military Observer Groups in Afghanistan and in Iran/Iraq.</s>
</p>

<p id="11">
 <s id="s11.1">We were pleased to learn that the Nobel Peace Prize is being awarded this year to the United Nations peace-keeping forces.</s> 
 <s id="s11.2">Sweden has participated in practically all the United Nations operations of this kind.</s> 
 <s id="s11.3">It is also an honour for Sweden that the Secretary-General, in consultation with the parties, has appointed our United Nations Ambassador to be his personal representative at the peace negotiations between Iran and Iraq.</s>
</p>

<p id="12">
 <s id="s12.1">The degrading apartheid system in South Africa must be abolished.</s> 
 <s id="s12.2">A decision by the United Nations Security Council on mandatory sanctions against South Africa would be the most effective measure to this end.</s>
</p>

<p id="13">
 <s id="s13.1">The conflict in the Middle East is among the most difficult to solve.</s> 
 <s id="s13.2">The Government actively supports the endeavours to convene an international peace conference under the auspices of the United Nations.</s>
</p>

<p id="14">
 <s id="s14.1">Sweden is dependent on free exchanges of goods and services across national boundaries.</s> 
 <s id="s14.2">We are setting the pace in the current negotiations to strengthen free trade.</s>
</p>

<p id="15">
 <s id="s15.1">Within the framework of EFTA and in collaboration with the other EFTA countries, the Government will intensify co-operation wit the EC in all fields to the extent it is compatible with our policy of neutrality.</s> 
 <s id="s15.2">Nordic co-operation will also be developed.</s> 
 <s id="s15.3">In this context, the requirements of full employment, welfare, a good working environment and trade union participation will be key issues.</s> 
 <s id="s15.4">Opportunities for study, work and cultural exchanges across national boundaries will be extended.</s>
</p>

<p id="16">
 <s id="s16.1">The Government intends to uphold and strengthen the rule of law in several ways.</s>
</p>

<p id="17">
 <s id="s17.1">The possibilities for courts and public prosecution authorities to carry out their important work will be improved.</s>
</p>

<p id="18">
 <s id="s18.1">The Government will put forward proposals for developing police work and making it more effective.</s>
</p>

<p id="19">
 <s id="s19.1">A proposal for a lower legal limit for the offence of driving with ability impaired by alcohol will be submitted to Parliament.</s>
</p>

<p id="20">
 <s id="s20.1">Crime prevention work at the local level is to be encouraged.</s> 
 <s id="s20.2">The fight against violence and economic crime will be given priority.</s>
</p>

<p id="21">
 <s id="s21.1">The treatment of offenders must be administered in such a way that prison escapes are prevented.</s> 
 <s id="s21.2">At the same time the term in prison and non-institutional care must facilitate rehabilitation after discharge.</s>
</p>

<p id="22">
 <s id="s22.1">The goal of our economic policy is full employment and greater prosperity for the whole nation.</s>
</p>

<p id="23">
 <s id="s23.1">The rate of inflation is too high and must be reduced.</s> 
 <s id="s23.2">Our budget policy must therefore continue to be tight and strong government finances maintained.</s> 
 <s id="s23.3">Costly reforms will only be carried through to the extent allowed by economic growth, reappraisal of expenditure and by rationalizations in the public sector.</s>
</p>

<p id="24">
 <s id="s24.1">A shortage of labour and low savings restrict growth and push up prices and costs.</s> 
 <s id="s24.2">Special measures will therefore be taken in order to encourage saving and make better use of people's desire to work.</s> 
 <s id="s24.3">Proposals will be put forward for increasing competition and keeping down costs in areas where price trends are boosting inflation.</s>
</p>

<p id="25">
 <s id="s25.1">A reduction of the marginal income-tax rate in 1989 by 3 percentage points will be proposed in the first place for full-time employees.</s>
</p>

<p id="26">
 <s id="s26.1">Later in the electoral period, proposals will be put forward for an extensive reform of the tax system.</s> 
 <s id="s26.2">The aim is to stimulate work and saving.</s> 
 <s id="s26.3">State income-tax will be reduced and capital taxes increased.</s> 
 <s id="s26.4">The tax system will be simplified and tax avoidance counteracted.</s> 
 <s id="s26.5">Company taxation will be reformed in the direction of lower rates of tax and broader tax bases.</s> 
 <s id="s26.6">Indirect taxation is to be reformed too.</s>
</p>

<p id="27">
 <s id="s27.1">In order further to increase employment and meet the shortage of labour the Government will develop its active labour market policy.</s> 
 <s id="s27.2">Recurrent training in working life and qualified further education will play an important role in this context.</s> 
 <s id="s27.3">Opportunities for the disabled to participate in working life must be further improved.</s> 
 <s id="s27.4">Immigrants' entry into the labour market should be facilitated.</s>
</p>

<p id="28">
 <s id="s28.1">Working life is to be made more secure and just.</s>
</p>

<p id="29">
 <s id="s29.1">The Government will invite the organizations in the labour market and the relevant authorities to participate in a commission on the working environment to make special efforts for the 400,000 workplaces most exposed to hazards.</s> 
 <s id="s29.2">The commission is to submit proposals for measures that will result in healthier working environments, and which will reduce the many work injuries.</s>
</p>

<p id="30">
 <s id="s30.1">During this electoral period, legislation on a sixth week of annual holiday with pay will be enacted.</s> 
 <s id="s30.2">This reform will be carried through in stages.</s>
</p>

<p id="31">
 <s id="s31.1">It is essential that the work of breaking down the barriers on the labour market for more flexible choices by both sexes be continued.</s> 
 <s id="s31.2">It must be made easier for men and women to combine gainful employment and parental responsibility.</s> 
 <s id="s31.3">Further measures will be taken to increase the number of women in various decision-making assemblies.</s>
</p>

<p id="32">
 <s id="s32.1">The broadening of regional policy that has taken place in recent years in the direction of higher competence, education and an enhanced infrastructure, will continue.</s>
</p>

<p id="33">
 <s id="s33.1">Small companies are responsible for much of the dynamics and renewal in Swedish industry and commerce.</s> 
 <s id="s33.2">We will therefore continue our efforts to create favourable development opportunities for small companies.</s>
</p>

<p id="34">
 <s id="s34.1">Our generous policy in solidarity with refugees stands firm.</s> 
 <s id="s34.2">The United Nations efforts for the worlds' refugees will be given continued strong support.</s> 
 <s id="s34.3">Racism and xenophobia will be forcefully combated.</s>
</p>

<p id="35">
 <s id="s35.1">Proposals will be submitted to Parliament for a new Aliens Act.</s> 
 <s id="s35.2">The administration of matters relating to aliens will be speeded up considerably.</s>
</p>

<p id="36">
 <s id="s36.1">Consideration for the environment and the countryside must characterize developments in all fields.</s> 
 <s id="s36.2">Parliament's decision on traffic policy is of great importance in this context.</s>
</p>

<p id="37">
 <s id="s37.1">A radical environmental policy presupposes a strong economy.</s> 
 <s id="s37.2">Efforts are being further pursued to reach agreements across boundaries on reduced air and water pollution and on protection of the earth's climate.</s> 
 <s id="s37.3">The plan for phasing out CFCs is being fulfilled.</s>
</p>

<p id="38">
 <s id="s38.1">Industrial products and processes are to be cleaner through stringent requirements and rapid adaptation to new technology.</s> 
 <s id="s38.2">Permits granted will be re-examined.</s> 
 <s id="s38.3">Requirements imposed on environmentally hazardous products, chemicals and on waste disposal management will be tightened.</s> 
 <s id="s38.4">Preliminary inspection of new chemical substances will be introduced.</s>
</p>

<p id="39">
 <s id="s39.1">Pollution charges for chlorine organics and sulphur will be introduced as early as 1989.</s> 
 <s id="s39.2">Proposals for pollution charges for other substances, among them carbon dioxide, will be presented during this term of office.</s>
</p>

<p id="40">
 <s id="s40.1">All legislation pertaining to the environment will be reviewed and co-ordinated.</s> 
 <s id="s40.2">Proposals for a new Nature Conservation Act as also further tightening of the Environment Protection Act will be presented during the life of this Parliament.</s>
</p>

<p id="41">
 <s id="s41.1">The organization of environmental protection will be given substantially increased resources.</s> 
 <s id="s41.2">Special measures will be applied in regions particularly exposed, for example west Skåne and the Sundsvall/Timrå area.</s>
</p>

<p id="42">
 <s id="s42.1">In the near future the Government will invite representatives of the three big cities to take part in discussions on how the environment of these cities is to be improved.</s>
</p>

<p id="43">
 <s id="s43.1">In 1990 a proposal will be submitted to Parliament on the two reactors at the Barsebäck and Ringhals nuclear power stations that are to be taken out of service in 1995 and 1996.</s> 
 <s id="s43.2">The energy system will be modified such that acidification is reduced and climatic effects counteracted.</s>
</p>

<p id="44">
 <s id="s44.1">The Government's agricultural policy aims to promote farming that thrives without having damaging effects on the environment.</s> 
 <s id="s44.2">There must be a move from today's intensive production to farming that better meets the requirements in respect of the environment and regional distribution.</s> 
 <s id="s44.3">Alternative methods of farming will be stimulated.</s> 
 <s id="s44.4">Measures will be taken to protect the visual amenity of the open landscape.</s>
</p>

<p id="45">
 <s id="s45.1">International developments will require changes in agricultural subsidies to forms implying less protectionism.</s> 
 <s id="s45.2">The Government intends to pursue a food policy such that the price trend is checked and the consumers offered food at reasonable prices.</s> 
 <s id="s45.3">Food controls will be tightened.</s>
</p>

<p id="46">
 <s id="s46.1">The public sector will be renewed in order to provide better service to people according to their needs and wishes.</s> 
 <s id="s46.2">Service and freedom of choice will be augmented.</s> 
 <s id="s46.3">Efficiency is to be promoted, by, among other things, allowing greater scope for employees' power of initiative.</s>
</p>

<p id="47">
 <s id="s47.1">Parental insurance will be extended from nine to eighteen months with payment according to the "loss of earnings" principle.</s> 
 <s id="s47.2">The extension will be completed by 1991.</s> 
 <s id="s47.3">The first stage, which enters into force on 1 July 1989, means payment for a further three months.</s>
</p>

<p id="48">
 <s id="s48.1">The extension of child care services will continue in accordance with Parliament's decision.</s>
</p>

<p id="49">
 <s id="s49.1">Through the extra increase of the base amount as of 1 January 1989, pensioners will receive full compensation for the 1982 devaluation.</s>
</p>

<p id="50">
 <s id="s50.1">The Government intends through, among other things, the work of the National Health Policy Commission to devote considerable attention to the provision of a universal right to high quality health and medical service.</s> 
 <s id="s50.2">Staff recruitment within the caring services must be improved.</s>
</p>

<p id="51">
 <s id="s51.1">The situation for severely disabled persons and for disabled children and their families will be given special attention.</s>
</p>

<p id="52">
 <s id="s52.1">Care of the elderly will be extended with the aim of creating security, independence and freedom of choice.</s>
</p>

<p id="53">
 <s id="s53.1">The fight against HIV and AIDS will continue as also the fight against drugs.</s>
</p>

<p id="54">
 <s id="s54.1">The Government bill on the nine-year compulsory school is now available for consideration.</s> 
 <s id="s54.2">The upper secondary school will be reformed.</s> 
 <s id="s54.3">This means changes in both the vocational and theoretical course programmes.</s> 
 <s id="s54.4">Places in the upper secondary school will be available to all young people under the age of 20.</s>
</p>

<p id="55">
 <s id="s55.1">There will be improved co-ordination of adult education, labour market training and personnel training.</s>
</p>

<p id="56">
 <s id="s56.1">The efforts to achieve increased equality and a more even social composition in all study paths will be intensified.</s> 
 <s id="s56.2">In this context, particular attention will be paid to the situation of young immigrants.</s>
</p>

<p id="57">
 <s id="s57.1">International co-operation within research and development is becoming increasingly important.</s> 
 <s id="s57.2">The Government will continue its efforts to create good opportunities for Swedish industry and Swedish researchers to participate in international research co-operation.</s>
</p>

<p id="58">
 <s id="s58.1">During the coming electoral period, SEK 300 million will be earmarked for the renewal and development of cultural life.</s> 
 <s id="s58.2">Children and young people will be given increased opportunities of encountering and themselves practising music, dancing, singing, literature, theatre and other artistic activities.</s> 
 <s id="s58.3">The conditions of professionals in the arts sector will be improved.</s> 
 <s id="s58.4">Cultural life in the whole country will be strengthened.</s>
</p>

<p id="59">
 <s id="s59.1">The popular movements, not least youth organizations and the sports movement, carry out valuable work which will be supported and facilitated.</s>
</p>

<p id="60">
 <s id="s60.1">A sufficient number of dwellings to meet housing needs are to be constructed.</s> 
 <s id="s60.2">Efforts to produce more housing for young people will be intensified.</s> 
 <s id="s60.3">Resources will be set free for the provision of housing by limiting other construction projects in overheated regions.</s> 
 <s id="s60.4">Further measures to curb cost trends will be taken.</s>
</p>

<p id="61">
 <s id="s61.1">The policies we pursue in the next three years will leave their mark on developments in this country during the decade to come.</s> 
 <s id="s61.2">And in the next few years we will have to face challenges with consequences for the next century.</s>
</p>

<p id="62">
 <s id="s62.1">On the threshold of the nineties, we should confirm and strengthen in the long term what must be the basis for future developments too: the economy, full employment and welfare.</s>
</p>

<p id="63">
 <s id="s63.1">We will then also create the scope for action for the renewal and the new efforts which are required in a number of important areas: within environmental and energy policy, in the public sector, in working life, in the area of taxation, and in order to strengthen our co-operation - economic, social and cultural - with other countries.</s>
</p>

<p id="64">
 <s id="s64.1">The preconditions for this the aim and direction of our policy are favourable.</s>
</p>

<p id="65">
 <s id="s65.1">International developments give hope of further steps towards peace, freedom and increased understanding between nations and peoples.</s>
</p>

<p id="66">
 <s id="s66.1">Sweden's economic situation has improved substantially in recent years.</s> 
 <s id="s66.2">The level of employment in this country is high.</s> 
 <s id="s66.3">The welfare state enjoys wide popular support.</s>
</p>

<p id="67">
 <s id="s67.1">There is broad political consensus and support for tackling the environmental problems forcefully.</s>
</p>

<p id="68">
 <s id="s68.1">We have good reason to feel optimistic when looking to the future.</s>
</p>

<p id="69">
 <s id="s69.1">But there is also reason to remind ourselves of how quickly a favourable development can be turned into the direct opposite.</s> 
 <s id="s69.2">This was the case in the 1970s when the Swedish economy was hit by the severest crisis since the 1930s.</s> 
 <s id="s69.3">The tasks we have ahead of us, and the danger of rapid dramatic changes, mean that responsibility, and the ability to take political action and to co-operate will be required in the future too.</s>
</p>

<p id="70">
 <s id="s70.1">For the first time in 70 years a new party is now entering Parliament.</s> 
 <s id="s70.2">I should like to welcome the members of the Environment Party the Greens to what I hope will be inspiring parliamentary work.</s>
</p>

<p id="71">
 <s id="s71.1">We all bear a joint responsibility to make the three coming years good ones for this country and all its inhabitants, for the environment, for our relations with other countries and for our own daily contacts and relations with other people no matter where we have our roots.</s>
</p>

<p id="72">
 <s id="s72.1">It is the Government's resposibility and aim to put to use all good initiatives, to work for broad solutions and to pursue a policy in the interests of the whole nation.</s>
</p></text>
