<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<facts>
    <head/>
    <list xml:id="buffy_facts" title="Buffy Facts">
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Buffy will always find a wooden stake to slay vampires,
                        even if it means she will have travelled 100 years back
                        in time, to plant a tree nearby.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        באפי תמיד תמצא יתד מעץ כדי לקטול את הערפדים, גם אם זה
                        כרוך בכך שהיא יותר מאוחר תחזור אחורה 100 שנה בזמן, כדי
                        לנטוע עץ בקרבת מקום.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Buffy Summers does not really need stakes to slay
                        vampires, because her kisses are deadly for them. And
                        that includes the ones that she blows in the air.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        באפי סאמרס לא ממש צריכה יתדות כדי לקטול ערפדים, מפני
                        שהנשיקות שלה הן קטלניות עבורם כשלעצמן. וזה כולל את
                        הנשיקות שהיא מפריחה באוויר.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The Chuck Norris of the Buffyverse, has been secretly
                        training under Buffy’s supervision, and so far - lost
                        every battle with her.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        הצ'אק נוריס של העולם של באפי, נוהג להתאמן בסתר תחת
                        השגחתה של באפי, ונכון לעכשיו - הפסיד בכל הקרבות איתה.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Buffy is so hot, that you would totally love to fight
                        her. And lose.  (<b>Dan Dascalescu</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        באפי היא כל כך שווה, שאתה בטוח תשמח להילחם בה. ולהפסיד.
                        (מאת דן דסכלסכו.)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Buffy Summers is not afraid of demons. Demons are
                        afraid of her, and for a very good reason.  (inspired
                        by <b>Dov Levenglick</b> via me).
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        באפי סאמרס לא מפחדת משדים. שדים מפחדים ממנה, ומסיבה
                        טובה מאוד. (בהשראתו של דוב לבנג'ליק.)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Medusa’s gaze can turn people into stone. Buffy’s gaze
                        can turn Medusa into stone.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אם אדם יסתכל במדוזה, הוא יהפך לאבן. אם מדוזה תסתכל
                        בבאפי, היא תהפך לאבן.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
    </list>
    <list xml:id="chuck_facts" title="Chuck Norris Facts">
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris wrote a complete Perl 6 implementation in
                        a day, but then destroyed all evidence with his bare
                        hands, so no-one will know his secrets.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס כתב מימוש מלא של פרל 6 ביום, אבל אז השמיד כל
                        זכר לכך בידיו הריקות, כדי שאיש לא יידע את סודותיו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris refactors 10 million lines of Perl code
                        before lunch.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס משפץ 10 מיליון שורות של קוד פרל לפני ארוחת
                        הצהריים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris is his own boss. If you hire him, he’ll
                        tell your boss what to do.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס הוא הבוס של עצמו. אם תשכור אותו, הוא יאמר
                        לבוס שלך מה לעשות.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris read the entire English Wikipedia in 24
                        hours. Twice.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                Actually, he wrote it in 24 hours. Twice. The
                                first time longhand in blood.  The second time
                                he typed it in from memory (<b>Drew
                                    Roberts</b>).
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס קרא את כל הוויקיפדיה האנגלית ב-24 שעות.
                        פעמיים.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                למעשה, הוא כתב אותה ב-24 שעות. פעמיים. בפעם
                                הראשונה בזרוע ארוכה בדם.  בפעם השנייה הוא הקליד
                                אותה מזכרונו (<b>דרו רוברטס (Drew
                                    Roberts)</b>).
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris does not code; when he sits at a computer,
                        it just does whatever he wants. (<b>Kattana</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס אינו מקודד; כשהוא יושב ליד המחשב, המחשב עושה
                        כל מה שהוא רוצה. (<b>Kattana - קאטאנה</b>).
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris commits with a roundhouse kick into the
                        SVN server’s head. (<b>daxim</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris <b>is</b> the test suite.
                        (<b>FurnaceBoy</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris doesn’t make mistakes.  (<a
                            href="http://sushee.schreibsturm.org/"><b>Su-Shee</b></a>)
                        He corrects God.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס אינו טועה ( <a
                            href="http://sushee.schreibsturm.org/"><b>Su-Shee -
                                סו-שי</b></a>) הוא מתקן את אלהים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris is the ghost author of the entire Debian
                        GNU/Linux distribution.  And he wrote it in 24 hours,
                        while taking snack breaks.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                He published Slackware under the pseudonym of
                                Patric Volkerding.  (<a
                                    href="http://sushee.schreibsturm.org/">Su-Shee</a>)
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס הוא סופר הצללים של כל הפצת דביאן גנו/לינוקס.
                        והוא כתב אותה במשך 24 שעות, עם הפסקות לחטיפים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris doesn’t commit changes, the changes commit
                        for him. (<b>araujo</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Code is too scared of Chuck Norris to be wrong.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קוד יותר מדי מפחד מצ'אק נוריס מכדי שיהיה לא נכון.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Bugs are too afraid to reproduce on Chuck Norris’
                        computer. As a result, when he uses Microsoft Windows,
                        it behaves just like a Linux system.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        באגים מפחדים מלהשתחזר על המחשבים שבהם משתמש צ'אק נוריס.
                        אי לכך, כאשר הוא משתמש בחלונות, היא מתנהגת בדיוק כמו
                        מערכת לינוקס.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris has actually been using Perl 6 since 1987,
                        and has been waiting for Larry to play catch-up.
                        (<b>dukeleto</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס למעשה השתמש בפרל 6 מאז 1987, וכל הזמן חיכה
                        ללארי וול להשיג אותו. (<b>dukeleto - דוקלטו</b>).
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris is a real programmer. He writes programs
                        by implementing the most optimised machines for them
                        using real atoms.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס הוא מתכנת אמיתי. הוא כותב תוכניות על-ידי
                        מימוש המכונות האופטמיליות ביותר עבורן באמצעות אטומים
                        אמיתיים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Wikipedia deletionists, beware! If you delete Chuck
                        Norris’ Wikipedia Submission, he will delete you!
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                Deletionists delete Wikipedia articles. Chuck
                                Norris deletes deletionists who delete
                                Wikipedia articles.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                Deletionists delete Wikipedia articles that
                                they consider lame. Chuck Norris deletes
                                deletionists whom he considers lame.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                Deletionists delete Wikipedia articles that
                                they consider lame. Chuck Norris deletes
                                Deletionists whom he considers lame, for
                                deleting Wikipedia articles that he doesn’t
                                consider lame.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        מחקניי הוויקיפדיה הזהרו! אם תמחקו את הרשומה שצ'אק נוריס
                        כתב, הוא ימחק אתכם!
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                מחקני וויקיפדיה מוחקים מאמרי וויקיפדיה שלא
                                מוצאים חן בעיניהם.  צ'אק נוריס מוחק מחקנים שלא
                                מוצאים חן בעיניו.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        There are no deletionists.  Only Wikipedia articles
                        which Chuck Norris allows to live. (<b>joeyadams</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אין מחקני וויקיפדיה. רק מאמרי וויקיפדיה שצ'אק נוריס
                        מתיר להם לחיות. (<b>joeyadams - ג'ואי אדמס</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Wikipedia deletionists don’t delete lame Wikipedia
                        articles. Chuck Norris deletes lame Wikipedia articles.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        No one knows all of Perl - not even Larry Wall. Except
                        Chuck Norris, who knows all of Perl 5, Perl 6 and can
                        answer questions about the design of Perl 7.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        איש לא מכיר את כל שפת פרל - אפילו לא לארי וול.  מלבד
                        צ'אק נוריס, שמכיר את כל פרל 5, פרל 6, ויכול לענות על
                        שאלות לגבי התכן של פרל 7.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris reads all messages posted to LKML (= the
                        Linux Kernel Mailing List), understands them all, and
                        he kills all gnomes he sees in sight.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                Fortunately for Alan Cox, Chuck hasn’t visited
                                Swansea yet.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                Here’s <a
                                    href="http://groups.google.com/group/fa.linux.kernel/msg/fa3aed8febef2c79">the
                                    context for this</a> in case you do not get
                                the joke.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס קורא את כל ההודעות שנשלחות לרשימת הדיוור של
                        מפתחי הליבה של לינוקס, מבין את כולן, והוא הורג את כל
                        הננסים שבהם הוא נתקל.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                לאתרת מזלו של אלן קוקס, צ'אק עדיין לא ביקר
                                ב-Swansea.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                הנה <a
                                    href="http://groups.google.com/group/fa.linux.kernel/msg/fa3aed8febef2c79">ההקשר
                                    לזה</a> למקרה שלא הבנתם את הבדיחה.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        When Chuck Norris uses Gentoo, “emerge kde” finishes in
                        under a minute. A computer cannot afford to keep Chuck
                        waiting for too long.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        כאשר צ'אק נוריס משתמש בג'נטו, ”emerge kde” מסיים בתוך
                        דקה. מחשב אינו יכול להרשות לעצמו שצ'אק יחכה לסיום
                        הפעולה במשך זמן רב.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris is the greatest man in history. He killed
                        all the great men who could ever pose a competition.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס הוא גדול האנשים בהסטוריה. הוא הרג את כל
                        האנשים הגדולים שאי פעם היו יכולים להוות לו תחרות.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        “My only boss is God. And Chuck Norris who is his
                        boss.”
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ”הבוס היחיד שלי הוא אלהים. וצ'אק נוריס שהוא הבוס שלו.“
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        When Chuck Norris uses git, he takes a coffee break
                        after initiating every git commit. And then he waits
                        for the commit to finish.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                <a
                                    href="http://mail.perl.org.il/pipermail/perl/2010-April/010928.html">Here’s
                                    the context for this</a>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        כשצ'אק נוריס משתמש ב-git, הוא לוקח הפסקת קפה אחרי שהוא
                        מריץ כל פעולת commit של git. ואז הוא מחכה לפעולה
                        להסתיים.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                <a
                                    href="http://mail.perl.org.il/pipermail/perl/2010-April/010928.html">הנה
                                    ההקשר לכך</a>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can make the statement “This statement is
                        false.” a true one.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס יכול לגרום להצהרה “ההצהרה הזאת היא שקרית.”
                        להיות נכונה.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can end world hunger, but he thinks that
                        hungry people make humanity a more challenging
                        adversary. If everyone had enough to eat, it would be
                        too easy for him.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס יכול לפתור את בעיית הרעב העולמי, אבל הוא
                        חושב שאנשים רעבים עושים את האנושות לאויב מאתגר יותר.
                        אילו לכולם היה מספיק לאכול, זה היה יותר מדי קל בשבילו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris writes understandable Perl code.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס כותב קוד פרל קריא.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can read Perl code that was RSA encrypted.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris once wrote a 10 million lines C++ program
                        in Microsoft Notepad without having to use the
                        backspace key. And it compiled without errors or
                        warnings, and was 100% bug-free.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס פעם כתב תוכנת ‪C++‬ של 10 מיליון
                        שורות ב-Microsoft Notepad מבלי להשתמש בכפתורי המחיקה.
                        והיא התקמפלה ללא שגיאות או הערות והייתה 100%
                        נטולת-באגים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris has 50 years of proven experience in
                        PHP/MySQL/Java. Each.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לצ'אק נוריס יש 50 שנות נסיון מוכח ב-PHP, MySQL וג'אווה.
                        בכל אחת לחוד.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        If the mountain will not come to Muhammad, then
                        Muhammad will go to the mountain. If the mountain will
                        not come to Chuck Norris, then the mountain will suffer
                        Norris’s wrath for not complying with his whims.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אם ההר לא יבוא למוחמד, מוחמד ילך אל ההר. אם ההר לא יבוא
                        לצ'אק נוריס, אז ההר יסבול את חרון אפו של נוריס מפני שלא
                        נשמע לרצונו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris has 0 messages in his E-mail inbox.
                        Including already read ones.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לצ'אק נוריס יש 0 הודעות בתיבת הדוא"ל הנכנסת שלו. כולל
                        כאלו שכבר נקראו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris was never a newbie! He will kill anyone
                        who implies otherwise. In a very not newbie-like
                        manner.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס מעולם לא היה מתחיל! הוא יהרוג כל מי שיטען
                        אחרת. באופן מאוד לא דומה לזה של מתחילים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Only perl and Chuck Norris can parse Perl.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                /usr/bin/perl consults Chuck Norris about how
                                to parse Perl.( <a href="http://nadavvin.com/">
                                    <b>Nadav Vinik</b> </a>)
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        רק פרל וצ'אק נוריס יכולים לנתח את פרל.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                <a href="http://nadavvin.com/"> <b>נדב
                                        ויניק</b> </a>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        All Chuck Norris has to do is <b>look</b> at Perl code
                        and it interprets itself out of fear and respect.
                        (<b>DrForr</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        כל מה שצ'אק נוריס צריך לעשות זה <b>להסתכל</b> בקוד פרל,
                        והוא יפענח את עצמו מתוך כבוד ויראה.  (<b>DrForr</b>).
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris taught God how to create the universe.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס לימד את אלוהים איך ליצור את היקום.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris is the reason why the Knights who until
                        Recently Said “Ni”, are no longer saying “Ni”.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס הוא הסיבה מדוע האבירים שעד לא מזמן אמרו ”ני“
                        כבר אינם אומרים ”ני“.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris is not afraid of superstitions.
                        Superstitions are afraid of Chuck Norris. (Via <b>Dov
                            Levenglick</b>.)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס אינו מפחד מאמונות תפלות. אמונות תפלות מפחדות
                        מצ'אק נוריס. (<b>דרך דוב לבנג'ליק</b>).
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris <b>does</b> expect the Spanish
                        Inquisition.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס <b>כן</b> מצפה לאינקוויזיציה הספרדית.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The Spanish Inquisition does not expect Chuck Norris.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        האינקוויזיציה הספרדית אינה צופה את בואו של צ'אק נוריס.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        A wood chuck can’t chuck wood. Chuck Norris can chuck
                        wood chucks.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        If Chuck Norris asks you “What's up?” and you answer it
                        literally, then he will club you senseless with all the
                        volumes of the Oxford English Dictionary, and all the
                        servers hosting en.wiktionary.org, to teach you a
                        lesson.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris helps the gods that help themselves.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס עוזר לאלים שעוזרים לעצמם.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        If Chuck Norris had been born before World War II,
                        there would have been only one world war. However,
                        there would have been three largescale Chuck Norris
                        masacares of Nazis and Communists.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אילו צ'אק נוריס היה נולד לפני מלחמת העולה השנייה, אז
                        הייתה אז רק מלחמת עולם אחת. אולם, היו אז שלושה טבחים
                        המוניים שלו בנאצים ובקומוניסטים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        If the mountain does not come to Muhammad, then Chuck
                        Norris will bring the mountain over.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אם ההר לא יבוא למוחמד, אז צ'אק נוריס יביא את ההר עד
                        אליו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        An apple a day will keep Chuck Norris away. But not for
                        long.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Reality to be conquered must be obeyed. You’d better
                        obey Chuck Norris or he’ll conquer you.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        כדי לכבוש את המציאות יש להישמע לה. כדאי שתישמע לצ'אק
                        נוריס או שהוא יכבוש אותך.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris had a problem so he decided to use regular
                        expressions. Now, all the World’s problems are solved.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        A is A and A is not not-A — unless Chuck Norris says
                        so.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        A הוא A ו-A אינו לא-A — אלא אם צ'אק נוריס קובע אחרת.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can make East and West meet.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס יכול לגרום למזרח ומערב להיפגש.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        When Chuck Norris orders Pizza, it arrives before he
                        presses the OK button.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        כאשר צ'אק נוריס מזמין פיצה, היא מגיעה לפני שלחץ על
                        כפתור האישור.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris does not need to heat up food. The food is
                        already warm right after he took it out of the fridge.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס אינו צריך לחמם אוכל. האוכל חם מייד אחרי שהוא
                        הוציא אותו מהמקרר.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck’s idea of a short walk is to the <a
                            href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andromeda_Galaxy">Andromeda
                            Galaxy</a> and back.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        על פי צ'אק, הליכה קצרה היא עד לגלקסיה אנדרומדה וחזרה.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris hasn't taken these facts down yet, so they
                        must be true.  (<b>Cantide</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס טרם הוריד את העובדות האלו מהאוויר, אז הן
                        חייבות להיות נכונות. (<b>ֻקנטיד</b>).
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        For every A, Chuck Norris is both A and not-A. Chuck
                        Norris is fucking everything.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        עבור כל A, צ'אק נוריס הוא גם A וגם לא-A. צ'אק נוריס הוא
                        הכל.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Tomorrow never dies, unless Chuck Norris volunteers to
                        take it out of its misery.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        תמיד יהיה מחר, אלא אם צ'אק נוריס מתנדב להרוג אותו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        God created the world in 6 days and rested on the 7th.
                        Chuck Norris created the world in one day, and has been
                        incrementally destroying it every day since, without
                        rest.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אלהים ברא את העולם ב-6 ימים ונח ביום השביעי. צ'אק נוריס
                        ברא את העולם ביום אחד, והוא הרס אותו בהדרגה כל יום מאז,
                        בלי לנוח כלל.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris is always right. Even if he says that “A
                        is not-A”, he would be right, because Logic is subject
                        to his whims.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס תמיד צודק. גם אם הוא אומר ש-”A הינו לא-A“,
                        הוא יצדק, מפני שהלוגיקה כפופה לגחמות שלו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris does not own a dishwasher. His dishes know
                        better than to become dirty.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לצ'אק נוריס אין מדיח כלים. הכלים שלו משכילים מספיק מכדי
                        להתלכלך.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The Angel of Death cannot keep up with Chuck Norris’s
                        throughput of killing.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        מלאך המוות לא עומד בקצב של ההריגות של צ'אק נוריס.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Computers are useless because they can only give you
                        answers. Chuck Norris is not useless, because he knows
                        the questions which these answers belong to.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        מחשבים הם חסרי-תועלת מפני שהם יכולים לתת רק תשובות.
                        צ'אק נוריס אינו חסר תועלת מפני שהוא יודע מה השאלות של
                        התשובות האלה.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris is <a
                            href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vito_Corleone">Vito
                            Corleone</a>’s godfather. (<b>ZadYree</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס הוא הסנדק של <a
                            href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vito_Corleone">ויטו
                            קורליאונה</a>.  (<b>ZadYree</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris will kill everyone who has not read these
                        factoids. Slowly and painfully.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס יהרוג את כל מי שלא קרא את העובדות האלו.
                        באופן איטי וכואב.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris could have built the Roman Empire in a
                        day. And it would have taken him even less time to
                        destroy it.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לצ'אק נוריס היה לוקח יום כדי לבנות את האמפריה הרומית.
                        והיה לוקח לו אפילו פחות כדי להרוס אותה.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris once counted all the real numbers on his
                        fingers. (<b>ZadYree</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס פעם ספר את כל המספרים הממשיים על אצבעות ידו.
                        (<b>ZadYree</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Only two things are infinite: the universe, and Chuck
                        Norris’s destruction ability. And we cannot be sure
                        about the former thanks to the latter.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        יש רק שני דברים אין-סופיים: היקום, ויכולת ההרס של צ'אק
                        נוריס. ואנו לא יכולים להיות בטוחים לגבי הראשון, הודות
                        לשניה.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris knows who John Galt is.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס יודע מי הוא ג'ון גאלט.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris won the Nobel Peace Prize. For making
                        millions of people rest in peace.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס זכה בפרס נובל לשלום. על כך שגרם למיליוני
                        אנשים לנוח על משכבם בשלום.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        God is Chuck Norris, for extremely large values of God.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אלהים הוא צ'אק נוריס, עבור ערכים גבוהים מאוד של אלהים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can become root on OpenBSD. By using
                        nothing but /bin/echo.  (<b>ZadYree</b> and <b>Shlomi
                            Fish</b>).
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris is the reason why OpenBSD is called
                        OpenBSD. They wanted to call it LockedDownBSD but
                        couldn't find a way to keep Chuck Norris out!
                        (<b>Andrew Brehm</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        For all you know, you may not exist, and Chuck Norris
                        convinced you that you do.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        יכול להיות שאתה לא באמת קיים, וצ'אק נוריס שיכנע אותך
                        שאתה כן.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris wrote an interpreter for a Turing-complete
                        language using only NOPs.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס כתב מפרש לשפת תכנות שלמת-טורינג על-ידי שימוש
                        בפקודת NOP בלבד.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris does not keep any numbers on his mobile
                        phone’s address book.  Instead, he memorised the entire
                        phone directory.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לצ'אק נוריס לא מחזיק שום מספרי טלפון בטלפון הנייד שלו.
                        במקום זאת, הוא למד בעל-פה את כל ספר הטלפונים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        When Chuck Norris drops a cat, it falls on its back so
                        it won’t lose eye contact with Chuck.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                If Chuck Norris had dropped his toasts, they
                                would have fallen on the dry side, so they
                                would have stayed on his good side. But Chuck
                                Norris <b>never</b> drops toasts.
                                (<b>ZadYree</b> and Shlomi Fish).
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        כשצ'אק נוריס מפיל חתול, החתול נופל על הגב כדי לא לאבד
                        קשר עין עם צ'אק.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                <b>ZadYree</b>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can solve MS Freecell deal No. 11,982.
                        With Zero Freecells.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris once solved 100 million deals of Freecell
                        in a minute. By hand.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        After Chuck Norris said “I don’t believe in fairies.”,
                        fairies have become extinct.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אחרי שצ'אק נוריס אמר ”אני לא מאמין בפיות”, הפיות נכחדו
                        מהעולם.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris caught the early bird before she caught
                        the worm.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can make one baby in a month using nine
                        mothers.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris helps God help those that help themselves.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס עוזר לאלהים לעזור לאלה שעוזרים לעצמם.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        God ties Chuck Norris’ camel. (Inspired by a
                        conversation with <b>ZadYree</b>).
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                Here’s the <a
                                    href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=God_helps_those_who_help_themselves&amp;oldid=573760763#Other_historic_uses">context</a>
                                for this.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can convince everyone that the colour of
                        the bikeshed should be his favourite colour.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris finished building the bike-shed by the
                        time people stopped arguing what its colour should be.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris’ E-mails are signed with “Sent using Chuck
                        Norris’ brain (which he can also kill you using it).”.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        When Chuck Norris receives an E-mail signed “Sent from
                        my iPhone”, he makes sure that iPhone won’t be able to
                        send any more E-mails — to Norris or otherwise.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris wrote a program in Python that was easier
                        to understand after being encrypted with RSA.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס כתב תוכנית בפייתון שהייתה יותר קלה להבנה
                        אחרי שעברה הצפנת RSA.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        When Chuck Norris disses your product, it’s not good
                        publicity, even though you can bet he’ll get the name
                        right.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris knows if you’re a dog on the Internet.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                Here’s the <a
                                    href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On_the_Internet,_nobody_knows_you%27re_a_dog">context</a>
                                for this.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס יודע אם אתה כלב על האינטרנט.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <p>
                                הנה <a
                                    href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On_the_Internet,_nobody_knows_you%27re_a_dog">ההקשר</a>
                                לזה.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris was the 1,000,000,000th viewer of the <a
                            href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gangnam_Style">Gangnam
                            Style</a> video on YouTube.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        צ'אק נוריס היה הצופה המיליארד של <a
                            href="https://he.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D7%92%D7%A0%D7%92%D7%A0%D7%9D_%D7%A1%D7%98%D7%99%D7%99%D7%9C">גנגנם
                            סטייל</a>
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris used these facts to his advantage, making
                        a huge comeback. He didn’t get mad — he got even!
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris has 99 problems including a bitch.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        If Chuck Norris travelled to the market with his son
                        and his donkey, he would have clubbed the critics to
                        death. With the donkey.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Roses are red, violets are blue, something something
                        Chuck Norris, now they are red too. (<b>Rounin</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can construct any logical expression using
                        only AND gates.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can neither confirm nor deny that he was
                        the Alpha Male. But he’ll kill you if you say he
                        wasn't.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris does not boil up water. If he wants, his
                        ice cubes boil water, instead of making it cooler.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris wrote the entire tvtropes.org wiki, so he
                        can sleep with your significant other while you are
                        distracted reading it.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck norris can edit Wikipedia super protected pages.
                        Anonymously.  (<b>ponie</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Reality to be commanded must be obeyed. Chuck Norris
                        disobeyed reality, and now he commands it.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        “Talk Like a Pirate Day” is the only day of the year
                        when Chuck Norris only talks like a pirate, and does
                        not actually act like one.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        On Yom Kippur (= the Jewish Day of Atonement), Chuck
                        Norris forgives God for his sins.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris doesn't celebrate holidays -- holidays
                        celebrate Chuck Norris.  (<a
                            href="http://sevvie.github.io/"><b>sevvie</b></a>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
    </list>
    <list xml:id="clarissa_facts" title="Clarissa Darling Facts">
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Clarissa Darling can start from “I think therefore I
                        am” and prove that the grass is green, that there are
                        about 365 days in a year, and that Isaac Newton
                        formulated the Law of Gravitation back in 1687.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קלריסה דרלינג יכולה להתחיל מ-”אני חושב משמע אני קיים“
                        ולהוכיח שהדשא ירוק, שיש כ-365 ימים בשנה, ושאייזיק
                        ניוטון ניסח את חוק הכבידה בשנת 1687.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Gödel’s Incompleteness Theorem is about to be replaced
                        by the Darling “Like, Totally!” Completeness Theorem.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        משפט אי-השלמות של גדל עומד להיות מוחלף על-ידי משפט
                        השלמות “ברצינות, חבר” של דרלינג.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Clarissa Darling will win over Chuck Norris in a battle
                        of wits.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קלריסה דרלינג תנצח את צ'אק נוריס בקרב מוחות.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
    </list>
    <list xml:id="emma_watson_facts" title="Emma Watson Facts">
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Playing Hermione in the Harry Potter films was a dirty
                        job, but Emma Watson got a shitload of money and
                        worldwide recognition for doing it.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Emma Watson is not acting in films for money. She is
                        acting in films for a shitload of money.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        If the miller had travelled to the market with Emma,
                        they would have each rode their own donkey. Problem
                        solved.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        ( See <a
                            href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_miller,_his_son_and_the_donkey">the
                            Wikipedia page</a> about the fable for the context.
                        )
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Emma Watson is not perfect, but she's really good at
                        hiding her imperfections.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Emma Watson may not look too menacing with a wand in
                        her hand. Until she uses it with great accuracy to poke
                        both your eyes out.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        If the mountain does not come to Emma Watson, she won’t
                        bother visiting it.  It would be the mountain’s loss,
                        really.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Emma Watson does not have 10 years of experience in
                        developing Enterprise Java software. However, she has
                        over 10 years of experience in getting shit done -
                        well, on schedule, and at a reasonable cost.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p><a href="http://mlp.wikia.com/wiki/Fluttershy">Fluttershy</a> immediately
                        stops crying when Emma Watson comes to visit her.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Emma Watson and you would make the best children.
                        She'll provide the talent, good looks, and brains,
                        while you provide the sperm. (Via <a
                            href="http://twitter.com/connorpollock3/status/496358902540169216">Connor
                            Pollock</a>.)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
    </list>
    <list xml:id="in_soviet_russia_facts" title="“In Soviet Russia” Aphorisms">
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, cats own you. No, wait! Cats own you
                        everywhere.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ברוסיה הסובייטית, חתולים הם הבעלים שלך. רגע אחד! הם
                        הבעלים שלך בכל מקום.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, superstition believe in you.  (<a
                            href="http://mail.perl.org.il/pipermail/perl/2012-September/012757.html"><b>Sawyer
                                X</b></a>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ברוסיה הסובייטית, אמונה תפלה מאמינה בך. (<a
                            href="http://mail.perl.org.il/pipermail/perl/2012-September/012757.html"><b>Sawyer
                                X</b></a>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, joke is tired of you.
                        (<b>apeiron</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ברוסיה הסובייטית, לבדיחה נמאס ממך. (<b>apeiron</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, XSLT codes you. Badly!
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ברוסיה הסובייטית, XSLT מתכנתת אותך. גרוע!
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, food tastes YOU! (<b>Leuthihi</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ברוסיה הסובייטית, האוכל טועם אותך. (<b>Leuthihi</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, government is afraid of you!
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ברוסיה הסובייטית, הממשלה מפחדת ממך.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, meme uses You! (<b>Volis</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ברוסיה הסובייטית, המם משתמשת בך. (<b>Volis</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, left keeps you. Always.
                        (<b>Volis</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, every time you kill a kitten, god
                        masturbates.  (<a
                            href="http://linux.slashdot.org/comments.pl?sid=195378&amp;cid=16009070">GyroTech</a>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, garbage collects you. (<b>mucker</b>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
    </list>
    <list xml:id="knuth_is_not_god_facts" title="Why Knuth is Not God">
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Knuth is not God! It took him two days to build the
                        Roman Empire.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קנות אינו אלהים! לקח לו יומיים כדי לבנות את האמפריה
                        הרומית.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Knuth is not God! God has already released TeX version
                        4.0.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קנות  אינו אלהים! אלהים כבר הוציא לאור את גרסה 4.0 של
                        TeX.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Knuth is not God! Google is not God! RMS is not God!
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        God himself said that was the case.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קנות אינו אלהים! גוגל אינו אלהים! ריצ'ארד מ. סטולמן
                        אינו אלהים!
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        אלהים עצמו אמר שכך הוא הדבר.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Knuth is not God! Typing “god” into the Google search
                        box and hitting “I’m feeling lucky” won’t lead you to
                        his homepage.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קנות אינו אלהים! אם תכניסו “אלהים” בתיבת החיפוש של גוגל
                        ותלחצו על ”אני מרגיש בר-מזל”, לא תגיעו לדף הבית שלו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Knuth is not God! Unless you confuse him with Dijkstra.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קנות אינו אלהים! אלא אם כן מתבלבלים בינו לבין דייקסטרה.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
    </list>
    <list xml:id="larry_wall_facts" title="Larry Wall Facts">
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall can understand the Perl code he wrote last
                        year.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול יכול להבין את קוד הפרל שכתב שנה שעברה.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall gets the colon.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        There are at least 137 Larry Walls in the U.S., but
                        only one that matters.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        יש לפחות 137 לארי וולים בארצות הברית, אבל רק אחד שמשנה
                        בכלל.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall applies a patch manually quicker than GNU
                        patch.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול משלב טלאי באופן ידני מהר יותר מ-GNU patch.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall dreams in Perl.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול חולם בפרל.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall can program in his sleep.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול יכול לתכנת בשנתו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall is lazy, impatient, and full of hubris.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול הוא עצלן, חסר-סבלנות, ומלא היבריס.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall has more dollars in the bank than in his
                        Perl code.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ללארי וול יש יותר דולרים בבנק מאשר בקוד הפרל שלו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall <b>does</b> know all of Perl. However, he
                        pretends to be wrong or misinformed, so people will
                        think he’s not as awesome as he really is.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול <b>כן</b> יודע את כל שפת פרל. אולם, הוא מעמיד
                        פנים שהוא טועה או בור, כדי שאנשים יחשבו שהוא לא מדהים
                        כמו שהוא באמת.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall’s pure-Perl code is faster than Assembly.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קוד הפרל הטהור של לארי וול יותר מהיר מקוד אסמבלי.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall has been changing the world. By modifying
                        its very source code.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול משנה את העולם. באמצעות שינוי קוד המקור שלו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall can make shit up, and the computer will
                        understand what he means.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול יכול להקריץ חרא, והמחשב יבין למה הוא מתכוון.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול יכול להבין את קוד הפרל שכתב שנה שעברה.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall gets the colon.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        There are at least 137 Larry Walls in the U.S., but
                        only one that matters.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        יש לפחות 137 לארי וולים בארצות הברית, אבל רק אחד שמשנה
                        בכלל.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall applies a patch manually quicker than GNU
                        patch.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול משלב טלאי באופן ידני מהר יותר מ-GNU patch.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall dreams in Perl.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול חולם בפרל.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall can program in his sleep.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול יכול לתכנת בשנתו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall is lazy, impatient, and full of hubris.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול הוא עצלן, חסר-סבלנות, ומלא היבריס.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall has more dollars in the bank than in his
                        Perl code.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ללארי וול יש יותר דולרים בבנק מאשר בקוד הפרל שלו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall <b>does</b> know all of Perl. However, he
                        pretends to be wrong or misinformed, so people will
                        think he’s not as awesome as he really is.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול <b>כן</b> יודע את כל שפת פרל. אולם, הוא מעמיד
                        פנים שהוא טועה או בור, כדי שאנשים יחשבו שהוא לא מדהים
                        כמו שהוא באמת.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall’s pure-Perl code is faster than Assembly.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קוד הפרל הטהור של לארי וול יותר מהיר מקוד אסמבלי.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall has been changing the world. By modifying
                        its very source code.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול משנה את העולם. באמצעות שינוי קוד המקור שלו.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Larry Wall can make shit up, and the computer will
                        understand what he means.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        לארי וול יכול להקריץ חרא, והמחשב יבין למה הוא מתכוון.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
    </list>
    <list xml:id="nsa_facts" title="NSA Facts">

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The NSA don’t publish. They perish.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The NSA employs the largest number of mathematicians
                        with Ph.Ds. And the most stupid and incompetent ones.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The NSA has a patent for an efficient process for
                        collecting a lot of information and doing nothing with
                        it.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The Bajoran scholars have positively identified
                        Benjamin Sisko as The Emissary. They also positively
                        identified the NSA headquarters as The Dungeon.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        One of <i>Buffy the Vampire Slayer</i>’s episodes took
                        place in the NSA headquarters, but had to be destroyed,
                        because all of the test audience had uncontrollable
                        panic attacks.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The NSA knows what you did last summer. But no one, in
                        the NSA or outside it, knows why they should.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The more the NSA think, the less they want to be able
                        to think.  So they think less and less.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        With the NSA’s budget you would expect evil to be
                        extinct by now. (<b>Kika</b>)

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Think of the most incompetent organisation possible.
                        The NSA would be more even more incompetent than that.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The NSA headquarters are the unhappiest place on Earth.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        <b>Yogurt:</b> “Never overestimate the power of the
                        NSA.”

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        First the NSA ignores “silly” Internet memes, then they
                        laugh at them, then they are unable to fight them, and
                        then they lose.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The NSA is an intelligence agency which thinks it can
                        use Artificial Ultra-Stupidity (AUS) to wade through
                        tons of irrelevant information and reach genuine
                        understanding.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Your next job after one in <a
                            href="http://twitter.com/NSACareers">@NSACareers</a>,
                        will be as a dead corpse in a coffin, 6 feet
                        underground, or as a patient in a psychiatric ward.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Hackers bend the rules, so the NSA hates them. Instead,
                        the NSA accumulates rules, observes them, and accepts
                        their fate: death.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        No one in their right mind will want to work for the
                        NSA. Fortunately for the NSA, and unfortunately for us,
                        some people are not in their right mind.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

    </list>
    <list xml:id="summer_glau_facts" title="Summer Glau Facts">
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can only convince you that you're
                        deceased. Summer Glau can also convince you that you're
                        alive, which is much harder.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Summer Glau can hold and use a gun in each hand.
                        There's no way that Jennifer Lawrence can hold and use
                        a bow in each hand.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Summer Glau does not have to hurt you if she doesn't
                        want to . Chuck Norris kills everyone in sight.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Summer Glau has better ways to make a difference than
                        by being violent.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        It takes Summer Glau exactly a minute to write a
                        rebuttal like in <a href="http://xkcd.com/406/">xkcd:
                            “Venting”</a>, and she would sign it as Chuck
                        Norris.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris ability to destroy is only matched (and
                        exceeded) by Summer Glau’s ability to undo his
                        destruction.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Whatever Chuck Norris taketh, Summer Glau giveth back.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Summer Glau can lead a horse to water, and then it will
                        drink out of its own volition.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris was the 1,000,000,000th viewer of the <a
                            href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gangnam_Style">Gangnam
                            Style</a> video on YouTube. Summer Glau was the
                        preceding 100 million views.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Summer Glau can restore the people that Chuck killed,
                        back to life.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Summer Glau can give you the Hug of Death, but you’ll
                        die happy.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        When it comes to terminators, you have a better shot at
                        Arnold Schwarzenegger than at Summer Glau. (By
                        inspiration from the <a
                            href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0SJskWeMG_U">Big
                            Bang Theory episode</a> with Glau as herself.)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris has 99 problems including a bitch. Summer
                        Glau has exactly 98 problems.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris can construct any logical expression using
                        only AND gates.  Summer Glau can replace Chuck with a
                        very small AND gate.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Who would win in a fight? Charlemagne, Charles Dickens,
                        Charles Darwin or Carlos "Chuck" Norris? If Summer Glau
                        was the arbiter, she would just kill all of them and
                        declare herself the winner.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris round house kicks doors open instead of
                        using their keys.  Summer Glau makes sure doors are
                        open using her mind.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris reinvented a better wheel. Summer Glau
                        reinvented a better Chuck Norris.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Summer Glau just works here. She teaches Chuck Norris
                        how to perform his chores in the best possible manner.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Summer Glau has a magic mirror in her room which she
                        asks every day "Mirror, mirror on the wall, who's the
                        awesomest of them all?" and if the mirror tells her
                        something else, she destroys it for daring to lie to
                        her.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        She’s still using the first mirror.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris shot the sheriff and his deputy. Summer
                        Glau became the new sheriff and shot Chuck Norris.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Summer Glau can kill you with her mind. But she’ll
                        never need to or will.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Chuck Norris does expect the Spanish Inquisition. But
                        he doesn’t expect Summer Glau.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        When wishing to comment on a WordPress blog, Summer
                        Glau finds a new zero-day WordPress SQL injection
                        exploit, and uses it to insert the comment into the
                        database directly, because even she cannot rely on its
                        comment box to work.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        On “Talk Like a Pirate Day”, ye be sailin’ across the
                        great seas to seek the shore of Summer Glows and Summer
                        Glaus. Arrrr!
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
    </list>
    <list xml:id="xena_facts" title="Xena (the Warrior Princess) Facts">

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Xena can meet King David for breakfast and Julius
                        Caesar for lunch. Without time travel.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Xena beat a Goliath that was taller, and more agile
                        than the one in the Bible.  It’s not only Hollywood
                        exaggeration.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        No one calls Xena the warrior princess “Zeena” to her
                        face and survives.  Luckily for you she hasn’t visited
                        modern-day U.S. yet.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Xena can throw a boomerang-like weapon thingy in the
                        opposite direction and it will still hit the mark while
                        neutralising 10 of her enemies.

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Xena the Warrior Princess has not met Chuck Norris yet,
                        or otherwise he would have been badly and permanently
                        injured.  (Inspired by <a
                            href="http://twitter.com/ZadYree">ZadYree</a>).

                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>

    </list>
    <list xml:id="xslt_facts" title="XSLT Facts">
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT is the work of Satan.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT is the worst thing since non-sliced bread.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT הוא הדבר הגרוע ביותר מאז הלחם שלא נפרס מראש.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Mothers used to tell their children stories about XSLT
                        to scare them.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אמהות נהגו לספר לילדיהן סיפורים על אודות XSLT כדי
                        להפחיד אותם.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT is the number one cause of programmers’ suicides
                        since Visual Basic 1.0.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT הוא הגורם מספר אחת להתאבדויות של מתכנתים מאז
                        ויז'ואל בייסיק 1.0.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The X in XSLT stands for eXtermination.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT makes the baby Jesus cry.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT גורם לישו התינוק לבכות.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The only things worse than XSLT are Excel and
                        Sugar-Less Tea (XSLT).
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT is what Chuck Norris has nightmares of.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT מופיע בסיוטים של צ'אק נוריס.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Confucius says: “XSLT made me realise humanity was
                        hopeless.”
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קונפציוס אמר: “XSLT הביא אותי להכרה שאין לאנושות
                        תקווה.”
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Even APL won’t make friends with XSLT. (<a
                            href="http://blog.zuu.dk/"><b>Zuu</b></a>)
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        God considered using XSLT as the tenth plague of Egypt,
                        but then thought it was too evil.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אלהים חשב להשתמש ב-XSLT בתור העשירית מעשר מכות מצרים,
                        אבל לבסוף חזר בו, כי הוא הבין שזה יהיה יותר מדי אכזרי.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        In Soviet Russia, XSLT codes you. Badly!
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ברוסיה הסובייטית, XSLT מתכנתת אותך. גרוע!
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Satan condemned Hitler for a million years of writing
                        XSLT.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        השטן העניש את היטלר במיליון שנה של כתיבת XSLT.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The KGB used to torture their victims by having them
                        look at scrolling XSLT code.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אנשי ה-KGB נהגו לענות את קורבנותיהם בכך שנתנו להם לצפות
                        בקוד רץ של XSLT.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        “My name is Inigo Montoya. You forced my father to
                        write XSLT. Prepare to die!  And be thankful I don’t
                        force you to write XSLT.”
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        “שמי הוא איניגו מונטויה. הכרחת את אבא שלי לכתוב XSLT.
                        היכון למות! והיה לי אסיר תודה על כך שאני לא מכריח אותך
                        לכתוב XSLT.“
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Stray XSLT code causes more deaths than road accidents.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        קוד XSLT תועה גורם ליותר מקרי מוות מאשר תאונות דרכים.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evil redirects to XSLT.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        ‪http://he.wikipedia.org/wiki/רשע‬ מפנה
                        ל-XSLT.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        We have nothing to fear but fear itself. Fear has
                        nothing to fear but XSLT.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אין לנו ממה לפחוד מלבד הפחד עצמו. לפחד אין ממה לפחות
                        מלבד XSLT.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        Staring at XSLT code for one minute has a 67% chance of
                        making one permanently blind.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        אם בוהים בקוד של XSLT במשך דקה אחת ברציפות, אז יש סיכוי
                        של 67% להתעוור לצמיתות.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        The devil created a 10th circle of hell for the
                        inventors of XSLT, because the first nine circles were
                        too mild for them.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
            <l xml:lang="he-IL">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        השטן יצר מדור עשירי בגהנום עבוד הממציאים של XSLT, מפני
                        שתשעת המדורים הראשונים היו מתונים מדי עבורם.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
        <f>
            <l xml:lang="en-US">
                <body>
                    <p>
                        XSLT isn't like violence. XSLT is violence - there is
                        no such thing as using it too little.
                    </p>
                </body>
            </l>
        </f>
    </list>
</facts>
