<document
	title	= "Using GXML: Templates"
	author	= "Josh Carter"
	email	= "josh@multipart-mixed.com"
	date	= "May 10, 2001"
>

<section name="Template Basics">

<p>
Templates allow you to transform an element in your source file into
something else in your output. The most common use is to apply
formatting; thus your input file in raw data and our output is nicely
formatted data.
</p>

<p>
Templates are kept in a separate directory from your other files, and
the name of the template file indicates the tag that it'll map to.
Thus, if you want to template all "person" elements, you create a file
called "<tt>person.xml</tt>" in your templates directory. The
<tt>person.xml</tt> file will most likely take attributes from the
person element in your data file by using variables.
</p>

<p>
Let's demonstrate. Say we have a data file as follows, and a
<tt>person.xml</tt> file I'll list afterward:
</p>

<pre>
    &lt;data-file&gt;
        &lt;person&gt;
            <t tag="name">Bob</t>
            <t tag="age">42</t>
        &lt;/person&gt;

        &lt;person&gt;
            <t tag="name">Ned</t>
            <t tag="age">24</t>
        &lt;/person&gt;
    &lt;/data-file&gt;
</pre>

<p>
<tt>person.xml</tt> in your template directory contains:
</p>

<pre>
    &lt;person&gt;
        <t tag="p">Person name is: <v>name</v>, age is <v>age</v></t>
    &lt;/person&gt;
</pre>

<p>
The output of running GXML over the data file will be:
</p>

<pre>
    &lt;data-file&gt;
        &lt;person&gt;
        <t tag="p">Person name is: Bob, age is 42</t>
        &lt;/person&gt;

        &lt;person&gt;
        <t tag="p">Person name is: Ned, age is 24</t>
        &lt;/person&gt;
    &lt;/data-file&gt;
</pre>

<p>
(Give or take some white space in the final output.) If you have HTML
translation turned on, the enclosing tags for the document and
templates will be stripped, producing:
</p>

<pre>
    <t tag="p">Person name is: Bob, age is 42</t>

    <t tag="p">Person name is: Ned, age is 24</t>
</pre>

<p>
And now we have something useful. However your data files are created,
you can create formatting templates which will produce output that
looks the way you want. If you decide to change the data, no problem,
just run GXML over it again and the output will be updated. Ditto
changing a template. This gives you a great deal of flexibility.
</p>

</section>
<section name="Nested Templates">

<p>
GXML fully supports nested templates. That is, a template can contain
elements which will get mapped into other templates. It won't take
long before your project(s) get complex to need this. For example, say
you have a "document" template, and a "link" template that you use for
hrefs to other pages/sites. Then you add a "photo" template, and you
want the caption to link to something. Go ahead and use your "link"
template within the "photo" one. It'll work like you expect.
</p>

</section>
<section name="Variable Rules With Templates">

<p>
The scoping rules for variables still apply with templates, and the
concept of "enclosing" attributes can span multiple templates. In the
example of nested document/photo/link templates, the "link" template
could have variables whose value is up in the document. No problem;
the variable matching engine works seamlessly across templates.
</p>

</section>
<section name="Variables Within Template Names">

<p>
This gets a little twisted. Let's say you have three templates for the
header of your document, one for if you have a lead photo on the left,
another with a lead photo centered, and another with no lead photo.
(This is what I do on multipart/mixed, actually.) You can select which
header template you want to use by using a variable as all or part of
your template name. Here's an example, assuming you have header
templates named "header-right" and "header-none":
</p>

<pre>
    # document source file:

    &lt;document
        name   = "Semi-annual Worm Preservation Report"
        author = "Bob the Man"

        photo-align  = "right"
        photo-source = "worms.jpg"
    &gt;

    (document body text here)

    &lt;/document&gt;

    # document.xml template file:

    &lt;document
        name-default   = "Untitled Document"
        author-default = "Unknown Author"

        photo-align-default  = "none"
    &gt;

    <b>
    &lt;header-<v>photo-align</v>/&gt;
    </b>

    <v>_BODY_</v>

    &lt;/document&gt;
</pre>

<p>
Now the header template will be selected based on the "photo-align"
attribute of your document, defaulting to "header-none." There are
other ways to do this; you'll see that in the next section on GXML
commands. Also note that defining default attribute values in your
templates can be very useful.
</p>

</section>
<section name="The Special _BODY_ Variable">

You may have noticed I used a weird looking variable in that last
example. There's a special variable for the text enclosed by an
element: <tt>_BODY_</tt>. In the example above, using <tt>_BODY_</tt>
in the document template meant "give me all the content of the
'document' element." Let's take a simpler example. Say we want the
concept of a hyperlink with description, written in our document as
follows:

<pre>
    &lt;linkitem name="Bob's Worm Land" href="http://worms.bob/"&gt;
    This site tells you everything you'd ever want to know about
    worms.
    &lt;/linkitem&gt;
</pre>

<p>
Your <tt>linkitem.xml</tt> template could look like this:
</p>

<pre>
    &lt;linkitem&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="<v>href</v>"&gt;<v>name</v>&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; <v>_BODY_</v>&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/linkitem&gt;
</pre>

</section>

<p>
<b><a href="commands.html">On to Commands!</a></b>
</p>

<p>
<b><a href="gxml-guide.html">Back to the GXML Guide</a></b>
</p>

<p>
<b><a href="gxml2html-guide.html">Back to the gxml2html Guide</a></b>
</p>

</document>
