<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<blog xmlns="http://www.blogml.com/2006/01/BlogML" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" root-url="http://blog.wcs.org/" date-created="2005-12-08T00:16:28">
	<title>Animal News</title>
	<sub-title type="text">The wild side of the news.</sub-title>
	<author name="Tex McNabbit" email="tex@wcs.org"/>
	<categories>
		<category id="10" date-created="2006-01-29T09:16:57" date-modified="2006-01-29T09:16:57" approved="true">
			<title type="text">Rescue</title>
		</category>
		<category id="101" date-created="2006-01-29T09:16:57" date-modified="2006-01-29T09:16:57" approved="true" parentref="100">
			<title type="text">Cats</title>
		</category>
		<category id="100" date-created="2006-01-29T09:16:57" date-modified="2006-01-29T09:16:57" approved="true">
			<title type="text">Pets</title>
		</category>
		<category id="200" date-created="2006-01-29T09:16:57" date-modified="2006-01-29T09:16:57" approved="true">
			<title type="text">Reptiles</title>
		</category>
		<category id="201" date-created="2006-01-29T09:16:57" date-modified="2006-01-29T09:16:57" approved="true" parentref="200">
			<title type="text">Snakes</title>
		</category>
	</categories>
	<posts>
		<post id="199" date-created="2010-01-01T09:00:00" date-modified="2010-01-01T09:00:00" approved="false" post-url="http://blog.wcs.org/post?id=199">
			<title>NYC Cat Finally Rescued After 14 Days</title>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>
			As a crowd of reporters and onlookers jostled for a glance, the 
			11-month-old black cat appeared docile and unscathed despite her 
			ordeal, which came to a happy end on Friday after a volunteer pulled 
			her to safety from a crawl space.
			</p>
			<p>
			"I think you'll all agree that she is in great shape," said a proud 
			Peter Myers, a delicatessen owner in the building who kept Molly in 
			his store to catch mice.
			</p>
			<p>
			Molly's distressed meows &mdash; audible from the sidewalk outside 
			the building &mdash; became international news, and rescuers worked 
			almost around the clock for her safe retrieval.
			</p>
			<p>
			The activity began after the cat wandered into a narrow space 
			between walls and got lost in the building's complex network of 
			beams and pipes.
			</p>
			<p>
			Those involved in the rescue effort drilled and hammered out bricks 
			in the cellar of the 157-year-old edifice, trying everything from 
			special cameras to traps to locate her and get her out. Kittens were 
			used as bait to appeal to Molly's maternal side. A pet psychic and 
			self-described "cat therapist" even stopped by to offer a hand.
			</p>
			<p>
			But in the end, it was good old-fashioned elbow grease that got the 
			job done.
			</p>
			]]></content>
			<categories>
				<category ref="10"/>
				<category ref="101"/>
			</categories>
		</post>
		<post id="120" date-created="2006-05-06T00:02:09" date-modified="2006-05-06T00:02:09" approved="true" post-url="http://blog.wcs.org/post?id=120">
			<title>Missing dog found nearly a week after plane crash</title>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>Six days after a small plane crash that killed two members of a family four, the family's missing dog was found alive by the same pair of teenage brothers who first helped the survivors.</p>

				<p>Family friends had been searching for Lindsey, a 9-year-old Dalmation who had been on the plane but was not found at the crash site.</p>

				<p>"We were called loonies," said Bob Jansen, who along with his wife Shirley had spent much of the week looking for Lindsey. "They told us we were searching for a dead dog."</p>

				<p>"The family's gone through hell on earth, and this is one tiny bright spot," Jansen said. "We can give the family a 55-pound piece of good news."</p>
			]]></content>
		</post>
		<post id="121" date-created="2006-04-16T10:27:40" date-modified="2006-04-16T10:27:00" approved="true" post-url="http://blog.wcs.org/post?id=121">
			<title>Cat saves baby's life</title>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>
			A cat saved the life of a newborn baby abandoned on the doorstep of 
			a Cologne house in the middle of the night by meowing loudly until 
			someone woke up, a police spokesman said Saturday.
			</p>
			<p>
			"The cat is a hero," Cologne police spokesman Uwe Beier said. "Its 
			loud meowing got the attention of the homeowner and saved the baby 
			from suffering life-threatening hypothermia. The homeowner opened 
			door to see why the cat was making so much noise and discovered the 
			newborn."
			</p>
			]]></content>
			<categories>
				<category ref="10"/>
				<category ref="101"/>
				<category ref="100"/>
			</categories>
		</post>
		<post id="122" date-created="2006-04-12T13:18:08" date-modified="2006-04-12T09:12:58" approved="true" post-url="http://blog.wcs.org/post?id=122">
			<title>Florida Island Residents Besieged by Iguanas</title>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>
			Kevin Enge, an exotic species expert with the Florida Fish and 
			Wildlife Conservation Commission, said he believes the iguana was 
			introduced to Boca Grande in the 1970s by a boat captain who brought 
			a few from Mexico for his kids but released them when they grew too 
			large. Their population exploded because each female iguana can lay 
			up to 75 eggs a year.
			</p>
			<p>
			The reptiles are found in a few other places in Florida, but nowhere 
			in the numbers seen on Gasparilla Island, home to television 
			renovator Bob Vila and a vacation spot for the Bush clan.
			</p>
			<p>
			"There's no way you'll get rid of them all. Once they're established 
			to that extent, it's a lost cause," Enge said.
			</p>
			]]></content>
			<categories>
				<category ref="200"/>
			</categories>
		</post>
		<post id="105" date-created="2006-04-10T19:11:00" date-modified="2006-04-10T19:11:00" approved="false" post-url="http://blog.wcs.org/post?id=105">
			<title>Fire Crew Save Cow Stuck in Mud</title>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>
			A team from Durham Fire and Rescue Service were called to Bishop 
			Auckland Rugby Club on Saturday morning to perform the unusual 
			rescue mission.
			</p>
			<p>
			It took two hours for officers to free the animal from the playing 
			field at Westmills, Bridge Road, using a winch and a heavy rescue 
			vehicle.
			</p>
			<p>
			The cow is being examined by an RSPCA vet while its owner is being 
			traced.
			</p>
			]]></content>
		</post>
		<post id="115" date-created="2006-01-01T11:00:49" date-modified="2006-01-01T11:00:49" approved="true" post-url="http://blog.wcs.org/post?id=115">
			<title>Biologist Battles Killer Pythons in US Park</title>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>
			"People buy them when they're small," he said. "I've seen them as 
			cheap as 20 bucks in flea markets."
			</p>
			<p>
			The inch-long hatchlings start off cute. Then they hit puberty.
			</p>
			<p>
			"By the end of the year, they're seven feet long," Snow said. "By 
			the end of two years, they're 10 feet long. And that's more snake 
			than anyone can handle."
			</p>
			<p>
			Overwhelmed with pets that eat more than they do, python owners 
			decide to release their snakes into the wild. It's so common in the 
			Everglades, Snow's had to start a python hot line.
			</p>
			<p>
			And there the Asian natives breed and find a comfortable home in the 
			Everglades' water, heat and vegetation. They have no predators.
			</p>
			<p>
			Pythons have also discovered suburbia, said Capt. Ernie Jillson, who 
			helps run the Miami-Dade County fire department's snake squad. They 
			catch around 20 pythons a year.
			</p>
			<p>
			Three years ago, a 15-footer stopped traffic when he spread himself 
			across a four-lane road. Last year, another 15-footer gave a 
			60-year-old woman quite the jolt when she walked outside to find the 
			snake sunbathing on her patio. And rescue workers had to save a cat 
			from the 10-foot python that was chasing it around the backyard pool.
			</p>
			<p>
			Lawmaker Poppell says he's no snake lover and doesn't understand 
			people's fascination with the slithery creatures.
			</p>
			]]></content>
			<categories>
				<category ref="201"/>
			</categories>
		</post>
		<post id="93" date-created="2005-12-21T09:01:22" date-modified="2005-12-21T09:01:22" approved="true" post-url="http://blog.wcs.org/post?id=93">
			<title>"Veggie Dog Diet" Fights Weight Gain</title>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>
			By adding string beans to your pet's diet, you add fiber to 
			their diet, thus helping resolve constipation and anal sac problems; 
			with the added fiber and reduced amount of dog food, you have 
			reduced the daily caloric intake, resulting in weight loss; with 
			green beans, you have given your pet a wonderful treat that happens 
			to be full of vitamins and minerals; and finally dogs, being plant 
			and meat eaters, crave the oral sensation derived from the texture 
			of string beans (some believe this is why some dogs eat grass 
			periodically). Other vegetables besides string beans can be used, 
			such as broccoli, carrots or lettuce.
			</p>
			]]></content>
			<categories>
				<category ref="100"/>
			</categories>
		</post>
	</posts>
</blog>
