<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- If you are running a bot please visit this policy page outlining rules you must respect. http://www.livejournal.com/bots/ -->
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop</id>
  <title>Smart Patrol</title>
  <subtitle>Suburban Robots That Monitor Reality</subtitle>
  <author>
    <email>skippenskop@yahoo.com</email>
    <name>Guybrush Threepwood</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/"/>
  <link rel="self" type="text/xml" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/data/atom"/>
  <updated>2005-09-21T18:55:36Z</updated>
  <link rel="service.feed" type="application/x.atom+xml" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/data/atom" title="Smart Patrol"/>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:176170</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/176170.html"/>
    <issued>2005-09-21T14:58:00</issued>
    <title>The Alphabet Backwards</title>
    <published>2005-09-21T18:55:36Z</published>
    <updated>2005-09-21T18:55:36Z</updated>
    <content type="html">There it was. The most majestic elephant I'd ever seen. A blue and red carpet draped over it's back, a dashing crown, tassels everywhere. The superhero of the animal kingdom. The spotlights shot in on it from both sides with faintly audible clicks. I'd heard for ages of circus elephants, how awe-inspiring their presence was. But also, to be sure, how dangerous they could be. Several fox prime time specials showing them trampling kids on bikes, throwing kids into pools, cracking their brains like peanuts. But when it turned its head and locked into my gaze I knew today was the day, I must have that elephant! The ringmaster looked a broken man when I approached him. Upon questioning, he explained that he was about to lose the circus because he needed to pay off hi third wife's gambling debts to her bookie. I explained that I did not intend to come across as such a selfish prick but oh how I desired his elephant. He smiled and looked at me for a moment before becoming instantly serious.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;"Kid, I've only got one thing tot ell you about that. And that is this: if you are going to buy yourself that elephant, you had better have a big enough backyard to deal with it."&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I laughed at the words as if I'd heard them a thousand times. My backyard was a sight to behold and one could never be sure what the invisible gardener had been doing to it, but I felt more ready than I have had and perhaps I ever would. He handed me the leash and I walked home in a adrenaline clouded haze. The fence gate parted and the elephant passed through easily in the yard. For a while I just stared at it, growing accustomed to its new surroundings. I took a few steps closer to where I could touch the beast. He felt so warm. It was now or never. I swallowed deep and began to climb him for a ride. The breeze felt so good atop his back, high above the trees. And the view was like nothing I'd ever seen throughout my grounded existence. The quiet serenity did not last long however and I felt my stomach lurch as the elephant took off like a bullet running around in waxing circles faster and faster until it leaped over the small farm house and darted between cars in the busy highway until finally reaching the old train tracks where it leaped and proceeded to roll all the way down the tunnel. We came to an abrupt stop and I flew off the elephants back, falling to my near doom until his trunk flew in front of him and snagged my wrist. I looked at him lovingly as he brought me up to his mouth and gulped me down. In his stomach the lights kept flickering on and off but I could hear the sweetest voice in the distance singing 'please don't change'.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The universe is my backyard.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:175993</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/175993.html"/>
    <issued>2005-09-16T10:46:00</issued>
    <title>Neither Wood Will</title>
    <published>2005-09-16T14:54:33Z</published>
    <updated>2005-09-16T20:14:57Z</updated>
    <content type="html">This week has already been so outside the lines and with another two days to go it is far from over. Especially if I don't leave my room as the carbon monoxide detector screeches. Or actually, 'unless' may be le mot juste. Somehow after going in for a doctor's appointment at work, I ended up taking over the meeting with the speech consultant and then proceeded to let myself be dragged into doing an overnight shift. So I just got home with a murderous headache and no turkey to speak of. Lots of vitamins though. And after intense consideration I am attempting a slightly blinded jump in most aspects of life. As is my trend of late. And tiny american flags for others. I can barely breathe, I better go upstairs.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:175786</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/175786.html"/>
    <issued>2005-09-15T03:48:00</issued>
    <title>At Any Given Moment</title>
    <published>2005-09-15T07:52:02Z</published>
    <updated>2005-09-15T07:52:02Z</updated>
    <content type="html">I learned to ride a bike today.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:175546</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/175546.html"/>
    <issued>2005-09-10T22:12:00</issued>
    <title>Deep voice off wet tiles</title>
    <published>2005-09-11T02:28:35Z</published>
    <updated>2005-09-11T02:28:35Z</updated>
    <content type="html">Oh, are you a sexy businessman in training? Do you share my feelings of having run yourself into a sweat drenched wall where we will stick?  You agree with me that you would also like to leave and that is ok for sure, for sure. Oh, there's someone behind you.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Seasonal concert report:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Wed 9/14: Clap Your Hands Say Yeah @ TT's&lt;br /&gt;Tues/Thurs/Fri 9/20,21,22: White Stripes @ Opera House&lt;br /&gt;Thurs 9/22: Dar Williams @ Sanders Theater&lt;br /&gt;Sat 9/24: Gravel Pit @ TT's&lt;br /&gt;Thurs 9/29: Beck @ Fleet Pavillion&lt;br /&gt;Sun 10/2: Metric @ Paradise&lt;br /&gt;Mon 10/3: Presidents @ Middle East&lt;br /&gt;Wed 10/5: Raveonettes @ Axis&lt;br /&gt;Mon 10/10: Decemberists @ Avalon&lt;br /&gt;Fri 10/14: Detroit Cobras @ Middle East&lt;br /&gt;Sat 10/15: Franz Ferdinand @ Orpheum&lt;br /&gt;Mon 10/17: Death Cab @ Orpheum&lt;br /&gt;Sat 10/22: Broken Social Scene @ Avalon&lt;br /&gt;Thurs 10/27: OKGo @ Middle East&lt;br /&gt;Mon 10/31: Dresden Dolls @ Avalon&lt;br /&gt;Thurs 11/2: Spoon @ Avalon&lt;br /&gt;Tues 11/8: NIN, QotSA, DFA79 @ Fleet Center&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Will search for more. I'm not rolling in the monies so I'm probably not going to many but yea. In other news, halfway there to being scheduled up at Salem despite the fact I''ve already fallen behind a few days. Meh, school and yea. In other news, 14 hour shift tomorrow. But in news I don't feel entirely apathetic towards at present, let's go get ice cream and halloween costumes.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:175234</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/175234.html"/>
    <issued>2005-09-08T01:23:00</issued>
    <title>You look more like a flooring inspector to me</title>
    <published>2005-09-08T06:06:51Z</published>
    <updated>2005-09-08T06:06:51Z</updated>
    <content type="html">So last semester, my adviser finally made herself available to me and we scheduled everything in. But I made one mistake of missing the telephone call in registration. And since Salem is the last college in the world to adopt internet registration it seems, I had to go to try myself at the registrar's office end of last term. Guy there said that since my adviser registered me for my psych courses that I couldn't do more until add/drop period at the beginning of this term. Then I get a letter (while I'm out of state for the one week I was gone and I don't actually find until way late) that NOTHING has been registered for me and I must go do it myself. I don't get it until after orientation's start for freshmen so now it's the first week of school and I still have no classes. Finally made it down there today since I've been working constantly lately and the line was down the hall, and didn't move more than a few feet for the like hour I stood there. So I guess I'm heading down once again super early tomorrow before work to try to get al squared away, get the classes I need. But at this point, if I can't get any classes that are remotely useful to me I have no idea what to do. Besides, of course, transfer my butt out of Salem asap. Not to say I'm faultless here but they're batting 1000 with messing up everything for me from their end, heh.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was out most of the weekend a week and a half ago and was pretty clueless as to the escalation of the Katrina situation and was horrified to see how bad it was. and then the only thing to make it worse is seeing how ridiculously bad the government handles the whole situation. It's absolutely stomach wrenching, all of it. Anyways, my knee-jerk reaction to drive down there and pull people out of the water is clearly over the top but I really wanna give what money I can, donate blood if they'll let me since I don't think my 8-10 weeks is up since my last time, and also I was talking to someone today about how their friend down there is trying to organize aid efforts and they pretty much need everything but especially things like tote/duffel bags and even toys and things you may not think about aside from food/water etc. Clothes too obviously. So if anyone wants in on anything lemmie know. I dunno, I doubt I can get much done but I feel like an ass sitting and eating my pancakes while the TV flashes death and destruction.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I really haven't been having all that much time to post though I think I was avoiding it anyways. I feel very comfortable coming here to piss and moan about the injustices of life (see: everything I've ever written) but I always feel bad for saying anything when I'm in a good mood. It's like gloating-feeling even though I don't mean it to be. Anticipated perceptions and all. Especially after going through friends pages full of other people doing the usual rantings. So yea I guess sorry if I get a little overexcited, I don't want people to feel like I'm abandoning the misery pit. Oh I will always have a home there. But okay, I really have been in super good spirits lately. Even with the school situation and even lots of shit happening at work. Hanging out at Becky + Jeannette's a bunch, seeing the GM a lot to end the summer, and, yes, the actualized improbability of me landing myself in a relationship once again. I think too that I've been too afraid of jinxing the whole thing to speak on it. But I'm feeling really really good about it, can't even describe. Just to even disprove my theory of me not being able to function in one never mind the actual awesomeness of it all.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:174977</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/174977.html"/>
    <issued>2005-09-06T02:09:00</issued>
    <title>Die Zukunft ist frei!</title>
    <published>2005-09-06T06:11:52Z</published>
    <updated>2005-09-06T06:13:25Z</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;img src="http://www.tentakelvilla.de/mi1/monkey-1.jpg"&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:174807</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/174807.html"/>
    <issued>2005-09-04T23:28:00</issued>
    <title>I haven't slept for 10 days because that would be too long</title>
    <published>2005-09-05T03:48:12Z</published>
    <updated>2005-09-05T03:48:12Z</updated>
    <content type="html">One of the lights in this room is all but burnt out so it faintly glows when you turn it on but every once in a while it will flicker really bright for an instant and it's like my own personal quassi-thunderstorm. If I go take a shower and bang things around then whoa, lookout realism. Tomorrow's a holday which means mandatory extra long shift on my sister's birthday and also have to do two doctor's appointments tuesday so that means I'm stretching it to the last minute to go fix my schedule at Salem as they have continued their perfect record of fucking up my registration. Perhaps I won't wait for next fall and try to transfer early by the spring term. School. I'm sure I won't hate it or anything but I really hope I find something more to get out of it this year. But I'm really not the least bit worried, spent the last of my summer working a ton but bumming around having loads of fun inbetween. Although I sadly missed some people I really wanted to see before school really comes full swing at my face. But yea, as long as there is good company willing and available, I'll be all set. I need to start planning the not so distant future. While also indulging myself in youthful spontaneity. Apologies to those few who expressed enjoyment in reading my rants, I've been slacking. But I'd really rather see you in person anyhow. Let's go.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:174591</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/174591.html"/>
    <issued>2005-08-31T03:56:00</issued>
    <title>Snake Oil Salesmen</title>
    <published>2005-08-31T08:00:37Z</published>
    <updated>2005-08-31T08:00:37Z</updated>
    <content type="html">Hahaha, so ok at 4 in the morning while I'm slightly off my rocker, I turn on the tv against my gut instinct because I can't hadnel the silence and I need to catch some sleep. Background information. Ok so the first commercial that comes on says "50,000 people a day get stds that prevent them from having a baby. Use a condom every time". Does no one appriciate the irony in everything these days? It's everywhere! More prevelant than the wrath of nature. You're methods are dubious, you're products are shoddy, and your bargains are petty. This distraction brought to you by the whole damn alphabet.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:174203</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/174203.html"/>
    <issued>2005-08-29T02:58:00</issued>
    <title>Words words words</title>
    <published>2005-08-29T07:02:15Z</published>
    <updated>2005-08-29T07:11:45Z</updated>
    <content type="html">I love when a day or two goes by and it feel like a week. Whether it be for good reasons or bad. I love it. Perceptually cheating time.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;Nothing is unclear to the understanding; it is only when we fail to understand that things appear unintelligible and confused.&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:174024</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/174024.html"/>
    <issued>2005-08-23T02:54:00</issued>
    <title>Whisper whisper</title>
    <published>2005-08-23T07:57:58Z</published>
    <updated>2005-08-23T08:01:02Z</updated>
    <content type="html">That was the shot and this is the chaser I suppose. I don't usually do chasers. If you don't like something enough to need to follow it immediately with something better than there's probably not a whole lot of reason to do it. Unless, or course, you're doing it for the benefit of someone else I suppose. But, of course, we're talking about smiles and similes here. Anyhow, down the hatch. I had a superbly fantastic adverb adjective weekend. I don't even know if I can expound everything without cheapening it. But needless to say again, things just seem to be clicking all around and I'm in a exasperatingly good mood in recent days. Hopefully things keep on the right path and even when school starts I can still say all that. Which is very soon. But not just yet.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Amidst the sprawling clutter upstairs is the curvy clock, one of many I'd wanted, and the table it sat on. And another memento that ended up finding our seventh of the wheel, was the candy dish. I swear, there has never been a product made that is harder to avoid any noise with then this candy dish. Sneaking a piece of candy while even the nearest ear is across the house is an honorable accomplishment. In good times, it was always always filled with something very delicious that I would've never paid a second glance to in a store but craved whenever in its presence. Just like the bucket of dirty, corroded building blocks in the tub next to it. When identical ones were brought into this house they were never touched, but the old ones there were always a prize to be one.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;At the tail end of my saturday sitting on the porch, I waited and waited to hear back from Alyson and in the end we did nothing as it turns out Lee is severely ill again. She had a terrible fever and a stiff neck. At first we thought it was lyme disease in remission from last summer but after being rushed for a spinal tap again, there are apparently worse fears now. Some people just have the worst string of luck in such specific ways. I hope she's ok.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I inadvertently caught a very specific and committed persona respond to someone admonishing them for squandering such vast talent on such shit material. By saying something like I (whichever verb of choice) whatever I find entertaining. And I couldn't help but smile and then feel silly for letting my social mirror criticism or whatever it should be called get in the way so much.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Everywhere I sit in my room there's a half full bottle of water ready to drink. I cut myself while preparing a salad today and have an xacceptablecorex battle scar. I'm going to return to the make your own noise instead of turning on the tv policy. I'm gonna do my best to keep paranoia and procrastination in check so I can do what it takes to get me where I wanna be. I'm gonna make silly bold statements until I've realized I've gone too far and lost sight of everything, ha. But really, I'm just gonna go blast my guitar and call out of work tomorrow since my car is at the mechanic's.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a name="cutid1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Don't fall in love with me yet&lt;br /&gt;We only recently met&lt;br /&gt;True I'm in love with you but&lt;br /&gt;you might decide I'm a nut&lt;br /&gt;Give me a week or two to&lt;br /&gt;go absolutely cuckoo&lt;br /&gt;then, when you see your error,&lt;br /&gt;then, you can flee in terror&lt;br /&gt;like everybody else does&lt;br /&gt;I only tell you this cause&lt;br /&gt;I'm easy to get rid of&lt;br /&gt;but not if you fall in love&lt;br /&gt;Know now that I'm on the make&lt;br /&gt;and if you make a mistake&lt;br /&gt;my heart will certainly break&lt;br /&gt;I'll have to jump in a lake&lt;br /&gt;and all my friends will blame you&lt;br /&gt;There's no telling what they'll do&lt;br /&gt;It's only fair to tell you&lt;br /&gt;I'm absolutely cuckoo&lt;br /&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:173342</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/173342.html"/>
    <issued>2005-08-23T02:20:00</issued>
    <title>when will we will hope so?</title>
    <published>2005-08-23T06:44:13Z</published>
    <updated>2005-08-23T06:48:44Z</updated>
    <content type="html">I'm pretty sure the spiders are coming from the ceiling. And then the &lt;b&gt;phone rang&lt;/b&gt; so I jumped out of the shower and threw a towel around my waist out of instinct and bolted from the moorhtab. I asked how she was doing and her familiar voice said &lt;marquee&gt;'I think I have the wrong number'&lt;/marquee&gt;I had not even begun to [wet myself], so I popped in a video and pressed  &amp;gt;&amp;gt;fast foward&amp;gt;&amp;gt;  to pass a little time. Something about spiders coming from the ceiling. An unnatural and self-contained &lt;font color="brown"&gt;fog&lt;/font&gt; surrounds me whenever I come to a stop. It smells like h-e-a-t and your favorite neurotransmitters. I guess I'll take the blame like your run of the mill &lt;i&gt;goat sucker&lt;/i&gt;. I said that "everything" is "completely" unrepresentative of reality "until" I reminded myself that "the" spiders "are probably" coming from "the ceiling". Smile in the mirror when it   reminds   you.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:173307</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/173307.html"/>
    <issued>2005-08-15T00:08:00</issued>
    <title>The Ass.</title>
    <published>2005-08-15T04:28:52Z</published>
    <updated>2005-08-15T04:28:52Z</updated>
    <content type="html">I realized that, sensibly enough, the more I'm doing the less I post. So lots of goodness gets left behind and I tend to rant here mostly just when I'm bored. Or frustrated with work or what not. Needs to change. But jeepers, I've having a blast living my life lately. I'm so tired from 14 hours shift today and have to prepare for antoher tomorrow and apparently another on tuesday as well so I was assuming I'd never get around to writing anything. Pretty much ever. But hey, you can just go read Audrey's journal for recap of friday-saturday mostly. Except it's way more awesome cause it's from her perspective instead of mine. More people should do that, I think I'd enjoy the memories even more. I'm such a spoiled brat with all the ridiculously awesome people that I can manage to surround myself with sometimes. Super spoiled. But keep on being awesome people and I will do my best to appriciate you. I'd go on and on but yea, I sadly really must try to sleep but just a check in. Still don't have my words but feelin' good.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Elliot Smith owns everyone at Mrs. Pacman.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:172849</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/172849.html"/>
    <issued>2005-08-11T02:24:00</issued>
    <title>For satisfying the child within...</title>
    <published>2005-08-11T06:27:41Z</published>
    <updated>2005-08-11T06:27:41Z</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;a href="http://www.boingtoys.com"&gt;Boing!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm gonna get me some doinket.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:172746</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/172746.html"/>
    <issued>2005-08-09T23:56:00</issued>
    <title>Yea, but that's like being the world's tallest midget</title>
    <published>2005-08-10T04:40:59Z</published>
    <updated>2005-08-10T04:40:59Z</updated>
    <content type="html">Tonight, on my way home, I was thinking of how chaoticly wonderful it would be if some bizarre occurance left the entire world without power for just an hour. In the middle of the night. But it didn't take long for rationality to catch up and think of the impending death and destruction that would result in. That made me sad, the inescapable logic. I still have a little shinji on my shoulder that tells me not to run away but I've replaced my consistent stand your ground attitude with an 'excuse me me, i'm stepping outside for a moment' approach for the moment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dear lady in the shorts, put your dog on a leash. You are stuck in the house. You are washing the clothes, put the clothes in the dryer! You are stuck in the truck. You are washing the truck, put the truck in the dryer! I want you to talk on the telephone into my ear.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;My offer to work tomorrow wasn't needed and I'm feeling pretty good about that in hindsight. I never made an official list of stuff I wanted to do this summer but it probably would've jsut made me feel like I got nothing done. It's been pretty ok, but there's still time left. I'd definitely like to see Me And You And Everyone We Know again. Among doing several other things. I think my point is I'm here, let's go.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Oh, and by the way, just to ring my bell, toot my horn, and pine for my bellhorn, my latest scores in sweeping mines (combolated): 4-24-72</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:172290</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/172290.html"/>
    <issued>2005-08-04T03:28:00</issued>
    <title>Let's Nail EVERYTHING To The Walls!</title>
    <published>2005-08-04T08:09:58Z</published>
    <updated>2005-08-04T08:16:41Z</updated>
    <content type="html">Man: Have you ever had a friend that just seemed so amazing of a person. Like, they may seem a bit far gone to the rest of the world and maybe even to themselves but they seem to so have it together, really know what's going on. So much so that you feel intimidated to be around them. Afraid that, even though you think they're so awesome as to not judge, that they will look at what you do, say, the person you are, and find they can do nothing but look down on you?&lt;br /&gt;Man, Another: Wow, you head the nail on the head there. I really do get that insecure feeling with some people. There are some people I admire to every extent, I'm not even sure they could understand that.&lt;br /&gt;Man: Ok good, that'll make this easier if you feel that way. I really don't want to see you anymore.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I think the multiple personalities angle needs a new twist. Nothing against Jekyll and Hyde but it's being run into the ground. People are certainly capable enough of being their own best antagonist, but the clear cut good and evil thing, meh. I wanna see two civilized halves that just entirely disagree. In some clever placements.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If my job was to unscrew metal shelving for 8 hours a day I think I would drown myself (if the spiders didn't do so first). No offense to any people who unscrew metal shelving for a living. But I, sir, have had my last screw.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I bet I could write&lt;br /&gt;anything formatted&lt;br /&gt;kind of like this&lt;br /&gt;and someone would surely&lt;br /&gt;believe it to be&lt;br /&gt;instantly&lt;br /&gt;poetic&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Isn't there some saying about how you should be running to good things rather than away from bad ones? Here upon this mountain, we eschew the use of lies in our food or plumage. I want to make linguistic rainbows. But I'll have to settle for mumbley puddles for now.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:172059</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/172059.html"/>
    <issued>2005-08-02T00:47:00</issued>
    <title>The last leaves of autumn...</title>
    <published>2005-08-02T04:47:47Z</published>
    <updated>2005-08-02T04:47:47Z</updated>
    <content type="html">There's an electrical storm going on outside and it's absolutely beautiful. Open highways illuminated by the flashes, bolts streaking across the sky. Reminds me of one I saw a long time ago when I was staying at a hotel between days of one of my older sister's aau basketball tournaments. There were lightning bolts coming down every few seconds. I certainly have a crush on every thunderstorm.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The angel of death is away...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I have a strong rekindled urge to write Loom and The Secret Of Monkey Island into screen plays. Maybe Bubble Bobble too.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;HURRY!&lt;/i&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:171808</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/171808.html"/>
    <issued>2005-07-31T03:02:00</issued>
    <title>But something fresh for the palate would be nice</title>
    <published>2005-07-31T07:58:23Z</published>
    <updated>2005-07-31T08:04:08Z</updated>
    <content type="html">If you've ever had that feeling when you leave someone that it might be the last time you'll ever see them...well, I'm not sure how to end that sentence exactly. Maybe it's easier to say goodbye once you're already gone. I dunno, irrational thoughts. Or the idea of passing over some opportunity that you feel you should take but for some logical reason you pass over and lose forever. Something like that.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Just gotta keep moving foward. I may not be entirely in the clear but I don't feel bad about saying that I'm bothered by the levels I see people dwell on to obtain certain things. Maslow's Hierarchy. It's like, ok, it'd be nice if you could rid yourself of the basic needs and skip right on to the higher stuff but you obviously can't. Need to satisfy all that, and ok if you're going to eat, sleep, have sex, whatever go right ahead and take pleasure about it, I guess, don't feel guilty, but there's no reason to spend your life constantly indulging in them to the point that it's not keeping you from moving on. And ok eating and sleeping are entirely necessary. But the things people will do for sex. It really makes my head spin, stomach lurch with disgust sometimes. Trying not to make judgments and all, I'm sure I'll understand it all a bit better someday, but jesus. I guess it's almost more just the entirely self-serving nature that is particularly accentuated there.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Get thee to a nunnery! Saw Hamlet on the common tonight. Was hopeful until swimwear was introduced, ha. Didn't manage to get over to Aly's though, alas. And with working hours being basically doubled for the rest of the summer, time will be more scarce and I really could use more of it. But oh we need the money.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is going to be a very interesting year, I can feel it. And by a year I guess I mean I'm still basing years' beginnings and ends off of school calendars. We're all like electrons, the more we know about where we are or where we're going the less we know about the other. Rat-a-tat-tat. Always more interesting than before though, that was a fun bit of enlightenment. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There's this whole bit I've been dying to put down in writing but it keeps getting too complex in my head and I always get way too tired sitting here thinking about it so perhaps I'll just give in again.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:171734</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/171734.html"/>
    <issued>2005-07-29T18:58:00</issued>
    <title>Physical Challenge!</title>
    <published>2005-07-29T23:08:47Z</published>
    <updated>2005-07-29T23:16:22Z</updated>
    <content type="html">That was by far one of the strangest shows I've ever been to. Live Sex Acts = the village people if they played only keyboard guitars and did bad covers of bad 80's songs. Fashion Flesh = boy with table full of boxes with all sorts of knobs and dials waiting to be turned and release noise upon noise. TRS-80 = Heavy drums and bass with re-edited movies from the 60's. Freezepop = BOYSONFILM pogo pogo tennis pogo my worst guilty pleasure. I've already bougth tickets for Metric and The Decemberists and am still looking for other shows. And my wallet thought it was going to get nice and fat again, tsk tsk. That is all.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:171462</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/171462.html"/>
    <issued>2005-07-26T00:07:00</issued>
    <title>There is no 'i' in gang bang</title>
    <published>2005-07-26T04:27:37Z</published>
    <updated>2005-07-26T04:27:37Z</updated>
    <content type="html">I left a voice mail last night with someone I never met. And I droned on and on, tangenting in and out of my intended point as I usually tend to in voice mails. And today I find out that they died earlier in the day. There's some terribly odd feeling that puts in my stomach.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But before I dip this entry too far gone into morbid stuff, I've been having a super great time the past week or two, however long it's been. Actually, I've been having a pretty super summer overall. Not what I was expecting but definitely a good time none the less. Backtracking some: week ago Thursday I went to a bar with Steffy, Aj, and Cassie. Spent the following night at Becky and Jeannette's party and then ended up in the obscenely nice, warm water of Revere Beach (see the news reports since then to find out why I'm taking 9 showers a day now) with Sara, Pat, and Steve. Missed other Joe's party the next night but made it to Danielle's block party which was a fun time as always too. Work and work and then off to Maine with the artist formally known as the group marriage. Excellent time up there tubing and kayaking and beaching and going to the HHH show where I was by far the oldest person (sketch) and other Maine-related activities. So nice to see everyone. My liver is severely displeased with me as of late too. Came back and went to Jaimie's party and then more workings. Tomorrow will be nice too, to have a day just to myself. But yea, that's the skelton outline of my life and times lately. Nothing really to complain about for once, which is pretty outlandish. Uhh, my boss is finally out for the next few months due to baby related issues so I guess that'll mean heapings of more work but I'm actually looking forward to more of a challenge there too. So yea, that's about it. Just checking in *click click*. Still got about a month left, let's use it. C-c-camping. K-k-kings.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:171119</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/171119.html"/>
    <issued>2005-07-18T22:48:00</issued>
    <title>Anything else would've been better</title>
    <published>2005-07-19T03:25:10Z</published>
    <updated>2005-07-19T03:27:17Z</updated>
    <content type="html">When they found him, he was curled up on his side in the tub of the upstairs bathroom. All the lights in the house were still on. It was evident that he had been doing his best to keep his innards from slipping through the gaping hole in his abdomen. The detective stared at him for a good five minutes although it seemed like a mere few second. Pondering over how the previous Sunday she had seen him in line at the supermarket. The 12 items or less line. Or didn't it used to be the ten items or less line? Anything to encourage shopping. On his kitchen windowsill was a small vase of wilted plastic flowers. Either a a purposeful clever statement by the man who saw the world so bleakly comical or an ironic occurrence for a man who was so far detached from this world. He was still wearing his blood soaked shirt but his shoes were set aside neatly to the left of the sink. Only a mere trickle trail of it leading from the bedroom across the hall. The house was spotless other than that. The boy next door watched nervously through the blinds of his bedroom window but no one noticed this. He was not asked to be seen when the police questioned his parents. He thought about that as he slowly lost consciousness and gave way to alcohol poisoning in a bar bathroom a few weeks after his 23rd birthday. And he was again unrecognized by the detective when she mistakenly lifted his sheet briefly in the morgue instead of the intended corpse. She racked her brain over this case as well and would again fail to find resolution. There was never any solace for her, but at least she saved up to  by switching her car insurance to geico.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:170928</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/170928.html"/>
    <issued>2005-07-11T23:03:00</issued>
    <title>You. Go. Smoosh.</title>
    <published>2005-07-12T03:17:27Z</published>
    <updated>2005-07-12T03:17:27Z</updated>
    <content type="html">*ENTRY DELETED DUE TO TOO INDEPTH COMPLAINING ABOUT WORK - ANDREA WHERE ARE YOU, WE BOTH CLEARLY NEED TO VENT*</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:170573</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/170573.html"/>
    <issued>2005-07-11T00:11:00</issued>
    <title>The Legend Of The Golden Egg</title>
    <published>2005-07-11T04:35:48Z</published>
    <updated>2005-07-11T04:35:48Z</updated>
    <content type="html">The comedian and the cynic, in love at long last. I want to meet the blind mole-rat who did the color scheme for Huckleberry Hill's new playground. My hours are through the roof lately and the extra money is definitely a plus. But I cannot handle 5 days a week here, nor can I stomach too many more 14 hour shifts on no sleep. So the search begins for a second part time (FLEXIBLE) job. Drink lots of water and you will be nice and wet. I'd really like to say more + better + morebetter but sleep.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:170384</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/170384.html"/>
    <issued>2005-07-08T04:09:00</issued>
    <title>Unforgettable</title>
    <published>2005-07-08T08:34:30Z</published>
    <updated>2005-07-08T08:34:30Z</updated>
    <content type="html">I feel different. In so very many ways. For the first time in a long while. In general. Not just now, lately. But especially now. In realizing it anyways. Different than before now I mean. Different than anything else too, yes, but not specifically that. I want opportunity.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:170230</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/170230.html"/>
    <issued>2005-07-05T23:33:00</issued>
    <title>The city shot, the highway rolling</title>
    <published>2005-07-06T03:32:55Z</published>
    <updated>2005-07-06T03:32:55Z</updated>
    <content type="html">Went mini-golfing for the first time in a while with Kosta and Dan tonight. Ice cream too, mm. Ran into Ralph and his girlfriend at the driving range so I decided to test my luck there - it's definitely a lot easier than it looks. Will be in Maine two weeks from now, that's pretty super. Somehow managed to be approved for a credit card of sorts so I will be getting my computer tomorrow - not the best thing in the world (unaffordable) but with a few things thrown in, it should work for everything I need. Slowly everyone else has realized Keith Foulke is terrible, victory. I've been craving an ax for mutilating vegetables. I should go mess around with my room to prepare - next time I post it should be from the new computer. If I can stomach hooking it up to the collective disease known as the internet. Yeee.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:skippenskop:169930</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/skippenskop/169930.html"/>
    <issued>2005-07-04T06:28:00</issued>
    <title>THE HISTORY OF THE ATOM</title>
    <published>2005-07-04T10:27:06Z</published>
    <updated>2005-07-04T10:27:06Z</updated>
    <content type="html">Well, it's 6 in the morning on July 4th and for the second year in a row I a) haven't slept at all and b) will be working 14 hour shift. I don't think I know of much going on anyhow but still. Plus one person is now quitting and another who I did a favor for by agreeing to switch a shift in the fall is now going back on that and thusly messing with my schedule entirely. Plus the manager will be going out for having the baby soon. Plus nobody follows through on anything. So discouraging. It's been spilling over into personal time as well - I haven't been getting anything done around the house. Although I have managed to get out on occasion as of late. Dan, Jeannette, and Abby (if I can manage to maintain contact on a regular basis, heh) have all kinda stepped up as much as can be hoped for at this point for music-related activities which is cool. Been having really intense dreams and remembering them lately. God, I really could use a not 14 hour shift today. Death by fireworks. Need to go climb a mountain, and go to the beach, and go camping, and go to Walden, and run around. It's July and that's nice but IT'S JULY and days seem so long but go so fast.</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
