<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

<preface id="ch_preface" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Preface</title>

	<sect1 id="sc_about_manual">
		<title>About the manual</title>

		<para>
		Before starting on the subject of the Triceps CEP itself,
		I want to tell some things about the organization of this manual.
		</para>

		<para>
		It had grown quite large, and if it were printed on paper,
		I would have divided it into at least three volumes.
		But in the electronic form it's more convenient as a single
		document, this way the cross-references between any parts
		of it work seamlessly.
		</para>

		<para>
		The manual keeps living and growing together with Triceps
		itself. As things change in Triceps, they change in the manual,
		but sometimes it's difficult to track down and update all
		the mentions of the changed subject. I've been spending
		a huge effort on tracking all such instances down but
		sometimes things slip through. Keep this in mind and
		don't be too scared when some paragraph says something
		contradictory.
		</para>

		<para>
		A known issue with this manual is that it tends to describe
		the subjects in the bottom-up fashion, starting from the
		low-level details and then building up to the high-level
		concepts. This is partially because the manual has been
		growing together with Triceps, which is being built from
		the ground up. And partially it's because I like the details.
		When I read about a product, I want to understand, how
		exactly it works. When I write, I want to convey this
		information. I rewrote some of the chapters to put the
		high-level descriptions up front. But it's a huge work
		that will take some time to complete for the whole manual.
		In the meantime, I'd rather not delay the releases for it,
		they've been already slowed a lot by the documentation work.
		So it will get better with time, and in the meantime,
		if you feel that some details are too much for you,
		feel free to skip over them.
		</para>

		<para>
		There are great many other improvements that can be done
		to the manual, and they will eventually be done. But my take on
		it is that it's better to have an imperfect manual now than
		a perfect one in some distant future. It had already been too
		long in the works, writing the manual for the version 2.0
		had taken a whole year.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_preface_concepts">
		<title>Some concepts</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>model</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		When talking about the CEP programs, I often use the term <quote>model</quote>.
		What is a model? It's basically a CEP program. And more about the models
		and about what is the CEP itself is described in
		<xref linkend="ch_field" xrefstyle="select: label"/>&#xA0;.
		</para>

		<para>
		Many of the examples are built around the world of stock trading.
		In the modern times almost everyone is probably familiar with the
		basics of this area. But if case if you're not, let me tell the
		most fundamental thing needed for understanding the examples:
		what is a <i>symbol</i>.
		</para>

		<para>
		When the stock shares of some company are traded on an exchange,
		this company gets assigned a short identifier. This identifier
		is known as the stock symbol for this company. This word is also
		often used to mean not just the identifier but also the shares
		denoted by it. If a company has multiple classes of shares, each
		class would have its own symbol. And if a company is traded on
		multiple exchanges, each exchange may have its own identifier for
		its shares. The options and other derivative financial
		products also have their own symbols.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</preface>
