<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

<chapter id="ch_field" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>The field of CEP</title>

	<sect1 id="sc_what_is_cep">
		<title>What is the CEP?</title>

		<para>
		CEP stands for the Complex Event Processing.  If you look at Wikipedia,
		it has separate articles for the Event Stream Processing and the
		Complex Event Processing. In reality it's all the same thing, with the
		naming driven by the marketing. I would not be surprised if someone
		invents yet another name, and everyone will start jumping on that
		bandwagon too.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>CEP</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>ESP</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		In general a CEP system can be thought of as a black box, where the
		input events come in, propagate in some way through that black box, and
		come out as the processed output events. There is also an idea that the
		processing should happen fast, though the definitions of <quote>fast</quote> vary
		widely.
		</para>

		<para>
		If we open the lid on the box, there are at least three ways to think
		of its contents:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		a spreadsheet on steroids
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		a data flow machine
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		a database driven by triggers
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>spreadsheet</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>data flow</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>trigger</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>model</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Hopefully you've seen a spreadsheet before. The cells in it are tied
		together by formulas. You change one cell, and the machine goes and
		recalculates everything that depends on it. So does a CEP system. If we
		look closer, we can discern the CEP engine (which is like the
		spreadsheet software), the CEP model (like the formulas in the
		spreadheet) and the state (like the current values in the
		spreadsheet). An incoming event is like a change in an input
		cell, and the outgoing events are the updates of the values in the
		spreadsheet. 
		</para>

		<para>
		Only a typical CEP system is bigger: it can handle some very complicated
		formulas and many millions of records. There actually are products that
		connect the Excel spreadsheets with the behind-the-curtain computations
		in a CEP system, with the results coming back to the spreadsheet
		cells. Pretty much every commercial CEP provider has a product
		that does that through the Excel RT interface. The way these models are
		written are not exactly pretty, but the results are, combining the nice
		presentation of spreadsheets and the speed and power of CEP.
		</para>

		<para>
		A data flow machine, where the processing elements are exchanging
		messages, is your typical academical look at CEP. The events
		represented as data rows are the messages, and the CEP model describes
		the connections between the processing elements and their internal
		logic. This approach naturally maps to the multiprocessing, with each
		processing element becoming a separate thread. The hiccup is that the
		research in the dataflow machines tends to prefer the non-looped
		topologies. The loops in the connections complicate the things.
		</para>

		<para>
		And many real-world relational databases already work very similarly to
		the CEP systems. They have the constraints and triggers propagating these
		constraints. A trigger propagates an update on one table to an update
		on another table. It's like a formula in a spreasheet or a logical
		connection in a dataflow graph.  Yet the databases usually miss two
		things: the propagation of the output events and the notion of being
		<quote>fast</quote>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The lack of propagation of the output events is totally baffling to me:
		the RDBMS engines already write the output event stream as the redo
		log. Why not send them also in some generalized format, XML or
		something? Then people realize that yes, they do want to get the output
		events and start writing some strange add-ons and aftermarket solutions
		like the log scrubbers. This has been a mystery to me for some 15
		years. I mean, how more obvious can it be? But nobody budges. Well,
		with the CEP systems gaining popularity and the need to connect them to
		the databases, I think it will eventually grow on the database vendors
		that a decent event feed is a competitive advantage, and I think it
		will happen somewhere soon. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The feeling of <quote>fast</quote> or lack thereof has
		to do with the databases being stored on disks. The growth of CEP has
		coincided with the growth in RAM sizes, and the data is usually kept
		completely in memory. People who deploy CEP tend to want the
		performance not of hundreds or thousands but hundreds of thousands
		events per second. The second part of <quote>fast</quote> is connected with the
		transactions. In a traditional RDBMS a single event with all its
		downstream effects is one transaction. Which is safe but may cause lots
		of conflicts. The CEP systems usually allow to break up the logic into
		multiple loosely-dependent layers, thus cutting on the overhead.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_uses_of_cep">
		<title>The uses of CEP</title>

		<para>
		Despite what Wikipedia says (and honestly, the Wikipedia articles on
		CEP and ESP are not exactly connected with reality), the pattern detection is <b>not</b> your
		typical usage, by a wide, wide margin. The typical usage is for the
		data aggregation: lots and lots of individual events come in, and you
		want to aggregate them to keep a concise and consistent picture for the
		decision-making. The actual decision making can be done by humans
		or again by the CEP systems. It may involve some pattern recognition
		but usually even when it does, it doesn't look like patterns, it looks
		like conditions and joins on the historical chains of events.
		</para>

		<para>
		The usage in the cases I know of includes the
		ad-click aggregation, the decisions to make a market trade, the
		watching whether the bank's end-of-day balance falls within the
		regulations, the choosing the APR for lending.
		</para>

		<para>
		A related use would be for the general alert consoles. The data
		aggregation is what they do too. The last time I worked with it up close
		(around 2006), the processing in the BMC Patrol and Nagios was just
		plain inadequate for anything useful, and I had to hand-code the data
		collection and console logic. I've been touching this issue recently
		again at Google, and apparently nothing has changed much since then.
		All the real monitoring is done with the systems developed in-house.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Sybase</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		But the CEP would have been just the
		ticket. I think, the only reason why it has not been widespread yet is
		that the commercial CEP licenses had cost a lot. But with the
		all-you-can-eat pricing of Sybase, and with the Open Source systems,
		this is gradually changing.
		</para>

		<para>
		Well, and there is also the pattern matching. It has been lagging
		behind the aggregation but growing too.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_landscape">
		<title>Surveying the CEP langscape</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Sybase</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Aleri</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Coral8</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>StreamBase</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		What do we have in the CEP area now? The scene is pretty much dominated
		by Sybase (combining the former competitors Aleri and Coral8) and StreamBase.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>execution model</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		There seem to be two major approaches to the execution model. One was
		used by Aleri, another by Coral8 and StreamBase. I'm not hugely
		familiar with StreamBase, but that's how it seems to me. Since I'm much
		more familiar with Coral8, I'll be calling the second model the Coral8
		model. If you find StreamBase substantially different, let me know.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>materialized view</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>SQL</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The Aleri idea is to collect and keep all the data. The relational
		operators get applied on the data, producing the derived data
		("materialized views") and eventually the results. So, even though the
		Aleri models were usually expressed in XML (though an SQL compiler was
		also available), fundamentally it's a very relational and SQLy
		approach.
		</para>

		<para>
		This creates a few nice properties. All the steps of execution can be
		pipelined and executed in parallel. For persistence, it's fundamentally
		enough to keep only the input data (what has been called BaseStreams
		and then SourceStreams), and all the derived computations can be easily
		reprocessed on restart (it's funny but it turns out that often it's
		faster to read a small state from the disk and recalculate the rest
		from scratch in memory than to load a large state from the disk).
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>SPLASH</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		It also has issues. It doesn't allow loops, and the procedural
		calculations aren't always easy to express. And keeping all the state
		requires more memory. The issues of loops and procedural computations
		have been addressed in Aleri by FlexStreams: modules that would perform the
		procedural computations instead of relational operations, written in
		SPLASH &emdash; a vaguely C-ish or Java-ish language. However this tends to
		break the relational properties: once you add a FlexStream,
		usually you do it for the reasons that prevent the derived
		calculations from being re-done, creating issues with saving and
		restoring the state. Mind you, you can write a FlexStream that doesn't
		break any of them, but then it would probably be doing something that
		can be expressed without it in the first place.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>CCL</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Coral8 has grown from the opposite direction: the idea has been to
		process the incoming data while keeping a minimal state in the variables
		and short-term <i>windows</i> (limited sliding recordings of the incoming
		data). The language (CCL) is very SQL-like. It relies on the state of
		variables and windows being pretty much global (module-wide), and
		allows the statements to be connected in loops. Which means that the
		execution order matters a lot. Which means that there are some quite
		extensive rules, determining this order. The logic ends up being very
		much procedural, but written in the peculiar way of SQL statements and
		connecting streams.
		</para>

		<para>
		The good thing is that all this allows to control the execution order
		very closely and write things that are very difficult to express in
		the pure un-ordered relational operators. Which allows to aggregate the
		data early and creatively, keeping less data in memory.
		</para>

		<para>
		The bad news is that it limits the execution to a single thread. If you
		want a separate thread, you must explicitly make a separate module, and
		program the communications between the modules, which is not exactly
		easy to get right. There are lots of people who do it the easy way and
		then wonder, why do they get the occasional data corruption. Also, the
		ordering rules for execution inside a module are quite tricky. Even for
		some fairly simple logic, it requires writing a lot of code, some of which
		is just bulky (try enumerating 90 fields in each statement), and some
		of which is tricky to get right.
		</para>

		<para>
		The summary is that everything is not what it seems: the Aleri models
		aren't usually written in SQL but are very declarative in their
		meaning, while the Coral8/StreamBase models are written in an SQL-like
		language but in reality are totally procedural.
		</para>

		<para>
		Sybase is also striking for a middle ground, combining the features
		inherited from Aleri and Coral8 in its CEP R5 and later: use the CCL
		language but relax the execution order rules to the Aleri level, except
		for the explicit single-threaded sections where the order is important.
		Include the SPLASH fragments for where the outright procedural logic is
		easy to use. Even though it sounds hodgy-podgy, it actually came
		together pretty nicely. Forgive me for saying so myself since I've done
		a fair amount of design and the execution logic implementation for it
		before I've left Sybase.
		</para>

		<para>
		Still, not everything is perfect in this merged world. The SQLy syntax
		still requires you to drag around all your 90 fields into nearly every
		statement. The single-threaded order of execution is still non-obvious.
		It's possible to write the procedural code directly in SPLASH but the
		boundary where the data passes between the SQLy and C-ish code still
		has a whole lot of its own kinks (less than in Aleri but still a lot).
		And worst of all, there is still no modular programming. Yeah, there
		are <quote>modules</quote> but they are not really reusable. They are
		tied too tightly to the schema of the data. What is needed, is more
		like &Cpp; templates. Only preferrably something more flexible and
		less difficult to debug than the &Cpp; templates.
		</para>

		<para>
		Let me elaborate a little on the point of <quote>dragging around all your
		fields</quote>. Here is a typical example: you have a stream of data
		and you want to pass through only the rows that find a match in some
		reference table. Which is reasonable to do with something like:
		</para>

<pre>
insert into filtered_data
select
	incoming_data.*
from 
	incoming_data as d left join reference_table as r
	on d.key_field = r.key_field;
</pre>

		<para>
		Only you can't write <pre>incoming_data.*</pre> in their syntax,
		you have to list every single field of it explicitly. If the data
		has 90 fields, that becomes quite a drag.
		</para>

		<para>
		StreamBase does have modules with parametrizable arguments (<quote>
		capture fields</quote>), somewhat like the &Cpp; templates. The limitation
		is that you can say <quote>and carry any additional fields through 
		unchanged</quote> but can't really specify subsets of fields
		for a particular usage (<quote>and use these fields as a key</quote>).
		Or at least that's my understanding. I haven't used it in practice
		and don't understand StreamBase too well.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_1950s">
		<title>We're not in 1950s any more, or are we?</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>CCL</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Part of the complexity with CCL programming is that the CCL programs
		tend to feel very broken-up, with the flow of the logic jumping all
		over the place.
		</para>

		<para>
		Consider a simple example: some incoming financial information may
		identify the securities by either RIC (Reuters identifier) or SEDOL
		or ISIN, and before processing it further we want to convert them
		all to ISIN (since the fundamentally same security may be identified in
		multiple ways when it's traded in multiple countries, ISIN is the
		common denominator). 
		</para>

		<para>
		This can be expressed in CCL approximately like this (no guarantees
		about the correctness of this code, since I don't have a compiler to
		try it out):
		</para>

<pre>
// the incoming data
create schema s_incoming (
  id_type string, // identifier type: RIC, SEDOL or ISIN
  id_value string, // the value of the identifier
  // add another 90 fields of payload...
);

// the normalized data
create schema s_normalized (
  isin string, // the identity is normalized to ISIN
  // add another 90 fields of payload...
);

// schema for the identifier translation tables
create schema s_translation (
  from string, // external id value (RIC or SEDOL)
  isin string, // the translation to ISIN
);

// the windows defining the translations from RIC and SEDOL to ISIN
create window w_trans_ric schema s_translation
  keep last per from;
create window w_trans_sedol schema s_translation
  keep last per from;

create input stream i_incoming schema s_incoming;
create stream incoming_ric  schema s_incoming;
create stream incoming_sedol  schema s_incoming;
create stream incoming_isin  schema s_incoming;
create output stream o_normalized schema s_normalized;

insert
  when id_type = 'RIC' then incoming_ric
  when id_type = 'SEDOL' then incoming_sedol
  when id_type = 'ISIN' then incoming_isin
select *
from i_incoming;

insert into o_normalized
select
  w.isin,
  i. ... // the other 90 fields
from
  incoming_ric as i join w_tranc_ric as w
    on i.id_value =  w.from;

insert into o_normalized
select
  w.isin,
  i. ... // the other 90 fields
from
  incoming_sedol as i join w_tranc_sedol as w
    on i.id_value =  w.from;

insert into o_normalized
select
  i.id_value,
  i. ... // the other 90 fields
from
  incoming_isin; 
</pre>

		<para>
		Not exactly easy, is it, even with the copying of payload data skipped?
		You may notice that what it does could also be expressed as procedural
		pseudo-code:
		</para>

<pre>
// the incoming data
struct s_incoming (
  string id_type, // identifier type: RIC, SEDOL or ISIN
  string id_value, // the value of the identifier
  // add another 90 fields of payload...
);

// schema for the identifier translation tables
struct s_translation (
  string from, // external id value (RIC or SEDOL)
  string isin, // the translation to ISIN
);

// the windows defining the translations from RIC and SEDOL to ISIN
table s_translation w_trans_ric
  key from;
table s_translation w_trans_sedol
  key from;

s_incoming i_incoming;
string isin;

if (i_incoming.id_type == 'RIC') {
  isin = lookup(w_trans_ric, 
    w_trans_ric.from == i_incoming.id_value
  ).isin;
} elsif (i_incoming.id_type == 'SEDOL') {
  isin = lookup(w_trans_sedol, 
    w_trans_sedol.from == i_incoming.id_value
  ).isin;
} elsif (i_incoming.id_type == 'ISIN') {
  isin = i_incoming.id_value;
}

if (isin != NULL) {
  output o_ normalized(isin,
    i_incoming.(* except (id_type, id_value))
  );
}
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Fortran</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>GOTO</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Basically, writing in CCL feels like programming in Fortran in the 50s:
		lots of labels, lots of GOTOs. Each stream is essentially a label, when
		looking from the procedural standpoint. It's actually worse than
		Fortran, since all the labels have to be pre-defined (with types!). And
		there isn't even the normal sequential flow, each statement must be
		followed by a GOTO, like on those machines with magnetic-drum main
		memory.
		</para>

		<para>
		This is very much like the example in my book 
		<biblioref linkend="Babkin10"/>,
		in section 6.4. <i>Queues as the sole synchronization
		mechanism</i>. You can alook at the draft text online at <ulink
		url="http://web.newsguy.com/sab123/tpopp/06odata.txt"/>. This
		similarity is not accidental: the CCL streams are queues, and they are
		the only communication mechanism in CCL.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>SQL</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The SQL statement structure also adds to the confusion: each statement
		has the destination followed by the source of the data, so each
		statement reads like it flows backwards.
		</para>
	</sect1>

</chapter>

