<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

<chapter id="ch_enter_triceps" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Enter Triceps</title>

	<sect1 id="sc_triceps_reasons">
		<title>What led to it</title>

		<para>
		It had happened that I've worked for a while on and with the Complex Event
		Processing (CEP) systems. I've worked for a few years on the internals
		of the Aleri CEP engine, then after Aleri acquired Coral8, some on the
		Coral8 engine, then after Sybase gobbled up them both, I've designed
		and did the early implementation of a fair bit of the Sybase CEP R5.
		After that I've moved on to Deutsche Bank and got the experience from
		the other side: using the CEP systems, primarily the former Coral8,
		now known as Sybase CEP R4.
		</para>

		<para>
		This made me feel that writing the CEP models is unnecessarily
		difficult. Even the essentially simple things take too much effort.
		I've had this feeling before as well, but one thing is to have it in
		abstract, and another is to grind against it every day. 
		</para>

		<para>
		Which in turn led me to thinking about making my own Open Source CEP
		system, where I could try out the ideas I get, and make the streaming
		models easier to write. I aim to do better than the 1950's style, to
		bring the advances of the structured programming into the CEP world.
		</para>

		<para>
		Thus the Triceps project was born. For a while
		it was called Biceps, until I've learned of the existence of a recearch
		project called BiCEP. It's spelled differently, and is in a
		substantially differnt area of CEP work, but it's easier to avoid
		confusion, so I went one better and renamed mine Triceps.
		</para>

		<para>
		Since then I've moved on from DB, and I'm currently not using any CEP
		at work (though you never know what would happen), but Triceps has
		already gained momentum by itself.
		</para>

		<para>
		The Triceps development has been largely shaped by two considerations:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		It has to be different from the Sybase products on which I worked.
		This is helpful from both legal standpoint and from marketing
		standpoint: Sybase and StreamBase already have similar products that
		compete head to head. There is no use getting into the same fray
		without some major resources.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		It has to be small. I can't spend the same amount of effort on Triceps
		as a large company, or even as a small one. Not only this saves time
		but also allows the modifications to be easy and fast. The point of
		Triceps is to experiment with the CEP language to make it easy to use:
		try out the ideas, make sure that they work well, or replace them with
		other ideas. The companies with a large established product can't
		really afford the radical changes: they have invested much effort into
		the product, and are stuck with supporting it and providing
		compatibility into the future.
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Esper</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Both of these considerations point into the same direction: an
		embeddable CEP system. Adapting an integrated system for an embedded
		usage is not easy, so it's a good open niche. Yeah, this niche
		is not empty either.  There already is Esper.  But from a cursory look, it
		seems to have the same issues as Coral8/StreamBase. It's also
		Java-centric, and Triceps is aimed for embeddability into different 
		languages.
		</para>

		<para>
		And an embeddable system saves on a lot of components.
		</para>

		<para>
		For starters, no IDE. Anyway, I find the IDEs pretty useless for
		development in general, and especially for the CEP development. Though
		it comes handy once in a while for the analysis of the code and
		debugging.
		</para>

		<para>
		No new language, no need to develop compilers, virtual machines,
		function libraries, external callout APIs. Well, the major goal of
		Triceps actually is the development of a new and better language. But
		it's one of these paradoxes: Aleri does the relational logic looking
		like procedural, Coral8 and StreamBase do the procedural logic looking
		like relational, and Triceps is a design of a language without a
		language. Eventually there probably will be a language, to be mixed
		with the parent one. But for now a lot can be done by simply using the
		Triceps library in an existing scripting language. The existing
		scripting languages are already powerful, fast, and also support the
		dynamic compilation.
		</para>

		<para>
		No separate server executable, no need to control it, and no custom
		network protocols: the users can put the code directly into their
		executables and devise any protocols they please. Well, it's not a
		real good answer for the protocols, since it means that everyone who
		wants to communicate the streaming data for Triceps over the network
		has to implement these protocols from scratch. So eventually Triceps
		will provide a default implementation. But it doesn't have to be done
		right away.
		</para>

		<para>
		No data persistence for now either. It's a nice feature, and I have
		some ideas about it too, but it requires a large amount of work, and
		doesn't really affect the API. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The language used to implement Triceps is &Cpp;, and the scripting
		language is Perl. Nothing really prevents embedding Triceps into other
		languages but it's not going to happen anywhere soon. The reason being
		that extra code adds weight and makes the changes more difficult.
		</para>

		<para>
		The multithreading support has been a major consideration from the
		start. All the &Cpp; code has been written with the multithreading in
		mind. However for the first release the multithreading did not
		propagate into the Perl API yet.
		</para>

		<para>
		Even though Triceps is a system aimed for quick experimentation, that does not imply
		that it's of a toy quality. The code is written in production quality
		to start with, with a full array of unit tests. In fact, the only way
		you can do the quick experimentation is by setting up the proper
		testing from the scratch. The idea of <quote>move fast and break
		things</quote> is complete rubbish.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_hello_world">
		<title>Hello, world!</title>

		<para>
		Let's finally get to business: write a simple <quote>Hello, world!</quote> program with
		Triceps. Since Triceps is an embeddable library, naturally, the
		smallest <quote>Hello, world!</quote> program would be in the host language without
		Triceps, but it would not be interesting. So here is the a bit
		contrived but more interesting Perl program that passes some data
		through the Triceps machinery:
		</para>

<!-- perl/Triceps/t/xHelloWorld.t -->
<pre>
use Triceps;

$hwunit = Triceps::Unit->new("hwunit");
$hw_rt = Triceps::RowType->new(
	greeting => "string",
	address => "string",
);

my $print_greeting = $hwunit->makeLabel($hw_rt, "print_greeting", undef, sub { 
	my ($label, $rowop) = @_;
	&sendf("%s!\n", join(', ', $rowop->getRow()->toArray()));
} );

$hwunit->call($print_greeting->makeRowop(&Triceps::OP_INSERT, 
	$hw_rt->makeRowHash(
		greeting => "Hello",
		address => "world",
	)
));
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>unit</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		What happens there? First, we import the Triceps module.
		Then we create a Triceps execution unit. An execution unit keeps the
		Triceps context and controls the execution for one logical thread.
		</para>

		<para>
		The argument of the constructor is the name of the unit, that can be used
		in printing messages about it. It doesn't have to be the same as the
		name of the variable that keeps the reference to the unit, but it's a
		convenient convention to make the debugging easier. This is a common
		idiom of Triceps: when you create something, you give it a name. If
		any errors occur later with this object, the name will be present int
		the error message, and you'll be able to find easily, which object has
		the issue and where it was created.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>confess</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		If something goes wrong, the Triceps methods will confess. To be precise,
		call <pre>Carp::confess</pre>, which is like Perl's <pre>die</pre>
		but also prints the stack trace. Triceps also includes its own high-level
		call stack into this trace.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>row type</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The next statement creates the type for rows. For the simplest
		example, one row type is enough. It contains two string fields. A row
		type does not belong to an execution unit. It may be used in parallel
		by multiple threads. Once a row type is created, it's immutable, and
		that's the story for pretty much all the Triceps objects that can be
		shared between multiple threads: they are created, they become
		immutable, and then they can be shared. (Of course, the containers
		that facilitate the passing of data between the threads would have to
		be an exception to this rule).
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>GOTO</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Then we create a label.
		The <quote>label</quote> is the Triceps term for the
		same kind of stream processing elements as in the other CEP systems.
		The Coral8 term for the same concept is <quote>stream</quote>.
		The <quote>SQLy vs procedural</quote> example in
		<xref linkend="sc_1950s" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		shows why these elements are analogs of labels in the procedural programming,
		and Triceps generally follows the procedural terminology.
		</para>

		<para>
		Of course,
		now, in the days of the structured programming, we don't create labels
		for GOTOs all over the place. But we still use labels. The function
		names are essentially labels, the loops in Perl may have labels. So a Triceps
		label can often be seen kind of like a function definition, but
		only kind of. It takes a data row as a parameter and does something
		with it. But unlike a proper function it has no way to return the
		processed data back to the caller. It has to either pass the processed
		data to other labels or collect it in some hardcoded data structure,
		from which the caller can later extract it back.
		Thus a Triceps label is still much more like a GOTO label.
		</para>

		<para>
		Triceps has the streaming functions too, where the caller does provide
		the way to return the result. These are more than the ordinary labels.
		</para>

		<para>
		A basic label takes a row type for the rows it accepts, a name (again,
		purely for the ease of debugging) and a reference to a Perl function
		that will be handling the data. Extra arguments for the function can
		be specified as well, but there is no use for them in this example. 
		</para>

		<para>
		Here it's a simple unnamed Perl function. Though of course a reference
		to a named function can be used instead, and the same function may be
		reused for multiple labels. Whenever the label gets a row operation to
		process, its function gets called with the reference to the label
		object, the row operation object, and whatever extra arguments were
		specified at the label creation (none in this example). The example
		just prints a message combined from the data in the row.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>row operation</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Rowop</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Note that the label's handler function doesn't just get a row as an
		argument.  It gets a row operation (<quote>rowop</quote> as it's
		called throughout the code). It's an important distinction. A row just
		stores some data. As the row gets passed around, it gets referenced
		and unreferenced, but it just stays the same until the last reference
		to it disappears, and then it gets destroyed. It doesn't know what
		happens with the data, it just stores them. A row may be shared
		between multiple threads. On the other hand, a row operation says
		<quote>take these data and do such and such a thing with them</quote>.
		A row operation is a combination of a row of data, an operation code,
		and a label that has to carry out the operation. 
		Since the row operation object is also immutable,
		a reference to a row operation may
		be kept and reused again and again.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>opcode</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>operation code</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Triceps has the explicit operation codes, very much like Aleri/Sybase R5 (only
		Aleri doesn't differentiate between a row and row operation, every row
		there has an opcode in it). It
		might be just my background, but let me tell you: the CEP systems
		without the explicit opcodes are a pain. The visible opcodes make life
		a lot easier. However unlike Aleri, there is no UPDATE opcode. The
		available opcodes are INSERT, DELETE and NOP (no-operation). If you
		want to update something, you send two operations: first DELETE for
		the old value, then INSERT for the new value. All this will be
		described in more detail later.
		</para>

		<para>
		For this simple example, the opcode doesn't really matter, so the
		label handler function quietly ignores it. It gets the row from the
		row operation and extracts the data from it into the Perl
		representation, then prints them. The Triceps row data may be
		represented in Perl in two ways: an array and a hash. In the array
		format, the array contains the values of the fields in the order they
		are defined in the row type. The hash format consists of name-value
		pairs, which may be stored either in an actual hash or in an array.
		The conversion from a row to a hash actually returns an array of
		values which becomes a real hash if it gets stored into a hash
		variable.
		</para>

		<para>
		As a side note, this also suggests, how the systems without explicit
		opcodes came to be: they've been initially built on the simple
		stateless examples. And when the more complex examples have turned up,
		they've been aready stuck on this path, and could not afford too deep
		a retrofit.
		</para>

		<para>
		The final part of the example is the creation of a row operation for
		our label, with an INSERT opcode and a row created from hash-formatted
		Perl data, and calling it through the execution unit. The row type
		provides a method to construct the rows, and the label provides a
		method to construct the row operations for it. The <pre>call()</pre>
		method of the execution unit does exactly what its name implies: it
		evaluates the label function right now, and returns after all its
		processing its done.
		</para>

		<para>
		This is a very simple example, so it does only one call. The real
		Triceps programs get a stream of incoming data, and do the
		calls to handle each row of it.
		</para>
	</sect1>

</chapter>
