<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->


<chapter id="ch_api_fund" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>API Fundamentals</title>

	<sect1 id="sc_api_lang">
		<title>Languages and layers</title>

		<para>
		As mentioned before, at the moment Triceps provides the APIs in &Cpp; and
		Perl. They are similar but not quite the same, because the nature of
		the compiled and scripted languages is different. The &Cpp; API is more
		direct and expects discipline from the programmer: if some incorrect
		arguments are passed, everything might crash. The Perl API should never
		crash. It should detect any incorrect use and report an orderly error.
		Besides, the idioms of the scripted languages are different from the
		compiled languages, and different usages become convenient.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>C++</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		So far only the Perl API is documented in this manual. Its is considered
		the primary one for the end users, and also richer and easier to use.
		The &Cpp; API will be documented as well, just it didn't make the cut for
		the version 1.0. If you're interested in the &Cpp; API, read the Perl
		documentation first, to understand the ideas of Triceps, and then
		look in the source code. The &Cpp; classes have very extensive comments
		in the header files.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>XS</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>SWIG</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The Perl API is implemented in XS. Some people, may wonder, why not
		SWIG? SWIG would automatically export the API into many languages, not
		just Perl. The problem with SWIG is that it just maps the API
		one-to-one. And this doesn't work any good, it makes for some very ugly
		APIs with abilities to crash from the user code. Which then have to be
		wrapped into more scripting code before they become usable. So then why
		bother with SWIG, it's easier to just use the scripting language's
		native extension methods.  Another benefit of the native XS support is
		the access to the correct memory management.
		</para>

		<para>
		In general, I've tried to avoid the premature optimization. The idea is
		to get it working at all first, and then bother about working fast.
		Except for the cases when the need for optimization looked obvious, and
		the logic intertwined with the general design strongly ehough, that if
		done one way, would be difficult to change in the future. We'll see, if
		these <quote>obvious</quote> cases really turn out to be the obvious
		wins, or will they become a premature-optimization mess.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is usually more than one way to do something in Triceps. It has 
		been written in layers: There is the &Cpp; API layer on the bottom, then
		the Perl layer that closely parallels it, then more of the niceties
		built in Perl. There is more than one way to organize the manual,
		structuring it by features or by layers. Eventually I went in the
		order of the major features, discussing each one of them at various
		layers. 
		</para>

		<para>
		I've also tried to show, how these layers are built on top of each other
		and connected. Which might be too much detail for the first reading.
		If you feel that something is going over your head, just skim over it.
		It could be marked more clearly but I don't like this kind of marking.
		I hate the side-panels in the magazines. I like the text to flow smoothly
		and sequentially. I don't like the <quote>simplifications</quote> that
		distort the real meaning and add all kinds of confusion. I like
		having all the details I can get, and then I can skip over the ones
		that look too complicated (and read them again when they start making
		sense).
		</para>

		<para>
		Also, a major goal of Triceps is the extensibility.  And the best way
		to learn how to extend it, is by looking up close at how it has already
		been extended.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_confessions">
		<title>Errors, deaths and confessions</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>die</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>confess</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Carp</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		When the Perl API of Triceps detects an error, it makes the interpreter
		die with an error message. Unless of course you catch it with <pre>eval</pre>.
		The message includes the call stack as the method <pre>Carp::confess()</pre>
		would. <pre>confess()</pre> is a very useful method that helps a lot
		with finding the source of the problem, it's much better than the plain
		<pre>die()</pre>. Triceps uses internally the methods from Carp to build
		the stack trace in the message. But it also does one better: it includes the
		stack of the Triceps label calls into the trace.
		</para>

		<para>
		You are welcome to use <pre>confess</pre> directly as well, it's
		typically done in the following pattern:
		</para>

<pre>
&someFunction() or confess "Error message";
&someFunction() or confess "Error message: $!";
</pre>

		<para>
		This is what the Triceps methods implemented in Perl do. The variable
		<pre>$!</pre> contains the error messages from the methods that
		deal with the system errors.
		To require the
		package with <pre>confess</pre>, do:
		</para>

<pre>
use Carp;
</pre>

		<para>
		The full description of Carp is available at 
		<ulink url="http://perldoc.perl.org/Carp.html"/>.
		It has more functions, however I find the full
		stack trace the most helpful thing in any case.
		</para>

		<para>
		There also are modules to make all the cases of <pre>die</pre> work like <pre>confess</pre>,
		<pre>Devel::SimpleTrace</pre> and <pre>Carp::Always</pre>. They work by intercepting
		the pseudo-signals <pre>__WARN__</pre> and <pre>__DIE__</pre>. The logic of
		<pre>Carp::Always</pre> is pretty simple, see
		<ulink url="http://cpansearch.perl.org/src/FERREIRA/Carp-Always-0.11/lib/Carp/Always.pm"/>,
		so if you're not feeling like installing the module, you can easily do the same directly
		in your code.
		</para>

		<para>
		If you want to intercept
		the error to add more information to the message, use <pre>eval</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
eval { $self->{unit}->call($rowop) }
	or confess "Bad rowop argument:\n$@";
</pre>

		<para>
		I have some better ideas about reporting the errors in the nested
		templated but they need to be implemented and tried out yet.
		</para>

		<para>
		A known problem with <pre>confess</pre> in a threaded program
		is that it leaks the scalars, apparently by leaving garbage on the Perl stack,
		even when intercepted with <pre>eval</pre>. It's actually not a problem when the confession
		is not intercepted, then the program exits anyway. But if confessing
		frequently and catching these confessions, the leak can accumulate
		to something noticeable.
		</para>

		<para>
		The problem seems to be in the line 
		</para>

<pre>
package DB;
</pre>

		<para>
		in the middle of one
		of its internal functions. Perhaps changing the package in the middle
		of a function is not such a great idea, leaving some garbage on the
		stack. The most interesting part is that this line can be removed
		altogether, with no adverse effects, and then the leak stops.
		So be warned and don't be surprised. Maybe it will get fixed.
		</para>

		<para>
		Now let's look at how the &Cpp; parts of Triceps interact with confessions.
		When the Perl code inside a label or tracer or aggregator or index sorting handler dies, the &Cpp;
		infrastructure around it catches the error. 
		It unrolls the stack trace through the
		&Cpp; code and passes the <pre>die</pre> request to the Perl code that called it.
		If that Perl code was called through another Triceps &Cpp; code, that &Cpp; code
		will catch the error and continue unrolling the stack and reporting back to Perl.
		When one Perl label calls another
		Perl label that calls the third Perl label, the call sequence goes in layers of 
		Perl&emdash;&Cpp;&emdash;Perl&emdash;&Cpp;&emdash;Perl&emdash;&Cpp;&emdash;Perl. 
		If that last label has its Perl code die
		and there are no <pre>eval</pre>s in between, the stack will be correctly unwound
		back through all these layers and reported in the error message.  The &Cpp;
		code will include the reports of all the chained label calls as well.
		If one of the intermediate Perl layers wraps the call in <pre>eval</pre>,
		it will receive the error message with the stack trace up to that point.
		</para>

		<para>
		More of the error handling details will be discussed later in
		<xref linkend="sc_sched_unwind" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		and 
		<xref linkend="sc_template_wrapfess" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_memory_fund">
		<title>Memory management fundamentals</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>memory management</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The memory is managed in Triceps using the reference counters. Each
		Triceps object has a reference counter in it. In &Cpp; this is done
		explicitly, in Perl it gets mostly hidden behind the Perl memory
		management that also uses the reference counters. Mostly.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Autoref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		In &Cpp; the Autoref template is used to produce the reference objects.
		The memory management at the &Cpp; level is  described in more detail in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_mem" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		As the references are copied around between these objects, the
		reference counts in the target objects are automatically adjusted. When
		the reference count drops to 0, the target object gets destroyed. While
		there are live references, the object can't get destroyed from under
		them. All nice and well and simple, however still possible to get
		wrong.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The major problem with the reference counters is the reference cycles.
		If object A has a reference to object B, and object B has a reference
		(possibly, indirect) to object A, then neither of them will ever be
		destroyed. Many of these cases can be resolved by keeping a reference
		in one direction and a plain pointer in the other. This of course
		introduces the problem of hanging pointers, so extra care has to be
		taken to not reference them. There also are the unpleasant situations
		when there is absolutely no way around the reference cycles. For
		example, the Triceps label's method may keep a reference to the next
		label, where to send its processed results. If the labels are connected
		into a loop (a perfectly normal occurrence), this would cause a
		reference cycle. Here the way around is to know when all the labels are
		no longer used (before the thread exit), and explicitly tell them to
		clear their references to the other labels. This breaks up the cycle,
		and then bits and pieces can be collected by the reference count logic.
		</para>

		<para>
		The reference cycle problem can be seen all the way up into the Perl level.
		However Triceps provides the ready solutions for its typical occurences.
		To explain it, more about Triceps operation has to be explained first,
		so it's described in detail later in
		<xref linkend="ch_memory" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		The reference counting may be single-threaded or multi-threaded. If an
		object may only be used inside one thread, the references to it use the
		faster single-threaded counting. In &Cpp; it's real important to not
		access and not reference the single-threaded objects from multiple
		threads. In Perl, when a new thread is created, only the multithreaded
		objects from the parent thread become accessible for it, the rest become
		undefined, so the issue gets handled automatically (as of version 1.0
		even the potentially multithreaded objects are still exported to Perl
		as single-threaded, with no connection between threads yet).
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>wrapper</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The &Cpp; objects are exported into Perl through wrappers. The wrappers
		perform the adaptation between Perl reference counting and Triceps
		reference counting, and sometimes more of the helper functions. Perl
		sees them as blessed objects, from which you can inherit and otherwise
		treat like normal objects. 
		</para>

		<para>
		When we say that a Perl variable <pre>$label</pre> contains a Triceps
		label object, it really means that it contains a <i>referece</i> to
		a label object. When it gets copied like <pre>$label2 = $label</pre>,
		this copies the reference and now both variables refer to the same
		label object (more exactly, even to the same wrapper object). Any 
		changes to the object's state done through one
		reference will also be visible through the other reference.
		</para>

		<para>
		When the Perl references are copied between the variables, this
		increases the Perl reference count to the same wrapper object. However
		if an object goes into the &Cpp; land, and then is extracted back (such
		as, create a Rowop from a Row, and then extract the Row from that
		Rowop), a brand new wrapper gets created. It's the same underlying &Cpp;
		object but with multiple wrappers. You can't tell that it's the same
		object by comparing the Perl references, because they may be pointing
		to the different wrappers. However Triceps provides the method
		<pre>same()</pre> that compares the data inside the wrappers. It can be
		used as
		</para>

<pre>
$row1->same($row2)
</pre>

		<para>
		and if it returns true, then both <pre>$row1</pre> and <pre>$row2</pre> point to the same
		underlying row. 
		</para>

		<para>
		Note also that if you inherit from the Triceps objects
		and add some extra data to them, none of that data nor even your
		derived class'es identity will be preserved when a new wrapper is created
		from the underlying &Cpp; object.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_code">
		<title>Code references and snippets</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>code</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>XS</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Many of the Triceps Perl API objects accept the Perl code arguments,
		to be executed as needed. This code can be specified as either a function
		reference or a string containing the source code snippet.
		The major reason to accept the arguments in the source code format
		is the ability to pass them through between the threads, which cannot
		be done with the compiled code. See more information on that in 
		<xref linkend="sc_mt_objects" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;. 
		</para>

		<para>
		Only a few of the classes can be exported between the threads
		but for consistency all the classes support the code arguments in
		either format. This feature is built into the general way the
		Triceps XS methods handle the code references.
		</para>

		<para>
		The following examples are equivalent, one using a function
		reference, another using a source code snippet.
		Of course, if you know that the created object will be
		exported to another thread, you must use the source code
		format. Otherwise you can take your pick.
		</para>

<pre>
$it= Triceps::IndexType->newPerlSorted("b_c", undef, 
sub {
	my $res = ($_[0]->get("b") <=> $_[1]->get("b")
		|| $_[0]->get("c") <=> $_[1]->get("c"));
	return $res;
}
);

$it= Triceps::IndexType->newPerlSorted("b_c", undef, 
'
	my $res = ($_[0]->get("b") <=> $_[1]->get("b")
		|| $_[0]->get("c") <=> $_[1]->get("c"));
	return $res;
'
);
</pre>

		<para>
		As you can see, when specifying the handler as source code,
		you must specify only the function body, and the 
		<pre>sub { ... }</pre> will be wrapped around it implicitly.
		Including the <pre>sub</pre> would be an error.
		</para>

		<para>
		There are other differences between the code references and the
		source code format:
		</para>

		<para>
		When you compile a function, it carries with it the lexical context. So
		you can make the closures that refer to the <quote>my</quote> variables in their
		lexical scope. With the source code snippets you can't do this. 
		The source code gets compiled in the context of the main package,
		and that's all they can see. In some cases, it might not even be
		compiled immediately. If an object has an explicit initialization,
		the code snippets get compiled at the initialization time.
		And if the object is exported to another thread, the code snippets
		will be re-compiled when an object's copy is created and initialized in that
		another thread.  Remember also that the global
		variables are not shared between the threads, so if you refer to a
		global variable in the code snippet and rely on a value in that
		variable, it won't be present in the other threads (unless the other
		threads are direct descendants and the value was set before their
		creation).
		</para>

		<para>
		The code written in Perl can make use of the source code snippets as well.
		If it just passes these code arguments to the XS methods, it
		will get this support automatically. But if it wants to call
		these snippets directly from the Perl code, Triceps provides
		a convenience method that would accept the code in either format
		and compile it if needed:
		</para>

<pre>
$code = Triceps::Code::compile($code_ref_or_source);
</pre>

		<para>
		It takes either a code reference or a source code string as an argument
		and returns the reference to the compiled code. If the argument was a
		code reference, it just passes through unchanged. If it was a source
		code snippet, it gets compiled (and the rules are the same, the text
		gets the <pre>sub { ... }</pre> wrapper added around it implicitly).
		</para>

		<para>
		If the argument was an <pre>undef</pre>, it also passes through unchanged. This is
		convenient in case if the code is optional. But if it isn't then the
		caller should check for <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		If the compilation fails, the method confesses, and includes the error
		and the source code into the message, in the same way as the XS methods
		do.
		</para>

		<para>
		The optional second argument can be used to provide information
		about the meaning of the code for the error messages. If it's undefined
		then the default is <quote>Code snippet</quote>:
		</para>

<pre>
$code = Triceps::Code::compile($code_ref_or_source, $description);
</pre>

		<para>
		For example, if the code represents an error handler,
		the call can be done as follows:
		</para>

<pre>
$code = Triceps::Code::compile($code, "Error handler");
</pre>

	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_constants">
		<title>Triceps constants</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>constants</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Triceps has a number of symbolic constants that are grouped into
		essentially enums. The constants themselves will be introduced with the
		classes that use them, but here is the general description common to
		them all.
		</para>

		<para>
		In Perl they all are placed into the same namespace. Each group of
		constants (that can be thought of as an enum) gets its name prefix. For
		example, the operation codes are all prefixed with OP_, the enqueueing
		modes with EM_, and so on.
		</para>

		<para>
		The underlying constants are all integer. The way to give symbolic
		names to constants in Perl is to define a function without arguments
		that would return the value. Each constant has such a function defined
		for it. For example, the opcode for the <quote>insert</quote> operation is the
		result of function <pre>Triceps::OP_INSERT</pre>. 
		</para>

		<para>
		Most methods that take constants as arguments are also smart enough to
		recognise the constant names as strings, and automatically convert them
		to integers. For example, the following calls are equivalent:
		</para>

<pre>
$label->makeRowop(&Triceps::OP_INSERT, ...);
$label->makeRowop("OP_INSERT", ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		For a while I've thought that the version with
		<pre>Triceps::OP_INSERT</pre> would be more efficient and might check
		for correctness of the name at compile time.  But as it turns out, no,
		on both counts. The look-up of the function by name happens at run
		time, so there is no compile-time check.  And that look-up happens to
		be a little slower than the one done by the Triceps &Cpp; code, so
		there is no win there either. The string version is not only shorter
		but also more efficient. The only win with the function is if you call it
		once, remember the result in a variable and then reuse. Unless you're 
		chasing the last few percent of performance in a tight loop, it's not
		worth the trouble. Perhaps in the future the functions will be replaced
		with the module-level variables: <i>that</i> would be both faster and
		allow the compile-time checking with <pre>use strict</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		What if you need to print out a constant in a message? Triceps provides
		the conversion functions for each group of constants. They generally
		are named <computeroutput>Triceps::<i>something</i>String</computeroutput>. 
		For example,
		</para>

<pre>
print &Triceps::opcodeString(&Triceps::OP_INSERT);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		would print <quote>OP_INSERT</quote>.
		If the argument is out of range of the valid enums, it would confess.
		There is also a version of these functions ending with <pre>Safe</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
print &Triceps::opcodeStringSafe(&Triceps::OP_INSERT);
</pre>

		<para>
		The difference is that it returns <pre>undef</pre> if the input value
		is out of range, thus being safe from confessions.
		</para>

		<para>
		There also are functions to convert from strings to constant values.
		They generally are named <computeroutput>Triceps::string<i>Something</i></computeroutput>. 
		For example,
		</para>

<pre>
&Triceps::stringOpcode("OP_INSERT")
&Triceps::stringOpcodeSafe("OP_INSERT")
</pre>

		<para>
		would return the integer value of <pre>Triceps::OP_INSERT</pre>. If the
		string name is not valid for this kind of constants, it would also
		either confess without <pre>Safe</pre> in the name or return <pre>undef</pre>
		with it.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_objprint">
		<title>Printing the object contents</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>print</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		When debugging the programs, it's important to find from the error
		messages, what is going on, what kinds of objects are getting involved.
		Because of this, many of the Triceps objects provide a way to print out
		their contents into a string. This is done with the method
		<pre>print()</pre>. The simplest use is as follows:
		</para>

<pre>
$message = "Error in object " . $object->print();
</pre>

		<para>
		Most of the objects tend to have a pretty complicated internal
		structure and are printed on multiple lines. They look better when the
		components are appropriately indented. The default call prints as if
		the basic message is un-indented, and indents every extra level by 2
		spaces.
		</para>

		<para>
		This can be changed with extra arguments. The general format of
		<pre>print()</pre> is:
		</para>

<programlisting>$object-&gt;print(<i>[$indent, [$subindent] ]</i>)</programlisting>

		<para>
		where <i>$indent</i> is the initial indentation, and <i>$subindent</i> is
		the additional indentation for every level. The default <pre>print()</pre> is
		equivalent to <pre>print("", "  ")</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		A special case is
		</para>

<pre>
$object->print(undef)
</pre>

		<para>
		It prints the object in a single line, without line breaks.
		</para>

		<para>
		Here is an example of how a row type object would get printed. The details
		of the row types will be described later, for now just assume that a
		row type is defined as:
		</para>

<pre>
$rt1 = Triceps::RowType->new(
	a => "uint8",
	b => "int32",
	c => "int64",
	d => "float64",
	e => "string",
);
</pre>

		<para>
		Then <pre>$rt1->print()</pre> produces:
		</para>

<pre>
row {
  uint8 a,
  int32 b,
  int64 c,
  float64 d,
  string e,
}
</pre>

		<para>
		With extra arguments <pre>$rt1->print("++", "--")</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
row {
++--uint8 a,
++--int32 b,
++--int64 c,
++--float64 d,
++--string e,
++}
</pre>

		<para>
		The first line doesn't have a <quote>++</quote> because the
		assumption is that the text gets appended to some other text
		already on this line, so any prefixes are used only for the
		following lines.
		</para>

		<para>
		And finally with an undef argument <pre>$rt1->print(undef)</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
row { uint8 a, int32 b, int64 c, float64 d, string e, }
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>printP</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The Rows and Rowops do not have the <pre>print()</pre> method.
		That's largely because the &Cpp; code does not deal with printing
		the actual data, this is left to the Perl code. So instead
		they have the method <pre>printP()</pre> that does a similar
		job. Only it's simpler and doesn't have any of the indenting
		niceties. It always prints the data in a single line. The <quote>P</quote> 
		in <quote>printP</quote> stands for <quote>Perl</quote>. The name
		is also different because of this lack of indenting niceties.
		See more about it in the 
		<xref linkend="sc_Rows" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;. 
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_hungarian">
		<title>The Hungarian notation</title>

		<para>
		The Hungarian notation is the idea that the name of each variable
		should be prefixed with some abbreviation of its type. It has probably
		become most widely known from the Microsoft operating systems.
		</para>

		<para>
		Overall it's a complete abomination and brain damage. But 
		I'm using it widely in the examples in this manual. Why? The problem is that there
		usually too many components for one logical purpose. For a table, there
		would be a row type, a table type, and the table itself. Rather than
		inventing separate names for them, it's easier to have a common name
		and an uniform prefix. Eventually something better would have to be
		done but for now I've fallen back on the Hungarian notation.
		One possibility is to just not give names to the intermediate
		entities. Say just have a named table, and then there would be
		the the type of the table and the row type of the table.
		</para>

		<para>
		Among the CEP systems, Triceps is not unique in the Hungarian notation
		department. Coral8/Sybase CCL has this mess of lots of schemas, input
		streams, windows and output streams, with the same naming problems. The
		uniform naming prefixes or suffixes help making this mess more
		navigable. I haven't actually used StreamBase but from reading the
		documentation I get the feeling that the Hungarian notation is probably
		useful for its SQL as well.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_perl_libex">
		<title>The Perl libraries and examples</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>examples</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>X package</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The official Triceps classes are collected in the Triceps package
		(and its subpackages). 
		</para>

		<para>
		However when writing tests and examples I've found
		that there are also some repeating elements. Initially I've been handling
		the situation by either combining all examples using such an element into a
		single file or by copying it around. Then I've collected all such fragments
		under the package Triceps::X.
		X can be thought of as a mark of eXperimental, eXample,
		eXtraneous code. 
		</para>

		<para>
		While the code in the official part of the library is extensively
		tested, the X-code is tested only in its most important functionality
		and not in the details.
		This code is not exactly of production quality but is
		good enough for the examples, and can be used as a starting point for
		development of the better code. Quite a few fragments of Triceps went
		this way: the joins have been done as an example first, and then
		solidified for the main code base, and so did the aggregation.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>TestFeed</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		One of these modules is Triceps::X::TestFeed. It's a small
		infrastructure to run the examples, pretending that it gets the input
		from stdin and sends output to stdout, while actually doing it all in
		memory. All of the more complicated examples have been written to use it. 
		When you look in the code of the actual running examples and compare
		it to the code snippets in the manual, you can see the differences.
		<!-- here must use <computeroutput> directly because otherwise the text gets substituted! -->
		A <computeroutput>&amp;readLine</computeroutput> shows instead of <pre><STDIN></pre>, and a
		<computeroutput>&amp;send</computeroutput> instead of <pre>print</pre> (and for the manual, I have a script that does
		the reverse substitutions automatically when I insert the code examples into
		it). 
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
