<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->


<chapter id="ch_Rows" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Rows</title>

	<para>
	In Triceps the relational data is stored and passed around as rows
	(once in a while I call them records, which is the same thing
	here). Each row belongs to a certain type, that defines the types
	of the fields. Each field may belong to one of the simple types.
	</para>

	<sect1 id="sc_SimpleTypes">
		<title>Simple types</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>simple</secondary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		The simple values in Triceps belong to one of the simple types:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		uint8
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		int32
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		int64
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		float64
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		string
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		I like the explicit specification of the data size, so it's not some
		mysterious <quote>double</quote> but an explicit <quote>float64</quote>.
		</para>

		<para>
		When the data is stored in the rows, it's stored in the strongly-typed
		binary format. When it's extracted from the rows for the Perl code to
		access, it gets converted into the Perl values. And the other way
		around, when stored into the rows, the conversion is done from the Perl
		values.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>uint8</pre> is the type intended to represent the raw bytes. So, for example,
		when they are compared, they should be compared as raw bytes, not
		according to the locale. Since Perl stores the raw bytes in strings,
		and its <pre>pack()</pre> and <pre>unpack()</pre> functions operate on strings, The Perl side
		of Triceps extracts the uint8 values from records into Perl strings,
		and the other way around. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The string type is intended to represent a text string in whatever
		current locale (at some point it may become always UTF-8, this question
		is open for now).
		</para>

		<para>
		Perl on the 32-bit machines has an issue with int64: it has no type to
		represent it directly. Because of that, when the int64 values are
		passed to Perl on the 32-bit machines, they are converted into the
		floating-point numbers. This gives only 54 bits (including sign) of
		precision, but that's close enough. Anyway, the 32-bit machines are
		obsolete by now, and Triceps it targeted towards the 64-bit machines.
		</para>

		<para>
		On the 64-bit machines both int32 and int64 translate to the Perl
		64-bit integers.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>time</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Note that there is no special type for timestamps. As of version 1.0
		there is no time-based processing inside Triceps, but that does not
		prevent you from passing around timestamps as data and use them in your
		logic. Just store the timestamps as integers (or, if you prefer,
		as floating point numbers). When the time-based processing will be
		added to Perl, the plan is to still use the int64 to store the number
		of microseconds since the Unix epoch. My experience with the time types
		in the other CEP systems is that they cause nothing but confusion.
		In the meantime, the time-based processing is still possible by driving
		the notion of time explicitly. It's described in the
		<xref linkend="ch_time" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_RowTypes">
		<title>Row types</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>row</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A row type is created from a sequence of (field-name, field-type)
		string pairs, for example:
		</para>

<pre>
$rt1 = Triceps::RowType->new(
	a => "uint8",
	b => "int32",
	c => "int64",
	d => "float64",
	e => "string",
);
</pre>

		<para>
		Even though the pairs look like a hash, don't use an actual hash to
		create row types! The order of pairs in a hash is unpredictable, while
		the order of fields in a row type usually matters.
		</para>

		<para>
		In an actual row the field may have a value or be NULL. The NULLs are
		represented in Perl as <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>array</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>arrays</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The real-world records tend to be pretty wide and contain
		repetitive data. Hundreds of fields are not unusual, and I know of a
		case when an Aleri customer wanted to have records of two thousand
		fields (and succeeded). This just begs for arrays. So the Triceps rows
		allow the array fields. They are specified by adding <quote>[]</quote> at the end of
		field type. The arrays may only be made up of fixed-width data, so no
		arrays of strings.
		</para>

<pre>
$rt2 = Triceps::RowType->new(
	a => "uint8[]",
	b => "int32[]",
	c => "int64[]",
	d => "float64[]",
	e => "string", # no arrays of strings!
);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>arrays</primary>
			<secondary>empty</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The arrays are of variable length, whatever array data passed when a
		row is created determines its length. The individual elements in the
		array may not be NULL (and if <pre>undef</pre>s are passed in the array used to
		construct the row, they will be replaced with 0s). The whole array
		field may be NULL, and this situation is equivalent to an empty array.
		</para>

		<para>
		The type uint8 is typically used in arrays, <quote>uint8[]</quote> is the Triceps
		way to define a blob field. In Perl the <quote>uint8[]</quote> is represented as a
		string value, same as a simple <quote>unit8</quote>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The rest of array values are represented in Perl as references to Perl
		arrays, containing the actual values.
		</para>

		<para>
		The row type objects provide a way for introspection:
		</para>

<pre>
$rt->getdef()
</pre>

		<para>
		returns back the array of pairs used to create this type. It can be
		used among other things for the schema inheritance. For example, the
		multi-part messages with daily unique ids can be defined as:
		</para>

<pre>
$rtMsgKey = Triceps::RowType->new(
	date => "string",
	id => "int32",
);

$rtMsg = Triceps::RowType->new(
	$rtMsgKey->getdef(),
	from => "string",
	to => "string",
	subject => "string",
);

$rtMsgPart = Triceps::RowType->new(
	$rtMsgKey->getdef(),
	type => "string",
	payload => "string",
);
</pre>

		<para>
		The meaning here is the same as in the CCL example:
		</para>

<pre>
create schema rtMsgKey (
	string date,
	integer id
);
create schema rtMsg inherits from rtMsgKey (
	string from,
	string to,
	string subject
);
create schema rtMsgPart inherits from rtMsgKey (
	string type,
	string payload
);
</pre>

		<para>
		The grand plan is to provide some better ways of defining the
		commonality of fields between row types. It should include the ability
		to rename fields, to avoid conflicts, and to remember this equivalence
		to be reused in the further joins without the need to write it over and
		over again. But it has not come to the implementation stage yet.
		</para>

		<para>
		The other methods are:
		</para>

<pre>
$rt->getFieldNames()
</pre>

		<para>
		returns the array of field names only.
		</para>

<pre>
$rt->getFieldTypes()
</pre>

		<para>
		returns the array of field types only.
		</para>

<pre>
$rt->getFieldMapping()
</pre>

		<para>
		returns the array of pairs that map the field names to their indexes in
		the field definitions. It can be stored into a hash and used for
		name-to-index translation. It's used mostly in the templates, to
		generate code that accesses data in the rows by field index (which is
		more efficient than access by name). For example, for <pre>rtMsgKey</pre>
		defined above it would return <pre>(date => 0, id => 1)</pre>.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_RowTypesEquiv">
		<title>Row types equivalence</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>match</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>equals</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowType</primary>
			<secondary>match</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowType</primary>
			<secondary>equals</secondary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		The Triceps objects are usually strongly typed. A label handles rows of
		a certain type. A table stores rows of a certain type.
		</para>

		<para>
		However there may be multiple ways to check whether a row fits for a
		certain type:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		It may be a row of the exact same type, created with the same RowType object.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		It may be a row of another type but one with the exact same definition.
		</listitem>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>case sensitivity</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<listitem>
		It may be a row of another type that has the same number of fields and
		field types but different field names. The field names (and everything
		else in Triceps) are case-sensitive.
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		The row types may be compared for these conditions using the methods:
		</para>

<pre>
$rt1->same($rt2)
$rt1->equals($rt2)
$rt1->match($rt2)
</pre>

		<para>
		The comparisons are hierarchical: if two type references are the same,
		they would also be equal and matching; two equal types are also
		matching.
		</para>

		<para>
		Most of the objects would accept the rows of any matching type (this
		may change or become adjustable in the future). However if the rows are
		not of the same type, this check involves a performance penalty. If the
		types are the same, the comparison is limited to comparing the
		pointers. But if not, then the whole type definition has to be
		compared. So every time a row of a different type is passed, it would
		involve the overhead of type comparison.
		</para>

		<para>
		For example:
		</para>

<!-- perl/Triceps/t/xSnippets.t -->
<pre>
my @schema = (
	a => "int32",
	b => "string"
);

my $rt1 = Triceps::RowType->new(@schema);
# $rt2 is equal to $rt1: same field names and field types
my $rt2 = Triceps::RowType->new(@schema); 
# $rt3  matches $rt1 and $rt2: same field types but different names
my $rt3 = Triceps::RowType->new(
	A => "int32",
	B => "string"
);

my $lab = $unit->makeDummyLabel($rt1, "lab");
# same type, efficient
my $rop1 = $lab->makeRowop(&Triceps::OP_INSERT,
	$rt1->makeRowArray(1, "x"));
# different row type, involves a comparison overhead
my $rop2 = $lab->makeRowop(&Triceps::OP_INSERT,
	$rt2->makeRowArray(1, "x"));
# different row type, involves a comparison overhead
my $rop3 = $lab->makeRowop(&Triceps::OP_INSERT,
	$rt3->makeRowArray(1, "x"));
</pre>

		<para>
		A dummy label used here is a label that does nothing (its usefulness
		will be explained later).
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Row</primary>
			<secondary>re-typing</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>XS</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Once the Rowop is constructed, no further penalty is involved: the
		row in the Rowop is re-typed to the type of the label from now on.
		It's physically still the same row with another reference to it,
		but when you get it back from the Rowop, it will have the label's
		type. It's all a part of the interesting interaction between &Cpp;
		and Perl. All the type checking is done in the Perl XS layer.
		The &Cpp; code just expects that the data is always right and doesn't
		carry the types around. When the Perl code wants to get the row
		back from the Rowop, it wants to know the type of the row.
		The only way to get it is to look, what is the label of this
		Rowop, and get the row type from the label. This is also the
		reason why the types have to be checked when the Rowop is
		constructed: if a wrong row is placed into the Rowop, there will
		be no later opportunity to check it for correctness, and bad
		data may cause a crash.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_Rows">
		<title>Rows</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Row</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The rows in Triceps always belong to some row type, and are always
		immutable. Once a row is created, it can not be changed. This allows it
		to be referenced from multiple places, instead of copying the whole row
		value. Naturally, a row may be passed and shared between multiple
		threads.
		</para>

		<para>
		The row type provides the constructor methods for the rows:
		</para>

<pre>
$row = $rowType->makeRowArray(@fieldValues);
$row = $rowType->makeRowHash($fieldName => $fieldValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Here <pre>$row</pre> is a reference to the resulting row. As usual, in case of
		error it will confess.
		</para>

		<para>
		In the array form, the values for the fields go in the same order as
		they are specified in the row type (if there are too few values, the
		rest will be considered NULL, having too many values is an error).
		</para>

		<para>
		The Perl value of <pre>undef</pre> is treated as NULL. 
		</para>

		<para>
		In the hash form, the fields are specified as name-value pairs. If the
		same field is specified multiple times, the last value will overwrite
		all the previous ones. The unspecified fields will be left as
		NULL. Again, the arguments of the function actually are an array, but
		if you pass a hash, its contents will be converted to an array on the
		call stack.
		</para>

		<para>
		If the performance is important, the array form is more efficient,
		since the hash form has to translate internally the field names to
		indexes.
		</para>

		<para>
		The row itself and its type don't have any concept of keys in general
		and of the primary key in particular. So any fields may be left as NULL.
		There is no <quote>NOT NULL</quote> constraint.
		</para>

		<para>
		Some examples:
		</para>

<pre>
$row  = $rowType->makeRowArray(@fields);
$row  = $rowType->makeRowArray($a, $b, $c);
$row  = $rowType->makeRowHash(%fields);
$row  = $rowType->makeRowHash(a => $a, b => $b);
</pre>

		<para>
		The usual Perl conversions are applied to the values. So for example,
		if you pass an integer 1 for a string field, it will be converted to
		the string <quote>1</quote>. Or if you pass a string <quote></quote> for an integer field, it
		will be converted to 0. 
		</para>

		<para>
		If a field is an array (as always, except for <pre>uint8[]</pre> which is
		represented as a Perl string), its value is a Perl array reference (or
		<pre>undef</pre>). For example:
		</para>

<pre>
$rt1 = Triceps::RowType->new(
	a => "uint8[]",
	b => "int32[]",
);
$row = $rt1->makeRowArray("abcd", [1, 2, 3]);
</pre>

		<para>
		An empty array will become a NULL value. So the following two are equivalent:
		</para>

<pre>
$row = $rt1->makeRowArray("abcd", []);
$row = $rt1->makeRowArray("abcd", undef);
</pre>

		<para>
		Remember that an array field may not contain NULL values. Any <pre>undef</pre>s
		in the array fields will be silently converted to zeroes (since arrays
		are supported only for the numeric types, a zero value would always
		be available for all of them). The following two are equivalent:
		</para>

<pre>
$row = $rt1->makeRowArray("abcd", [undef, undef]);
$row = $rt1->makeRowArray("abcd", [0, 0]);
</pre>

		<para>
		The row also provides a way to copy itself, modifying the values of
		selected fields:
		</para>

<pre>
$row2 = $row1->copymod($fieldName => $fieldValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		The fields that are not explicitly specified will be left unchanged.
		Since the rows are immutable, this is the closest thing to the field
		assignment. <pre>copymod()</pre> is generally more efficient than
		extracting the row into an array or hash, replacing a few of them with
		new values and constructing a new row. It bypasses the
		binary-to-Perl-to-binary conversions for the unchanged fields.
		</para>

		<para>
		The row knows its type, which can be obtained with
		</para>

<pre>
$row->getType()
</pre>

		<para>
		Note that this will create a new Perl wrapper to the underlying type
		object. So if you do:
		</para>

<pre>
$rt1 = ...;
$row = $rt1->makeRow...;
$rt2 = $row->getType();
</pre>

		<para>
		then <pre>$rt1</pre> will not be equal to <pre>$rt2</pre> by the direct
		Perl comparison (<pre>$rt1 != $rt2</pre>). However both <pre>$rt1</pre>
		and <pre>$rt2</pre> will refer to the same row type object, so
		<pre>$rt1-&gt;same($rt2)</pre> will be true.
		</para>

		<para>
		The row references can also be compared for sameness:
		</para>

<pre>
$row1->same($row2)
</pre>

		<para>
		The row contents can be extracted back into Perl representation as
		</para>

<pre>
@adata = $row->toArray();
%hdata = $row->toHash();
</pre>

		<para>
		Again, the NULL fields will become <pre>undef</pre>s, and the array fields (unless
		they are NULL) will become Perl array references. Since the empty array
		fields are equivalent to NULL array fields, on extraction back they
		will be treated the same as NULL fields, and become <pre>undef</pre>s.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is also a convenience function to get one field from a row at a
		time by name:
		</para>

<pre>
$value = $row->get("fieldName");
</pre>

		<para>
		If you need to access only a few fields from a big row, <pre>get()</pre> is more
		efficient (and easier to write) that extracting the whole row with
		<pre>toHash()</pre> or even with <pre>toArray()</pre>. But don't forget that every time you
		call <pre>get()</pre>, it creates a new Perl value, which may be pretty involved
		if the value is an array. So the most efficient way then for the
		values that get reused many times is to call <pre>get()</pre>, remember the result in a Perl
		variable, and then reuse that variable.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is also a way to conveniently print a rows contents, usually for
		the debugging purposes:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $row->printP();
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>print</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The name <pre>printP</pre> is an artifact of implementation: it shows that this
		method is implemented in Perl and uses the default Perl conversions of
		values to strings. The <pre>uint8[]</pre> arrays are printed directly as strings.
		The result is a sequence of <pre>name="value"</pre> or 
		<pre>name=["value", "value", "value"]</pre> 
		for all the non-NULL fields. The backslashes and double quotes
		inside the values are escaped by backslashes in Perl style. For
		example, reusing the row type above,
		</para>

<pre>
$row = $rt1->makeRowArray('ab\ "cd"', [0, 0]);
print $row->printP(), "\n";
</pre>

		<para>
		will produce
		</para>

<pre>
a="ab\\ \"cd\"" b=["0", "0"]
</pre>

		
		<para>
		It's possible to check quickly if all the fields of a row are NULL:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $row->isEmpty();
</pre>

		<para>
		It returns 1 if all the fields are NULL and 0 otherwise.
		</para>

		<para>
		Finally, there is a deep debugging method:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $row->hexdump()
</pre>

		<para>
		That dumps the raw bytes of the row's binary format, and is useful only
		to debug the more weird issues.
		</para>

	</sect1>

</chapter>
