<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

<chapter id="ch_LabelsRowops" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Labels and Row Operations</title>

	<sect1 id="sc_Labels">
		<title>Labels basics</title>

		<para>
		In each CEP engine there are two kinds of logic: One is to get some
		request, look up some state, maybe update some state, and return the
		result. The other has to do with the maintenance of the state: make
		sure that when one part of the state is changed, the change propagates
		consistently through the rest of it. If we take a common RDBMS for an
		analog, the first kind would be like the ad-hoc queries, the second
		kind will be like the triggers. The CEP engines are very much like
		database engines driven by triggers, so the second kind tends to
		account for a lot of code.
		</para>

		<para>
		The first kind of logic is often very nicely accommodated by the
		procedural logic. The second kind often (but not always) can benefit
		from a more relational, SQLy definition. However the SQLy definitions
		don't stay SQLy for long.  When every every SQL
		statement executes, it gets compiled first into the procedural form,
		and only then executes as the procedural code.
		</para>

		<para>
		The Triceps approach is tilted toward the procedural execution. That is,
		the procedural definitions come out of the box, and then the high-level
		relational logic can be defined on top of them with the templates and
		code generators.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		These bits of code, especially where the first and second kind connect,
		need some way to pass the data and operations between them. In Triceps
		these connection points are called Labels.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Aleri</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Coral8</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The streaming data rows enter the procedural logic through a label.
		Each row causes one call on the label. From the functional standpoint
		they are the same as Coral8 Streams, as has been shown in
		<xref linkend="sc_1950s" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		Except that in Triceps the labels receive not just
		rows but operations on rows, as in Aleri: a combination of a row and an
		operation code. 
		</para>

		<para>
		They are named <quote>labels</quote> because Triceps has been built
		around the more procedural ideas, and when looked at from that side,
		the labels are targets of calls and GOTOs.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>data flow</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>GOTO</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		If the streaming model is defined as a data flow graph, each arrow in
		the graph is essentially a GOTO operation, and each node is a label.
		</para>

		<para>
		A Triceps label is not quite a GOTO label, since the actual procedural
		control always returns back after executing the label's code. It can be
		thought of as a label of a function or procedure. But if the caller
		does nothing but immedially return after getting the control back, it
		works very much like a GOTO label.
		</para>

		<para>
		Each label accepts operations on rows of a certain type.
		</para>

		<para>
		Each label belongs to a certain execution unit, so a label can be used
		only strictly inside one thread and can not be shared between threads.
		</para>

		<para>
		Each label may have some code to execute when it receives a row
		operation. The labels without code can be useful too.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>chaining</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>DummyLabel</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A Triceps model contains the straightforward code and the mode complex
		stateful elements, such as tables, aggregators, joiners (which may be
		implemented in &Cpp; or in Perl, or created as user templates). These
		stateful elements would have some input labels, where the actions may
		be sent to them (and the actions may also be done as direct method
		calls), and output labels, where they would produce the indications of
		the changed state and/or responses to the queries. This is shown
		in the diagram in
		<xref linkend="fig_label_chain" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;.
		The output labels
		are typically the ones without code (<quote>dummy labels</quote>). They do nothing
		by themselves, but can pass the data to the other labels. This passing
		of data is achieved by <i>chaining</i> the labels: when a label is
		called, it will first execute its own code (if it has any), and then
		call the same operation on whatever labels are chained from it. Which
		may have more labels chained from them in turn. So, to pass the data,
		chain the input label of the following element to the output label of
		the previous element.
		</para>

		<figure id="fig_label_chain" >
			<title>Stateful elements with chained labels.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/label-000-chain.xml"/> 
			<!-- <graphic scale="100%" contentwidth="5in" fileref="label-000-chain.svg"/> -->
		</figure>

		<para>
		The make things clear, a label doesn't have to be a part of a stateful
		element. The labels absolutely can exist by themselves. It's just that
		the stateful elements can use the labels as their endpoints.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_Label_construction">
		<title>Label construction</title>

		<para>
		The execution unit provides methods to construct labels. A dummy label
		is constructed as:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>dummy</secondary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
$label = $unit->makeDummyLabel($rowType, "name");
</pre>

		<para>
		It takes as arguments the type of rows that the label will accept and
		the symbolic name of the label. As usual, the name can be any but for the ease of
		debugging it's better to give the same name as the label variable.
		</para>

		<para>
		The label with Perl code is constructed as follows:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>Perl</secondary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
$label = $unit->makeLabel($rowType, "name", $clearSub,
	$execSub, @args);
</pre>

		<para>
		The row type and name arguments are the same as for the dummy label.
		The following two arguments provide the references to the Perl functions
		that perform the actions. 
		They can be specified as a function reference or a source code string, see
		<xref linkend="sc_code" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;. 
		<pre>$execSub</pre> is the function that executes to
		handle the incoming rows. It gets the arguments:
		</para>

<pre>
&$execSub($label, $rowop, @args)
</pre>

		<para>
		Here <pre>$label</pre> is this label, <pre>$rowop</pre> is the row operation, and <pre>@args</pre>
		are the same as extra arguments specified at the label creation.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>chaining</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The row operation actually contains the label reference, so why pass it
		the second time? The reason lies in the chaining. The current label may
		be chained, possibly through multiple levels, to some original label,
		and the rowop will refer to that original label. The extra argument
		lets the code find the current label.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>$clearSub</pre> is the function that clears the label. It will be explained in the
		<xref linkend="sc_memory_labels" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		Either of <pre>$execSub</pre> and <pre>$clearSub</pre> can be specified as <pre>undef</pre>. Though
		a label with an undefined <pre>$execSub</pre> makes the label useless for anything
		other than clearing. On an attempt to send data to it, it will complain that
		the label has been cleared.
		The undefined <pre>$clearSub</pre> causes the function
		<pre>Triceps::clearArgs()</pre> to be used as the default, which provides the
		correct reaction for most situations.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>clearing</secondary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		There is a special convenience constructor for the labels that are used
		only for clearing an object (their usefulness is discussed in
		<xref linkend="sc_memory_labels" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;).
		</para>

<pre>
$lb = $unit->makeClearingLabel("name", @args);
</pre>

		<para>
		The arguments would be the references to the objects that need clearing,
		usually the object's <pre>$self</pre>. They will be cleared with
		<pre>Triceps::clearArgs()</pre> when the label clearing gets called.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_LabelOther">
		<title>Other label methods</title>

		<para>
		The chaining of labels is done with the method:
		</para>

<pre>
$label1->chain($label2);
</pre>

		<para>
		<pre>$label2</pre> becomes chained to <pre>$label1</pre>.
		A label can not be chained to itself, neither directly nor through
		other intermediate labels. The row types of the chained labels must be equal
		(this is more strict than for queueing up the row operations for labels,
		and might change one or the other way in the future).
		</para>

		<para>
		When <pre>$label1</pre> executes, its chained labels will normally
		be executed in the order they were chained. However sometines it's
		necessary to add a label to the chain later but have it called
		first. This is done with the method:
		</para>

<pre>
$label1->chainFront($label2);
</pre>

		<para>
		It chains <pre>$label2</pre> at the start of the chain. Of course,
		if more labels will be chained at the front afterwards, <pre>$label2</pre>
		will be called only after them. But usually there is a need for only
		one such label, and it's usually connected to the FnReturn and Facet
		objects. For an example, see
		<xref linkend="sc_mt_pipeline" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		A label's chainings can be cleared with
		</para>

<pre>
$label1->clearChained();
</pre>

		<para>
		It returns nothing, and clears the chainings from this label. There is
		no way to unchain only some selected labels.
		</para>

		<para>
		To check if there are any labels chained from this one, use:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $label->hasChained();
</pre>

		<para>
		The same check can be done with
		</para>

<pre>
@chain = $label->getChain();

if ($#chain >= 0) { ... }
</pre>

		<para>
		but <pre>hasChained()</pre> is more efficient since it doesn't have
		to construct that intermediate array.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is also a convenience method that
		creates a new label by chaining it from an existing label:
		</para>

<pre>
$label2 = $label1->makeChained($name, $subClear, $subExec, @args);
</pre>

		<para>
		The arguments are very much the same as in <pre>Unit::makeLabel()</pre>, only there is
		no need to specify the row type for the new label (nor obviously the
		Unit), these are taken from the original label. It's really a wrapper
		that finds the unit and row type from <pre>label1</pre>, makes a new
		label, and then chains it off <pre>label1</pre>.
		</para>


		<para>
		The whole label can be cleared with
		</para>

<pre>
$label->clear();
</pre>

		<para>
		This is fully equivalent to what happens when an execution unit clears
		the labels: it calls the clear function (if any) and clears the
		chainings. Note that the labels that used to be chained from this one
		do not get cleared themselves, they're only unchained from this one.
		To check whether the label has been already cleared use:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $label->isCleared();
</pre>

		<para>
		Labels have the usual way of comparing the references:
		</para>

<pre>
$label1->same($label2)
</pre>

		<para>
		returns true if both references point to the same label object.
		</para>

		<para>
		The labels introspection can be done with the methods:
		</para>

<pre>
$rowType = $label->getType();
$rowType = $label->getRowType();
$unit = $label->getUnit();
$name = $label->getName();
@chainedLabels = $label->getChain();
$execSubRef = $label->getCode();
</pre>

		<para>
		The methods <pre>getType()</pre> and <pre>getRowType()</pre> are the same, they both return
		the row type of the label. <pre>getType()</pre> is shorter, which looked convenient
		for a while, but <pre>getRowType()</pre> has the name consistent with the
		rest of the classes. This consistency comes useful when passing the objects
		of various types to the same methods, using the Perl's name-based
		polymorphism. For now both of them are present, but <pre>getType()</pre> will
		likely be deprecated in the future.
		</para>

		<para>
		If the label has been cleared, <pre>getUnit()</pre> will return an
		<pre>undef</pre>. <pre>getChain()</pre> returns an array of references
		to the chained labels. <pre>getCode()</pre> is actually half-done
		because it returns just the Perl function reference to the execution
		handler but not its arguments, nor reference to the clearing function.
		It will be changed in the future to fix these issues.
		<pre>getCode()</pre> is not applicable to the dummy labels, and would
		return an <pre>undef</pre> for them.
		</para>

		<para>
		The labels actually exist in multiple varieties. The underlying common
		denominator is the &Cpp; class Label. This class may be extended and the
		resulting labels embedded into the &Cpp; objects. These labels can be
		accesses and controlled from Perl but their logic is hardcoded in their
		objects and is not directly visible from Perl. The dummy labels are
		a subclass of labels in general, and can be constructed directly
		from Perl. Another subclass is the labels with the Perl handlers.
		They can be constructed from Perl, and really only from Perl. The &Cpp;
		code can access and control them, in a symmetrical relation. The
		method <pre>getCode()</pre> has meaning only on these Perl labels.
		Finally, the clearing labels also get created from Perl, and fundamentally
		are Perl labels with many settings hardcoded in the constructor.
		<pre>getCode()</pre> can be used on them too but since they have
		no handler code, it would always return <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is also a way to change a label's name:
		</para>

<pre>
$label->setName($name);
</pre>

		<para>
		It returns nothing, and there is probably no reason to call it. It will
		likely be removed in the future.
		</para>

		<para>
		The label also provides the constructor methods for the row operations, 
		which are described below.
		</para>

		<para>
		And for completeness I'll mention the methods used to mark the
		label as non-reentrant and to read this mark back. They will be described
		in detail in 
		<xref linkend="sc_sched_recursion" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>
<pre>
$label->setNonReentrant();
$val = $label->isNonReentrant();
</pre>

	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_Rowop">
		<title>Row operations</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Rowop</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>row operation</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		A row operation (also known as rowop) in Triceps is an unit of work for
		a label. It's always destined for a particular label (which could also
		pass the rowop to its chained labels), and has a row to process and an opcode.
		The opcodes will be described momentarily in the
		<xref linkend="sc_opcodes" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		A row operation is constructed as:
		</para>

<pre>
$rowop = $label->makeRowop($opcode, $row);
</pre>

		<para>
		The opcode may be specified an integer or as a string.
		Historically, there is also an optional extra argument for the enqueuing
		mode but it's already obsolete, so I don't show it here.
		</para>

		<para>
		Since the labels are single-threaded, the rowops are single-threaded
		too. The rowops are immutable, just as the rows are. It's possible
		to keep a rowop around and call it over and over again.
		</para>

		<para>
		A rowop can be created from a bunch of fields in an array or hash form 
		in two steps:
		</para>

<pre>
$rowop = $label->makeRowop($opcode, $rt->makeRowHash(
	$fieldName => $fieldValue, ...));
$rowop = $label->makeRowop($opcode, $rt->makeRowArray(@fields));
</pre>

		<para>
		Since this kind of creation happens fairly often, writing out these
		calls every time becomes tedious. The Label provides the combined
		constructors to make life easier:
		</para>

<pre>
$rowop = $label->makeRowopHash($opcode, $fieldName => $fieldValue, ...);
$rowop = $label->makeRowopArray($opcode, @fields);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Note that they don't need the row type argument any more,
		because the label knows the row type and provides it.
		Internally these methods are currently implemented in Perl, and just wrap
		the two calls into one.  In the future they will be rewritten
		in &Cpp; for greater efficiency.
		</para>

		<para>
		There also are the methods that create a rowop and immediately
		call it. They will be described with the execution unit.
		</para>

		<para>
		A copy of rowop (not just another reference but an honest separate
		copied object) can be created with:
		</para>

<pre>
$rowop2 = $rowop1->copy();
</pre>

		<para>
		However, since the rowops are immutable, a reference is just as good as
		a copy. This method is historic and will likely be removed or modified.
		</para>

		<para>
		A more interesting operation is the rowop adoption:
		it is a way to pass the row and opcode from one rowop to another new
		one, with a different label.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>adoption</secondary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
$rowop2 = $label->adopt($rowop1);
</pre>

		<para>
		It is very convenient for building the label handlers that pass the
		rowops to the other labels unchanged. For example, a label
		that filters the data and passes it to the next label, can be implemented as
		follows:
		</para>

<pre>
my $lab1 = $unit->makeLabel($rt1, "lab1", undef, sub {
	my ($label, $rowop) = @_;
	if ($rowop->getRow()->get("a") > 10) {
		$unit->call($lab2->adopt($rowop));
	}
});
</pre>

		<para>
		This code doesn't even look at the opcode in the rowop, it just
		passes it through and lets the next label worry about it.
		The functionality of <pre>adopt()</pre> also can be implemented with
		</para>

<pre>
$rowop2 = $label->makeRowop($rowop1->getOpcode(), $rowop1->getRow());
</pre>

		<para>
		But <pre>adopt()</pre> is easier to call and also more efficient,
		because less of the intermediate data surfaces from the &Cpp; level to
		the Perl level.
		</para>

		<para>
		The references to rowops can be compared as usual:
		</para>

<pre>
$rowop1->same($rowop2)
</pre>

		<para>
		returns true if both point to the same rowop object.
		</para>

		<para>
		The rowop data can be extracted back:
		</para>

<pre>
$label = $rowop->getLabel();
$opcode = $rowop->getOpcode();
$row = $rowop->getRow();
</pre>

		<para>
		A Rowop can be printed (usually for debugging purposes) with
		</para>

<pre>
$string = $rowop->printP();
$string = $rowop->printP($name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Just as with a row, the method <pre>printP()</pre> is implemented in Perl. In
		the future a <pre>print()</pre> done right in &Cpp; may be added, but for now I try
		to keep all the interpretation of the data on the Perl side. Even though
		<pre>printP()</pre> is implemented in Perl, it can print the rowops
		for any kinds of labels.  The
		following example gives an idea of the format in which the rowops get
		printed:
		</para>

<pre>
$lb = $unit->makeDummyLabel($rt, "lb");
$rowop = $lb->makeRowop(&Triceps::OP_INSERT, $row);
print $rowop->printP(), "\n";
</pre>

		<para>
		would produce
		</para>

<pre>
lb OP_INSERT a="123" b="456" c="3000000000000000" d="3.14" e="text" 
</pre>

		<para>
		The row contents is printed through <pre>Row::printP()</pre>, so it has
		the same format.
		</para>

		<para>
		The optional argument allows to override the name of the label
		printed. For example, if in the example above the last line were
		to be replaced with
		</para>

<pre>
print $rowop->printP("OtherLabel"), "\n";
</pre>

		<para>
		the result will become:
		</para>

<pre>
OtherLabel OP_INSERT a="123" b="456" c="3000000000000000" d="3.14" e="text" 
</pre>

		<para>
		It makes the printing of rowops in the chained
		labels more convenient. A chained label's execution handler receives
		the original unchanged rowop that refers to the first label in the
		chain. So when it gets printed, it will print the name of the first
		label in the chain, which might be very surprising. The explicit
		argument allows to override it to the name of the chained label (or to
		any other value).
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_opcodes">
		<title>Opcodes</title>

		<para>
		The defined opcodes are:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>opcode</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<pre>&Triceps::OP_NOP</pre> or <pre>"OP_NOP"</pre>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<pre>&Triceps::OP_INSERT</pre> or <pre>"OP_INSERT"</pre>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<pre>&Triceps::OP_DELETE</pre> or <pre>"OP_DELETE"</pre>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		The meaning is straightforward: NOP does nothing, INSERT inserts
		a row, DELETE deletes a row. There is no opcode to replace or
		update a row. The updates are done as two separate operations: first
		DELETE the old value then INSERT the new value. The order is
		important: the old value has to be deleted before inserting the new one.
		But there is no requirement that these operations must go one
		after another. If you want to update ten rows, you can first
		delete all ten and then insert the new ten. In the
		normal processing the end result will be the same, even though
		it might go through some different intermediate states.
		It's a good idea to write your models to follow the same principle.
		</para>

		<para>
		Internally an opcode is always represented as an integer constant.
		The same constant value can be obtained by calling the functions
		<pre>&Triceps::OP_*</pre>. However when constructing the rowops,
		you can also use the string literals <pre>"OP_*"</pre> with
		the same result, they will be automatically transtaled to the integers. 
		In fact, the string literal form is slightly
		faster (unless you save the result of the function in a variable
		and then use the integer value from that variable for the
		repeated construction).
		</para>

		<para>
		But when you get the opcodes back from rowops, they are always
		returned as integers. Triceps provides functions that convert
		the opcodes between the integer and string constants:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>constants</primary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
$opcode = &Triceps::stringOpcode($opcodeName);
$opcodeName = &Triceps::opcodeString($opcode); 
</pre>

		<para>
		They come handy for all kinds of print-outs. If you pass the invalid
		values, the conversion to integers will return an <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The conversion of the invalid integers to strings is more interesting.
		And by the way, you can pass the invalid integer opcodes to the
		rowop construction too, and they won't be caught. The way they
		will be processed is a bit of a lottery. The proper integer values
		are actually bitmasks, and they are nicely formatted to make sense.
		The invalid values would make some random bitmasks, and they will
		get processed in some unpredictable way. When converting an invalid
		integer to a string, <pre>opcodeString</pre> tries to predict and 
		show this way in a set of letters <pre>I</pre> and <pre>D</pre>
		in square brackets, for INSERT and DELETE flags. If both are present, 
		usually the INSERT flag wins over the DELETE in the processing. 
		If none are present, it's a NOP.
		</para>

		<para>
		In the normal
		processing you don't normally read the opcode and then compare
		it with different values. Instead you check the meaning of the
		opcode (that is internally a bitmask) directly with the rowop methods:
		</para>

<pre>
$rowop->isNop()
$rowop->isInsert()
$rowop->isDelete()
</pre>

		<para>
		The typical idiom for the label's handler function is:
		</para>

<pre>
if ($rowop->isInsert()) {
	# handle the insert logic ...
} elsif($rowop->isDelete()) {
	# handle the delete logic...
}
</pre>

		<para>
		The NOPs get silently ignored in this idiom, as they should be.
		Generally there is no point in creating the rowops with the <pre>OP_NOP</pre> opcode,
		unless you want to use them for some weird logic.
		</para>

		<para>
		The main Triceps package also provides functions to check the integer
		opcode values directly:
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::isNop($opcode)
Triceps::isInsert($opcode)
Triceps::isDelete($opcode)
</pre>

		<para>
		The same-named methods of Rowop are just the more convenient and
		efficient way to say
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::isNop($rowop->getOpcode())
Triceps::isInsert($rowop->getOpcode())
Triceps::isDelete($rowop->getOpcode())
</pre>

		<para>
		They handle the whole logic directly in &Cpp; without an extra
		Perl conversion of the values.
		</para>

	</sect1>

</chapter>
