<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

<chapter id="ch_memory" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Memory Management</title>

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_cycles">
		<title>Reference cycles</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>memory management</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Remember that the
		Triceps memory management uses the reference counting, which does not like
		the reference cycles, as has been mentioned in
		<xref linkend="sc_memory_fund" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;. 
		The reference cycles cause the objects to be never
		freed. It's no big deal if the data structures exist until the program
		exit anyway but it becomes a memory leak if they keep being created and deleted
		dynamically.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>model</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The problems come not with the data that goes through the models but
		with the models themselves. The data gets reference-counted without any
		issues. The reference cycles can get formed only between the elements of
		the models: labels, tables etc. If you don't need them destroyed until
		the program exits (or more exactly, until the Perl interpreter instance
		exits), there is no problem. The leaks could happen only if the model
		elements get created and destroyed as the program runs, such as if you
		use them to parse and process the short-lived ad-hoc queries.
		</para>

		<para>
		These leaks are pretty hard to diagnose. There are some
		packages, like Devel::Cycle, but they won't detect the loops that
		involve a reference at &Cpp; level. And when the Perl interpreter exits,
		it clears up all the variables used, even the ones involved in the
		loops, so if you run it under valgrind, valgrind doesn't show any
		leaks. There is a package Devel::LeakTrace that should be able
		to detect all these left-over variables. However I can't tell for sure
		yet, so far I haven't had enough patience to build all the
		dependencies for it.
		</para>

		<para>
		One possibility is to use the weak references (using the module Scalar::Util).
		But the problem is that you need to not forget weakening the references
		manually. Too much work, too much attention, too easy to forget. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The mechanism used in Triceps works by breaking up the reference cycles
		when the data needs to be cleared. The execution unit
		keeps track of all its labels, and when it gets destoryed, clears them
		up, breaking up the cycles. It's also possible to clear the labels
		individually, by a manual call.
		</para>

		<para>
		The clearing of a label clears all the chainings.
		The chained labels get cleared too in their turn, and eventually the whole chain
		clears up. This removes the links in the forward direction, and if any
		cycles were present, they become open.
		More on the details of label clearing in the 
		<xref linkend="sc_memory_labels" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;. 
		</para>

		<para>
		Another potential for reference cycles is between the execution
		unit and the labels. A unit keeps a reference to all its labels. So the
		labels can not keep a reference to the unit. And they don't. Internally
		they have a plain &Cpp; pointer to the unit. However the Perl level
		may present a problem.
		</para>

		<para>
		In many cases 
		the labels have a Perl reference to the template object where they belong. 
		And that object is likely to have a Perl reference to the unit. It's one more
		opportunity for the reference cycle. This code usually looks like this:
		</para>

<pre>
package MyTemplate;

sub new # ($class, $unit, $name, $rowType, ...)
{
	my $class = shift;
	my $unit = shift;
	my $name = shift;
	my $rowType = shift;
	my $self = {};

	...

	$self->{unit} = $unit;
	$self->{inputLabel} = $unit->makeLabel($rowType, $name . ".in",
		sub { ... }, sub { ... }, $self);

	...

	bless $self, $class;
	return $self;
}
</pre>

		<para>
		So the unit refers to the label at the &Cpp; level, the label has a
		<pre>$self</pre> reference to the Perl object that owns it, and 
		the object's <pre>$self->{unit}</pre> refers back to the unit.
		Once the label clearing happens, the link from the unit will
		disappear and the cycle would unroll. But the clearing would not
		happen by itself because the unit can't get automatically
		defererenced and destroyed.
		</para>

		<para>
		Because of this, the unit provides an explicit way to trigger the clearing:
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->clearLabels();
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Unit</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		If you want to get rid of an execution unit with all its components
		without exiting the whole program, use this call. It will start the
		chain reaction of destruction. Of course, don't forget to undefine all the other
		references in your program to these objects being destroyed.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is also a way to trigger this chain reaction automatically.
		It's done with a helper object that is created as follows:
		</para>

<pre>
my $clearUnit = $unit->makeClearingTrigger();
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>UnitClearingTrigger</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		When the reference to <pre>$clearUnit</pre> gets destroyed, it
		will call <pre>$unit->clearLabels()</pre> and trigger the destruction
		of the whole unit. Obviously, don't copy the <pre>$clearUnit</pre>
		variable, keep it on one place.
		</para>

		<para>
		If you put it into a block variable, the unit will get destroyed on
		exiting the block. If you put it into a global variable in a thread,
		the unit will get destroyed when the thread exits (though I'm a bit
		hazy on the Perl memoery management with threads yet, it might get
		all cleared by itself without any special tricks too).
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_memory_labels">
		<title>Clearing of the labels</title>

		<para>
		To remind, a label that executes the Perl code is created with:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>Perl</secondary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
$label = $unit->makeLabel($rowType, "name", \&clearSub,
	\&execSub, @args);
</pre>

		<para>
		The function <pre>clearSub</pre> deals with the destruction. 
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>clearing</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>chaining</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The clearing of a label drops all the references to <pre>execSub</pre>, <pre>clearSub</pre>
		and arguments, and clears all the chainings. And of course the chained
		labels get cleared too.  But before anything else
		is done, <pre>clearSub</pre> gets a chance to execute and clear any
		application-level data. It gets as its arguments all the
		arguments from the label constructor, same as <pre>execSub</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
clearSub($label, @args) 
</pre>

		<para>
		A typical case is to keep the state of a stateful element in a hash:
		</para>

<pre>
package MyTemplate;

sub new # ($class, $unit, $name, $rowType, ...)
{
	my $class = shift;
	my $unit = shift;
	my $name = shift;
	my $rowType = shift;
	my $self = {};

	...

	$self->{unit} = $unit;
	$self->{inputLabel} = $unit->makeLabel($rowType, $name . ".in",
		\&clear, \&handle, $self);

	...

	bless $self, $class;
	return $self;
}
</pre>

		<para>
		These elements may end up pointing to the other elements. It's fairly common to keep
		the pointers to the other elements (especially tables) that provide inputs to this one.
		In general, these references <quote>up</quote> should be safe because the clearing of the
		labels would destroy the references <quote>down</quote> and open the cycles.
		But the way things get connected in the heat of the moment, you never know.
		It's better to be safe than sorry.
		To be on the safe side, the clearing function can wipe out the whole state of the element
		by undefining its hash:
		</para>

<pre>
sub clear # ($label, $self)
{
	my ($label, $self) = @_;
	undef %$self;
}
</pre>

		<para>
		The whole contents of the hash becomes lost, all the refrences from it disappear.
		And if you use this approach in every object, the complete destruction reigns
		and everything is nicely laid to waste.
		</para>

		<para>
		Writing these clear methods for each class quickly becomes tedious and easy to
		forget. Triceps is a step ahead: it provides a ready function
		<pre>Triceps::clearArgs()</pre> that does all this destruction. It can undefine
		the contents of various things passed as its arguments, and then also undefines
		these arguments themselves. Just reuse it:
		</para>

<pre>
$self->{inputLabel} = $unit->makeLabel($rowType, $name . ".in",
	\&Triceps::clearArgs, \&handle, $self);
</pre>

		<para>
		But that's not all. Triceps is actually <i>two</i> steps ahead. If the
		<pre>clearSub</pre> is specified as <pre>undef</pre>, Triceps automatically
		treats it to be <pre>Triceps::clearArgs()</pre>. The last snippet and
		the following one are equivalent:
		</para>

<pre>
$self->{inputLabel} = $unit->makeLabel($rowType, $name . ".in",
	undef, \&handle, $self);
</pre>

		<para>
		No need to think, the default will do the right thing for you. Of course,
		if by some reason you don't want this destruction to happen, you'd have to
		override it with an empty function <quote><pre>sub {}</pre></quote>.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_clearing_labels">
		<title>The clearing labels</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>clearing</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Some templates don't have their own input labels, instead they just
		combine and tie together a few internal objects, and use the input
		labels of some of these internal objects as their inputs. Among
		the templates included with Triceps, JoinTwo is
		one of them, it just combines two LookupJoins. Without an input label,
		there would be no clearing, and the template object would never
		get undefined. 
		</para>

		<para>
		This can be solved by creating an artificial label that is not connected
		anywhere and has no code to execute. Its only purpose in life would be
		to clear the object when told so.
		To make life easier, rather than abusing <pre>makeLabel()</pre>,
		there is a way to create the special clearing-only labels:
		</para>

<pre>
$lb = $unit->makeClearingLabel("name", @args);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>ClearingLabel</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The arguments would be the references to the objects that need clearing,
		usually <pre>$self</pre>.  For a concrete usage example, here is how
		JoinTwo uses it:
		</para>

<pre>
$self->{clearingLabel} = $self->{unit}->makeClearingLabel(
	$self->{name} . ".clear", $self);
</pre>

		<para>
		Since this call <quote>should never fail</quote>, on
		any errors it will confess. There is no need to check the result. The
		result can be saved in a variable or can be simply ignored. If you
		throw away the result, you won't be able to access that label from the
		Perl code but it won't be lost: it will be still referenced from the
		unit, until the unit gets cleared.
		</para>

		<para>
		Note how the clearing label doesn't have a row type. In reality every
		label does how a row type, just it would be silly to abuse the random
		row types to create the clearing-only labels. Because of this, the
		clearing labels are created with a special empty row type that has no
		fields in it. If you ever want to use this row type for any other
		purposes, you can get it with the method
		</para>

<pre>
$rt = $unit->getEmptyRowType();
</pre>

		<para>
		Under the hood, the clearing label is the same as a normal label
		with Perl code, only with the special default values used
		for its construction. The normal Perl label methods would work on
		it like on a normal label.
		</para>

		<para>
		</para>

	</sect1>

</chapter>
