<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

<chapter id="ch_tables" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Tables</title>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_hello">
		<title>Hello, tables!</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		The tables are the fundamental elements of state-keeping in Triceps. 
		Let's start with a basic example:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>insert</secondary>
		</indexterm>

<!-- t/xHelloTable.t helloWorldDirect reduced, shifted left -->
<pre>
my $hwunit = Triceps::Unit->new("hwunit");
my $rtCount = Triceps::RowType->new(
	address => "string",
	count => "int32",
);

my $ttCount = Triceps::TableType->new($rtCount)
	->addSubIndex("byAddress", 
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "address" ])
	)
;
$ttCount->initialize();

my $tCount = $hwunit->makeTable($ttCount, "tCount");

while(&readLine) {
	chomp;
	my @data = split(/\W+/);

	# the common part: find if there already is a count for this address
	my $rhFound = $tCount->findBy(
		address => $data[1]
	);
	my $cnt = 0;
	if (!$rhFound->isNull()) {
		$cnt = $rhFound->getRow()->get("count");
	}

	if ($data[0] =~ /^hello$/i) {
		my $new = $rtCount->makeRowHash(
			address => $data[1],
			count => $cnt+1,
		);
		$tCount->insert($new);
	} elsif ($data[0] =~ /^count$/i) {
		&send("Received '", $data[1], "' ", $cnt + 0, " times\n");
	} else {
		&send("Unknown command '$data[0]'\n");
	}
}
</pre>

		<para>
		What happens here? The main loop reads the lines from standard input, splits
		into words and uses
		the first word as a command and the second word as a key. Note that
		it's not CSV format, it's words with the non-alphanumeric characters separating
		the words. <quote>Hello, table!</quote>, <quote>hello world</quote>, <quote>count world</quote> are examples
		of the valid inputs. For someting different, the commands are compared
		with their case ignored (but the case matters for the key).
		</para>

		<para>
		The example counts,
		how many times each key has been <pre>hello</pre>-ed, and prints this count back
		on the command <pre>count</pre>. Here is a sample, with the input
		lines printed in bold:
		</para>

<exdump>
> Hello, table!
> Hello, world!
> Hello, table!
> count world
Received 'world' 1 times
> Count table
Received 'table' 2 times
</exdump>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>procedural API</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		In this example the table is read and modified using the direct procedural calls.
		As you can see, there isn't even any need for unit scheduling and
		such. There is a scheduler-based interface to the tables too, it will be shown
		soon. But in many cases the direct access is easier. Indeed,
		this particular example could have been implemented with the plain Perl
		hashes. Nothing wrong with that either. Well, the Perl tables provide
		many more intersting ways of indexing the data. But if you don't need them,
		they don't matter. And at some future point the
		tables will be supporting the on-disk persistence, but no reason to
		bother much about that now: things are likely to change a dozen times
		yet before that happens. Feel free to just use the Perl data structures
		if they make the code easier.
		</para>

		<para>
		A table is created through a table type. This allows to stamp out
		duplicate tables of the same type, which can get handy when the
		multithreading will be added. A table is local to a thread. A table
		type can be shared between threads. To look up
		something in another thread's table, you'd either have to ask it
		through a request-reply protocol or to keep a local copy of the table.
		Such a copy can be easily done by creating a copy table from the same type.
		</para>

		<para>
		In reality, right now all the business with table types separated from
		the tables is more pain than gain. It not only adds extra steps but
		also makes difficult to define a template that acts on a table by
		defining extra features on it. Something will be done about it, I have
		a few ideas.
		</para>

		<para>
		The table type gets first created and configured, then initialized.
		After a table type is initialized, it can not be changed any more.
		That's the point of the initialization call: tell the type that all
		the configuration has been done, and it can go immutable now. 
		Fundamentally, configuting a table type just makes it collect
		bits and pieces. Nothing but the most gross errors can be detected
		at that point. At initialization time everything comes together
		and everything gets checked for consistency.  A table
		type must be fully initialized in one thread before it can be shared
		with other threads. The historic reason for this API is that it mirrors
		the &Cpp; API, which has turned out not to look that good in Perl. It's
		another candidate for a change. 
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>hashed</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A table type gets the row type and at least one index. Here it's a
		hashed index by the key field <pre>address</pre>. "Hashed" means that
		you can look up the rows by the key value but there are no promises
		about any specific row order. And the hashing is used to make the
		key comparisons more efficient. The key of a hashed index may
		consist of multiple fields.
		</para>

		<para>
		The table is then created from the table type, and given a name.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>replacement</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The rows can then be inserted into the table (and removed too, not
		shown in this example yet). The default behavior of the hashed index is to
		replace the old row if a new row with the same key is inserted.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>find</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandle</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The search in the table is done by the method <pre>findBy()</pre> with 
		the key fields of the index.  Which returns a RowHandle
		object. A RowHandle is essentially an iterator in the table. Even if
		the row is not found, a RowHandle will be still returned but it will be
		NULL, which is checked for by <pre>$rh->isNull()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		No matter which command will be used, it's always useful to look up
		the previous row for the key: its contents would be either printed
		or provide the previous value for the increase. So the model does
		it first and gets the count from it. If it's not found, then the 
		count is set to 0. 
		</para>

		<para>
		Then it looks at the command and does what it's been told.
		Updating the count amounts to creating a new row with the new
		values and inserting it into the table. It replaces the previous one.
		</para>

		<para>
		This is just the tip of the iceberg. The tables in Triceps have a lot
		more features.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_label">
		<title>Tables and labels</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		A table does not have to be operated in a procedural way. It can be
		plugged into the the scheduler machinery. Whenever a table is created,
		three labels are created with it.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
			<secondary>table</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>label API</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		The input label is for sending the modification rowops to the
		table. The table provides the handler for it that applies the
		incoming rowops to the table. 
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		The output label propagates the
		modifications done to the table. It is a dummy label, and does
		nothing by itself. It's there for chaining the other labels to it. The
		output rowop comes quite handy to propagate the table's modifications
		to the rest of the state.
		</listitem>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>tracing</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<listitem>
		The pre-modification label is also a dummy label, for chaining other
		labels to it. It sends the rowops right before they are applied
		to the table. This comes very handy for the elements that need to
		act depending on the previous state of the table, such as joins.
		The pre-modification label doesn't simply mirror the input label.
		The rows received on the input label may trigger the automatic changes
		to the table, such as an old row being deleted when a new row with
		the same key is inserted. All these modifications, be they automatic
		or explicit, will be reported to the pre-modification label.
		Since the pre-modification label is used relatively rarely, it contains
		a special optimization: if there is no label chained to it, no rowop
		will be sent to it in the first place. Don't be surprised if you
		enable the tracing and don't see it in the trace.
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>replacement</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Again, the rowops coming through these labels aren't necessarily
		the same. If a DELETE rowop comes to the input label, referring to a
		row that is not in the table, it will not propagate anywhere. If an INSERT rowop
		comes in and causes another row to be replaced, the replaced row will
		be sent to the pre-modification and output labels as a DELETE rowop first.
		</para>

		<para>
		Anf of course the table may be modified through the procedural
		interface. These modifications also produce rowops on the
		pre-modification and output labels.
		</para>

		<para>
		The labels of the table have names. They are produced by adding
		suffixes to the table name. They are "tablename.in", "tablename.pre"
		and "tablename.out".
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>scheduling</primary>
			<secondary>recursion</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>scheduling</primary>
			<secondary>loop</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>loop</primary>
			<secondary>scheduling</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>recursion</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>bundling</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		In the <quote>no bundling</quote> spirit, a rowop is sent to the pre-modification
		label right before it's applied to the table, and to the output label
		right after it's applied. If the labels executed from there need to read the table,
		they can, and will find the table in the exact state with no intervening
		modifications. However, they can't modify the table neither directly nor
		by calling its input label. When these labels are called, the table is in
		the middle of a modification and it can't accept another one. Such attempts
		are treated as recursive modifications, forbidden, and the program 
		will die on them. If you need to modify
		the table, use <pre>schedule()</pre> or <pre>loopAt()</pre> to have the next modification done
		later. However there are no guarantees about other modifications getting
		done in between. When the looped rowop executes, it might need to check the state
		of the table again and decide if its operation still makes sense.
		</para>

		<para>
		So, let's make a version of <quote>Hello, table</quote> example that passes the
		modification requests as rowops through the labels. It will print the information about
		the updates to the table as they happen, so there is no more use having a
		separate command for that. But for another demonstration let's add a
		command that would clear the counter of hellos.  Here is its code:
		</para>

<!-- t/xHelloTable.t helloWorldLabels shifted left -->
<pre>
my $hwunit = Triceps::Unit->new("hwunit");
my $rtCount = Triceps::RowType->new(
	address => "string",
	count => "int32",
);

my $ttCount = Triceps::TableType->new($rtCount)
	->addSubIndex("byAddress", 
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "address" ])
	)
;
$ttCount->initialize();

my $tCount = $hwunit->makeTable($ttCount, "tCount");

my $lbPrintCount = $hwunit->makeLabel($tCount->getRowType(),
	"lbPrintCount", undef, sub { # (label, rowop)
		my ($label, $rowop) = @_;
		my $row = $rowop->getRow();
		&send(&Triceps::opcodeString($rowop->getOpcode), " '", 
			$row->get("address"), "', count ", $row->get("count"), "\n");
	} );
$tCount->getOutputLabel()->chain($lbPrintCount);

# the updates will be sent here, for the tables to process
my $lbTableInput = $tCount->getInputLabel();

while(&readLine) {
	chomp;
	my @data = split(/\W+/);

	# the common part: find if there already is a count for this address
	my $rhFound = $tCount->findBy(
		address => $data[1]
	);
	my $cnt = 0;
	if (!$rhFound->isNull()) {
		$cnt = $rhFound->getRow()->get("count");
	}

	if ($data[0] =~ /^hello$/i) {
		$hwunit->makeHashSchedule($lbTableInput, "OP_INSERT",
			address => $data[1],
			count => $cnt+1,
		);
	} elsif ($data[0] =~ /^clear$/i) {
		$hwunit->makeHashSchedule($lbTableInput, "OP_DELETE",
			address => $data[1]
		);
	} else {
		&send("Unknown command '$data[0]'\n");
	}
	$hwunit->drainFrame();
}
</pre>

		<para>
		The table creation is the same as last time. 
		The row finding in the table is also the same.
		</para>

		<para>
		The printing of the modifications to the table is done with <pre>$lbPrintCount</pre>,
		which is connected to the table's output label. It prints the opcode,
		the address of the greeting, and the count of greetings. It will
		show us what is happening to the table as soon as it happens.
		An unit trace could be used instead but a custom printout contains
		less noise.
		The pre-modification label is of no interest here, so it's not used.
		</para>

		<para>
		The references to the labels of a table are gotten with:
		</para>

<pre>
$label = $table->getInputLabel();
$label = $table->getPreLabel();
$label = $table->getOutputLabel();
</pre>

		<para>
		The deletion does not require an exact row to be sent in. All it needs
		is a row with the keys for deletion, the rest of the fields in it
		are ignored. So the <quote>clear</quote> command puts only the key field in it.
		</para>

		<para>
		Here is an example of input (in bold) and output:
		</para>

<exdump>
> Hello, table!
OP_INSERT 'table', count 1
> Hello, world!
OP_INSERT 'world', count 1
> Hello, table!
OP_DELETE 'table', count 1
OP_INSERT 'table', count 2
> clear, table
OP_DELETE 'table', count 2
> Hello, table!
OP_INSERT 'table', count 1
</exdump>

		<para>
		An interesting thing happens after the second <quote>Hello, table!</quote>: the code
		send only an <pre>OP_INSERT</pre> but the output shows an <pre>OP_DELETE</pre> and <pre>OP_INSERT</pre>.
		The <pre>OP_DELETE</pre> for the old row gets automatically generated when a
		row with repeated key is inserted. 
		Now, depending on what you want, just sending in the first place the consequent inserts of
		rows with the same keys, and relying on the table's internal
		consistency to turn them into updates, might be a good thing or not.
		Overall it's a dirty way to write but sometimes it comes convenient.
		The clean way is to send the explicit deletes first. When the data
		goes through the table, it gets automatically cleaned.
		The subscribers to the table's output and pre-modification labels
		get the clean and consistent picture: a row never gets simply replaced, they
		always see an <pre>OP_DELETE</pre> first and only then an <pre>OP_INSERT</pre>.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_iteration">
		<title>Basic iteration through the table</title>

		<para>
		Let's add a dump of the table contents to the "Hello, table" example,
		either version of it. For that, the code needs to go through every record
		in the table:
		</para>

<!-- t/xHelloTable.t helloWorldDirect fragment, shifted left -->
<pre>
	elsif ($data[0] =~ /^dump$/i) {
		for (my $rhi = $tCount->begin(); !$rhi->isNull(); $rhi = $rhi->next()) {
			&send($rhi->getRow->printP(), "\n");
		}
	}
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>iteration</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		As you can see, the row handle works kind of like an STL iterator.
		Only the end of iteration is detected by receiving a NULL row handle.
		Calling <pre>next()</pre> on a NULL row handle is OK but it would just return
		another NULL handle.
		And there is no decrementing the iterator, you can only go forward
		with <pre>next()</pre>. The backwards iteration is in the plans but
		not implemented yet.
		</para>

		<para>
		An example of this fragment's output would be:
		</para>

<!-- t/xHelloTable.t helloWorldDirect fragment, removed backslashes -->
<exdump>
> Hello, table!
> Hello, world!
> Hello, table!
> count world
Received 'world' 1 times
> Count table
Received 'table' 2 times
> dump
address="world" count="1" 
address="table" count="2" 
</exdump>

		<para>
		The order of the rows in the printout is the same as the order of rows
		in the table's index. Which is no particular order, since it's a hashed
		index. As long as you stay with the same 64-bit AMD64 architecture
		(with LSB-first byte order), it will stay the same on consecutive runs.
		But switching to a 32-bit machine or to an MSB-first byte order (such
		as a SPARC, if you can still find one) will change the hash
		calculation, and with it the resulting row order. There are the
		ordered indexes as well, they will be described later.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_delete">
		<title>Deleting a row</title>

		<para>
		Deleting a row from a table through the input label is simple: send a
		rowop with <pre>OP_DELETE</pre>, it will find the row with the matching key 
		and delete it, as was shown above.
		In the procedural way the same can be done with the method
		<pre>deleteRow()</pre>. The added row deletion code for the main loop of 
		<quote>Hello, table</quote> (either version, but particularly relevant
		for the one from
		<xref linkend="sc_table_hello" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;)
		is:
		</para>

<!-- t/xHelloTable.t helloWorldDirect fragment, shifted left -->
<pre>
	elsif ($data[0] =~ /^delete$/i) {
		my $res = $tCount->deleteRow($rtCount->makeRowHash(
			address => $data[1],
		));
		&send("Address '", $data[1], "' is not found\n") unless $res;
	}
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>procedural API</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>remove row</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The result allows to differentiate between the situations when the 
		row was found and deleted and the row was not found.
		On any error the call confesses.
		</para>

		<para>
		However we already find the row handle in advance in <pre>$rhFound</pre>. For this case a more
		efficient form is available, and it can be added to the example as:
		</para>

<!-- t/xHelloTable.t helloWorldDirect fragment, shifted left -->
<pre>
		elsif ($data[0] =~ /^remove$/i) {
			if (!$rhFound->isNull()) {
				$tCount->remove($rhFound);
			} else {
				&send("Address '", $data[1], "' is not found\n");
			}
		}
</pre>

		<para>
		It removes a specific row handle from the table. In whichever way you
		find it, you can remove it. An attempt to remove a NULL handle would be
		an error and cause a confession.
		</para>

		<para>
		The reason why <pre>remove()</pre> is more efficient than <pre>deleteRow()</pre> is
		that <pre>deleteRow()</pre> amounts to finding the row handle by key and then
		removing it. And the <pre>OP_DELETE</pre> rowop sent to the input label
		calls <pre>deleteRow()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>deleteRow()</pre> never deletes more than one row, even if multiple
		rows match (yes, the indexes don't have to be unique).
		There isn't any method to delete multiple rows at once. Every row has
		to be deleted by itself.
		As an example, here is the implementation of the command <quote>clear</quote> for
		<quote>Hello, table</quote> that clears all the table contents by
		iterating through it:
		</para>

<!-- t/xHelloTable.t helloWorldDirect fragment, shifted left -->
<pre>
	elsif ($data[0] =~ /^clear$/i) {
		my $rhi = $tCount->begin(); 
		while (!$rhi->isNull()) {
			my $rhnext = $rhi->next();
			$tCount->remove($rhi);
			$rhi = $rhnext;
		}
	}
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>iteration</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		After a handle is removed from the table, it continues to exist, as
		long as there are references to it. It could even be inserted back into
		the table. However until (and unless) it's inserted back, it can not be
		used for iteration any more. Calling <pre>next()</pre> on a handle that
		is not in the table would just return a NULL handle. So the next row has
		to be found before removing the current one.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_RowHandle">
		<title>A closer look at the RowHandles</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandle</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A few uses of the RowHandles have been shown by now. So, what is a
		RowHandle? As Captain Obvious would say, RowHandle is a class (or
		package, in Perl terms) implementing a row handle.
		</para>

		<para>
		A row handle keeps a table's service information (including the index
		data) for a single data row, including of course a reference to the row
		itself. Each row is stored in the table through its handle. 
		The row handle is also an iterator in the table, and a special one:
		it's an iterator for <i>all</i> the table's indexes at once.
		For you SQLy people, an iterator is essentially a cursor on an index.
		For you Java people, an iterator can be used to do more than step
		sequentially through rows.
		So far only the table types with one index have been shown, but
		in reality multiple indexes are supported, potentially with quite
		complicated arrangements. More on the indexes later, for now just keep
		it in mind.  A row handle can be found through one index and then used
		to iterate through another one. Or you can iterate through one index,
		find a certain row handle and continue iterating through another index
		starting from that handle. If you remember a reference on a particular
		row handle, you can always continue iteration from that point later.
		(unless the row handle gets removed from the table).
		</para>

		<para>
		A RowHandle
		always belongs to a particular table, the RowHandles can not be shared
		nor moved between two tables, even if the tables are of the same type.
		Since the tables are single-threaded, obviously the RowHandles may not
		be shared between the threads either.
		</para>

		<para>
		However a RowHandle may exist without being inserted into a table. In
		this case it still has a spiritual connection to that table but is not
		included in the index (the iteration attempts with it would just return 
		<quote>end of the index</quote>), and will be destroyed as soon as all the
		references to it disappear.
		</para>

		<para>
		The insertion of a row into a table actually happens in two steps:
		</para>

		<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		A RowHandle is created for a row.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		This new handle is inserted into the table.
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>
		This is done with the following code:
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $table->makeRowHandle($row);
$table->insert($rh);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>insert</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Only it just so happens that to make life easier, the method
		<pre>insert()</pre> has been made to accept either a row handle or
		directly a row. If it finds a row, it makes a handle for it behind the
		curtains and then proceeds with the insertion of that handle. Passing a
		row directly is also more efficient (if you don't have a handle already
		created for it for some other reason) because the row handle creation
		then happens entirely in the &Cpp; code, without surfacing into Perl.
		</para>

		<para>
		A handle can be created for any row of a type matching the table's
		row type. For a while it was accepting only equal types but that
		was not consistent with what the labels are doing, so I've changed it.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>replacement</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The method <pre>insert()</pre> has a return value. It's often ignored but occasionally
		comes handy.  1 means that the row has been inserted successfully, and
		0 means that the row has been rejected. On errors it confesses.
		An attempt to insert a NULL handle or a handle that is already in the
		table will cause a rejection, not an error.
		Also the table's index may reject a row with duplicate key (though
		right now this option is not implemented, and the hash index silently
		replaces the old row with the new one).
		</para>

		<para>
		There is a method to find out if a row handle is in the table or not:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $rh->isInTable();
</pre>

		<para>
		Though it's used mostly for debugging, when some strange things start going on.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>find</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The searching for rows in the table by key has been previously shown with the
		method <pre>findBy()</pre>. Which happens to be a wrapper over a more general method
		<pre>find()</pre>: it constructs a row from its argument fields and then calls
		<pre>find()</pre> with that row as a sample of data to find.
		The method <pre>find()</pre> is similar to <pre>insert()</pre> in the
		handling of its arguments: the <quote>proper</quote> way is to give
		it a row handle argument, but the more efficient way is to give it a 
		row argument, and it will create the handle for it as needed before
		performing a search.
		</para>

		<para>
		Now you might wonder: huh, <pre>find()</pre> takes a row handle and returns a row
		handle? What's the point? Why not just use the first row handle? Well,
		those are different handles:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		The argument handle is normally not in the table. It's created brand
		new from a row that contains the keys that you want to find, just for
		the purpose of searching.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		The returned handle is always in the table (of course, unless it's
		NULL). It can be further used to extract back the row data, and/or for
		iteration.
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		Though nothing really prevents you from searching for a handle that is
		already in the table. You'll just get back the same handle, after
		gratuitously spending some CPU time. (There are exceptions to this,
		with the more complex indexes that will be described later).
		</para>

		<para>
		Why do you need to create new a row handle just for the search? Due to
		the internal mechanics of the implementation. A handle stores the
		helper information for the index. For example, the hash index
		calculates the hash value of all the row's key fields once and
		stores it in the row handle. Despite it being called a hash index, it
		really stores the data in a tree, with the hash value used to speed up
		the comparisons for the tree order. It's much easier to make both the
		<pre>insert()</pre> and <pre>find()</pre> work with the hash value and row reference
		stored in the same way in a handle than to implement them differently. Because of
		this, <pre>find()</pre> uses the exactly same row handle argument format as
		<pre>insert()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		Can you create multiple row handles referring to the same row? Sure,
		knock yourself out. From the table's perspective it's the same thing as
		multiple row handles for multiple copies of the row with the same values
		in them, only using less memory.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is more to the row handles than has been touched upon yet. It
		will all be revealed when more of the table features are described.
		The internal structure of the row handles will be described in the
		<xref linkend="sc_table_indextree" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_fifo">
		<title>A window is a FIFO</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>window</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>FIFO</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		A fairly typical situation in the CEP world is when a model needs to
		keep a limited history of events. For a simple example, let's discuss,
		how to remember the last two trades per stock symbol. The size of two
		has been chosen to keep the sample input and outputs small.
		</para>

		<para>
		This is normally called a window logic, with a sliding window. You can
		think of it in a mechanical analogy: as the trades become available,
		they get printed on a long tape. However the tape is covered with a
		masking plate. The plate has a window cut in it that lets you see only
		the last two trades.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Coral8</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Some CEP systems have the special data structures that implement this
		logic, that are called windows. Triceps has a feature on a table
		instead that makes a table work as a window. It's not unique in this
		department: for example Coral8 does the opposite, calls everything a
		window, even if some windows are really tables in every regard but
		name.
		</para>

		<para>
		Here is a Triceps example of keeping the window for the last two trades
		and iteration over it:
		</para>

<!-- t/xWindow.t doWindow -->
<pre>
our $uTrades = Triceps::Unit->new("uTrades");
our $rtTrade = Triceps::RowType->new(
	id => "int32", # trade unique id
	symbol => "string", # symbol traded
	price => "float64",
	size => "float64", # number of shares traded
);

our $ttWindow = Triceps::TableType->new($rtTrade)
	->addSubIndex("bySymbol", 
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "symbol" ])
			->addSubIndex("last2",
				Triceps::IndexType->newFifo(limit => 2)
			)
	)
;
$ttWindow->initialize();
our $tWindow = $uTrades->makeTable($ttWindow, "tWindow");

# remember the index type by symbol, for searching on it
our $itSymbol = $ttWindow->findSubIndex("bySymbol");
# remember the FIFO index, for finding the start of the group
our $itLast2 = $itSymbol->findSubIndex("last2");

# print out the changes to the table as they happen
our $lbWindowPrint = $uTrades->makeLabel($rtTrade, "lbWindowPrint",
	undef, sub { # (label, rowop)
		&send($_[1]->printP(), "\n"); # print the change
	});
$tWindow->getOutputLabel()->chain($lbWindowPrint);

while(&readLine) {
	chomp;
	my $rTrade = $rtTrade->makeRowArray(split(/,/));
	my $rhTrade = $tWindow->makeRowHandle($rTrade);
	$tWindow->insert($rhTrade);
	# There are two ways to find the first record for this
	# symbol. Use one way for the symbol AAA and the other for the rest.
	my $rhFirst;
	if ($rTrade->get("symbol") eq "AAA") {
		$rhFirst = $tWindow->findIdx($itSymbol, $rTrade);
	} else  {
		# $rhTrade is now in the table but it's the last record
		$rhFirst = $rhTrade->firstOfGroupIdx($itLast2);
	}
	my $rhEnd = $rhFirst->nextGroupIdx($itLast2);
	&send("New contents:\n");
	for (my $rhi = $rhFirst; 
			!$rhi->same($rhEnd); $rhi = $rhi->nextIdx($itLast2)) {
		&send("  ", $rhi->getRow()->printP(), "\n");
	}
}
</pre>

		<para>
		This example reads the trade records in CSV format, inserts them into
		the table, and then prints the actual modifications reported by the
		table and the new state of the window for this symbol. And here is a sample
		log, with the input lines in bold:
		</para>

<exdump>
> 1,AAA,10,10
tWindow.out OP_INSERT id="1" symbol="AAA" price="10" size="10" 
New contents:
  id="1" symbol="AAA" price="10" size="10" 
> 2,BBB,100,100
tWindow.out OP_INSERT id="2" symbol="BBB" price="100" size="100" 
New contents:
  id="2" symbol="BBB" price="100" size="100" 
> 3,AAA,20,20
tWindow.out OP_INSERT id="3" symbol="AAA" price="20" size="20" 
New contents:
  id="1" symbol="AAA" price="10" size="10" 
  id="3" symbol="AAA" price="20" size="20" 
> 4,BBB,200,200
tWindow.out OP_INSERT id="4" symbol="BBB" price="200" size="200" 
New contents:
  id="2" symbol="BBB" price="100" size="100" 
  id="4" symbol="BBB" price="200" size="200" 
> 5,AAA,30,30
tWindow.out OP_DELETE id="1" symbol="AAA" price="10" size="10" 
tWindow.out OP_INSERT id="5" symbol="AAA" price="30" size="30" 
New contents:
  id="3" symbol="AAA" price="20" size="20" 
  id="5" symbol="AAA" price="30" size="30" 
> 6,BBB,300,300
tWindow.out OP_DELETE id="2" symbol="BBB" price="100" size="100" 
tWindow.out OP_INSERT id="6" symbol="BBB" price="300" size="300" 
New contents:
  id="4" symbol="BBB" price="200" size="200" 
  id="6" symbol="BBB" price="300" size="300" 
</exdump>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>group</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>replacement</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		You can see that the window logic works: at no time is there
		more than two rows in each group. As more rows are inserted,
		the oldest rows get deleted.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>table</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>index</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Now let's dig into the code.
		The first thing to notice is that the table type has two
		indexes (strictly speaking, index types, but most of the time
		they can be called indexes without creating a confusion) in it. Unlike
		your typical database, the indexes in this example are nested.
		</para>

<pre>
TableType
+-IndexType Hash "bySymbol"
  +-IndexType Fifo "last2"
</pre>

		<para>
		If you follow the nesting, you can see, that the first call <pre>addSubIndex()</pre>
		adds an index type to the table type, while the textually second
		<pre>addSubIndex()</pre> adds an index to the previous index.
		</para>

		<para>
		The same can also be written out in multiple separate calls,
		with the intermediate results stored in the variables:
		</para>

<pre>
$itLast2 = Triceps::IndexType->newFifo(limit => 2);
$itSymbol = Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "symbol" ]);
$itSymbol->addSubIndex("last2", $itLast2);
$ttWindow = Triceps::TableType->new($rtTrade);
$ttWindow->addSubIndex("bySymbol", $itSymbol);
</pre>

		<para>
		I'm not perfectly happy with the way the table types are constructed
		with the index types right now, since the parenthesis levels have
		turned out a bit hard to track. This is another example of following
		the &Cpp; API in Perl that didn't work out too well, and it will change
		in the future. But for now please bear with it.
		</para>

		<para>
		The index nesting is kind of intuitively clear, but the details may
		take some time to get your head wrapped around them. You can think of
		it as the inner index type creating the miniature tables that hold the
		rows, and then the outer index holding not individual rows but those
		miniature tables. So, to find the rows in the table you go through two
		levels of indexes: first through the outer index, and then through the
		inner one. The table takes care of these details and makes them
		transparent, unless you want to stop your search at an intermediate
		level: such as, to find <i>all</i> the transactions with a given
		symbol, you need to do a search in the outer index, but then from that
		point iterate through all rows in the found inner index. For this you
		obviously have to tell the table, where do you want to stop in
		the search.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>FIFO</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The outer index is the hash index that we've seen before, the inner
		index is a FIFO index. A FIFO index doesn't have any key, it just keeps
		the rows in the order they were inserted. You can search in a FIFO
		index but most of the time it's not the best idea: since it has no
		keys, it searches linearly through all its rows until it finds an exact
		match (or runs out of rows). It's a reasonable last-resort way but it's
		not fast and in many cases not what you want. This also sends
		a few ripples through the row deletion. Remember that the method
		<pre>deleteRow()</pre> and sending the <pre>OP_DELETE</pre> to the table's input label invoke
		<pre>find()</pre>, which would cause the linear search on the FIFO indexes. So
		when you use a FIFO index, it's usually better to find the row handle
		you want to delete in some other way and then call <pre>remove()</pre> on it, or
		use another approach that will be shown later. Or just keep inserting
		the rows and never delete them, like this example does.
		</para>

		<para>
		A FIFO index may contain multiple copies of an exact same
		row. It doesn't care, it just keeps whatever rows were given to it in
		whatever order they were given. 
		</para>

		<para>
		By default a FIFO index just keeps whatever rows come to it. However it
		may have a few options. Setting the option <pre>limit</pre> limits the number of
		rows stored in the index (not per the whole table but per one of those
		<quote>miniature tables</quote>). When you try to insert one row too many, the oldest
		row gets thrown out, and the limit stays unbroken. That's what creates
		the window behavior: keep the most recent N rows.
		</para>

		<para>
		If you look at the sample output, you can see that inserting the rows
		with ids 1-4 generates only the insert events on the table. But the
		rows 5 and 6 start overflowing their FIFO indexes, and cause the oldest
		row to be automatically deleted before completing the insert of the new
		one.
		</para>

		<para>
		A FIFO index doesn't have to be nested inside a hash index. If you put
		a FIFO index at the top level, it will control the whole table. So it
		would be not two last record per key but two last records inserted in the
		whole table.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>initialization</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>index</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Continuing with the example, the table gets created, and then the index
		types get extracted back from the table type. Now, why not just write
		out the table type creation with intermediate variables 
		as shown above and remember the index
		references? At some point in the past this actually would have worked
		but not any more. It has to do with the way the table type and its
		index types are connected. It's occasionally convenient to create one
		index type and then reuse it in multiple table types. However for the
		whole thing to work, the index type must be tied to its particular
		table type. This tying together happens when the table type is
		initialized. If you put the same index type into two table types, then when
		the first table type is initialized, the index type will get tied to
		it. The second table type would then fail to initialize because an
		index in it is already tied elsewhere. To get around this
		dilemma, now when you call <pre>addSubIndex()</pre>, it doesn't connect the
		original index type, instead it makes a copy of it. That copy then gets
		tied with the table type and later gets returned back with <pre>findSubIndex()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The table methods that take an index type argument
		absolutely require that the index type must be tied to that table's type. If
		you try to pass a seemingly the same index type that has not been tied,
		or has been tied to a different table type, that is an error. 
		</para>

		<para>
		One last note on this subject: there is
		no interdependency between the methods <pre>makeTable()</pre> and <pre>findSubIndex()</pre>,
		they can be done in either order.
		</para>

		<para>
		The example output comes from two sources. The running updates on the table's
		modifications (the lines with <pre>OP_INSERT</pre> and <pre>OP_DELETE</pre>) are printed from the label
		<pre>$lbWindowPrint</pre>. The new window contents is printed from the main loop.
		</para>

		<para>
		The main loop reads the trade records in the simple
		CSV format without the opcode, and for simplicity inserts directly 
		into the table with the procedural API, bypassing
		the scheduler. After the row is inserted, the contents of its index
		group (that <quote>miniature table</quote>) gets printed. The insertion could as
		well have been done with passing directly the row reference, without
		explicitly creating a handle. But that handle will be used to
		demonstrate an interesting point.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>iteration</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>group</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		To print the contents of an index group, we need to find its
		boundaries. In Triceps these boundaries are expressed as the first row
		handle of the group, and as the row handle right after the group. There
		is an internal logic to that, and it will be explained later, but for
		now just take it on faith.
		</para>

		<para>
		With the information we have, there are two ways to find the first row of the group:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>find</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>find</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		With the table's method <pre>findIdx()</pre>. It's very much like <pre>find()</pre>, only it
		has an extra argument of a specific index type. If the index type given
		has no further nesting in it, <pre>findIdx()</pre> works exactly like <pre>find()</pre>. In
		fact, <pre>find()</pre> is exactly such a special case of <pre>findIdx()</pre> with an
		automatically chosen index type. If you use an index type with further nesting
		under it, <pre>findIdx()</pre> will return the handle of the first row in the
		group under it (or the usual NULL row handle if not found).
		</listitem>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandle</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<listitem>
		If we create the row handle explicitly before inserting it into the
		table, as was done in the example, that will be the exact row handle
		inserted into the table. Not a copy or anything but this particular row
		handle. After a row handle gets inserted into the table, it knows its
		position in the indexes. It knows, in which group it is.
		And we still have a reference to it. So then
		we can use this knowledge to navigate within the group, 
		jump to the first row handle in the group
		with <pre>firstOfGroupIdx()</pre>. It also takes an index type but in this case
		it's the type that controls the group, the FIFO index in out case.
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		The example shows both ways. As a demonstration, it uses the first way
		if the symbol is <quote>AAA</quote> and the second way for all the other symbols.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>iteration</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The end boundary is found by calling <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> on the first row's
		handle. The handle of the newly inserted row could have also been used for
		<pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre>, or any other handle in the group. For any
		handle belonging to the same group, the result is exactly the same.
		</para>

		<para>
		And finally, after the iteration boundaries have been found,
		the iteration on the group can run. The end
		condition comparison is done with <pre>same()</pre>, to compare the row
		handle references and not just their Perl-level wrappers. The stepping
		is done with <pre>nextIdx()</pre>, with is exactly like <pre>next()</pre> but according to a
		particular index, the FIFO one. This has actually been done purely to
		show off this method. In this particular case the result produced by
		<pre>next()</pre>, <pre>nextIdx()</pre> on the FIFO index type and <pre>nextIdx()</pre> on 
		the outer hash index type is exactly the same. We'll come to the reasons of
		that yet.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>aggregation</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Looking forward, as you iterate through the group, you could do some manual aggregation
		along the way. For example, find the average price of the last two
		trades, and then do something useful with it.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is also a piece of information that you can find without iteration:
		the size of the group.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>group size</secondary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
$size = $table->groupSizeIdx($idxType, $row_or_rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		This information is important for the joins, and iterating every time through the
		group is inefficient if all you want to get is the group size. Since when you need
		this data you usually have the row and not the row handle, this operation
		accepts either and implicitly performs a <pre>findIdx()</pre> on the row to find the
		row handle. Moreover, even if it receives the argument of a row handle that
		is not in the table, it will also automatically perform a <pre>findIdx()</pre> on it
		(though calling it for a row handle in
		the table is more efficient because the group would not need to be
		looked up first). 
		</para>

		<para>
		If there is no such group in the table, the result will be 0. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The <pre>$idxType</pre> argument is the non-leaf parent index of the group. (Using a
		leaf index type is not an error but it always returns 0, because there
		are no groups under it). It's basically the same index type as you
		would use in <pre>findIdx()</pre> to find the first row of the group
		or in <pre>firstOfGroupIdx()</pre> or <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> to find the boundaries
		of thr group.
		Remember, a non-leaf
		index type defines the groups, and the nested index types under it
		define the order in those groups (and possibly further break them down
		into sub-groups).
		</para>

		<para>
		It's a bit confusing, so let's recap with another example.
		If you have a table type defined as:
		</para>

<!-- from t/xJoin.t -->
<pre>
our $ttPosition = Triceps::TableType->new($rtPosition)
	->addSubIndex("primary",
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "date", "customer", "symbol" ])
	)
	->addSubIndex("currencyLookup", # for joining with currency conversion
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "date", "currency" ])
		->addSubIndex("grouping", Triceps::IndexType->newFifo())
	)
	->addSubIndex("byDate", # for cleaning by date
		Triceps::SimpleOrderedIndex->new(date => "ASC")
		->addSubIndex("grouping", Triceps::IndexType->newFifo())
	)
;
</pre>

		<para>
		then it would make sense to call <pre>groupSizeIdx()</pre>, 
		<pre>firstOfGroupIdx()</pre> and <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre>
		with the indexes
		<quote>currencyLookup</quote> or <quote>byDate</quote> 
		but not with <quote>primary</quote>,
		<quote>currencyLookup/grouping</quote> nor <quote>byDate/grouping</quote>.  You can call
		<pre>findIdx()</pre> with any index, but for
		<quote>currencyLookup</quote> or <quote>byDate</quote> it would return the first row of the group
		while for
		<quote>primary</quote>, <quote>currencyLookup/grouping</quote> or <quote>byDate/grouping</quote>
		it would return the only matching row. On the other hand, for iteration in a group, it makes
		sense to call <pre>nextIdx()</pre> only on 
		<quote>primary</quote>, <quote>currencyLookup/grouping</quote> or <quote>byDate/grouping</quote>.
		Calling <pre>nextIdx()</pre> on the non-leaf index types is not an error
		but it would in effect resolve to the same thing as using their
		first leaf sub-indexes.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_secondary">
		<title>Secondary indexes</title>

		<para>
		The last example dealt only with the row inserts, because it could not
		handle the deletions that well. What if the trades may get cancelled
		and have to be removed from the table? There is a solution to this
		problem: add one more index. Only this time not nested but in parallel.
		The indexes in the table type become tree-formed:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>hashed</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>secondary</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>tree</secondary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
TableType
+-IndexType Hash "byId" (id)
+-IndexType Hash "bySymbol" (symbol)
  +-IndexType Fifo "last2"
</pre>

		<para>
		It's very much like the common relational databases where you can
		define multiple indexes on the same table. Both indexes <pre>byId</pre> and
		<pre>bySymbol</pre> (together with its nested sub-index) refer to the same
		set of rows stored in the table. Only <pre>byId</pre> allows to easily find
		the records by the unique id, while <pre>bySymbol</pre> is responsible for
		keeping then grouped by the symbol, in FIFO order. It could be said
		that <pre>byId</pre> is the primary index (since it has a unique key) and
		<pre>bySymbol</pre> is a secondary one (since it does the grouping) but
		from the Triceps'es standpoint they are pretty much equal and parallel
		to each other.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>aggregation</primary>
			<secondary>manual</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		To illustrate the point, here is a modified version of the previous
		example. Not only does it manage the deletes but also computes the
		average price of the collected transactions as it iterates through
		the group, thus performing a manual aggregation.
		</para>

<!-- t/xWindow.t doSecondary -->
<pre>
our $uTrades = Triceps::Unit->new("uTrades");
our $rtTrade = Triceps::RowType->new(
	id => "int32", # trade unique id
	symbol => "string", # symbol traded
	price => "float64",
	size => "float64", # number of shares traded
);

our $ttWindow = Triceps::TableType->new($rtTrade)
	->addSubIndex("byId", 
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "id" ])
	)
	->addSubIndex("bySymbol", 
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "symbol" ])
			->addSubIndex("last2",
				Triceps::IndexType->newFifo(limit => 2)
			)
	)
;
$ttWindow->initialize();
our $tWindow = $uTrades->makeTable($ttWindow, "tWindow");

# remember the index type by symbol, for searching on it
our $itSymbol = $ttWindow->findSubIndex("bySymbol");
# remember the FIFO index, for finding the start of the group
our $itLast2 = $itSymbol->findSubIndex("last2");

# remember, which was the last row modified
our $rLastMod;
our $lbRememberLastMod = $uTrades->makeLabel($rtTrade, "lbRememberLastMod",
	undef, sub { # (label, rowop)
		$rLastMod = $_[1]->getRow();
	});
$tWindow->getOutputLabel()->chain($lbRememberLastMod);

# Print the average price of the symbol in the last modified row
sub printAverage # (row)
{
	return unless defined $rLastMod;
	my $rhFirst = $tWindow->findIdx($itSymbol, $rLastMod);
	my $rhEnd = $rhFirst->nextGroupIdx($itLast2);
	&send("Contents:\n");
	my $avg;
	my ($sum, $count);
	for (my $rhi = $rhFirst; 
			!$rhi->same($rhEnd); $rhi = $rhi->nextIdx($itLast2)) {
		&send("  ", $rhi->getRow()->printP(), "\n");
		$count++;
		$sum += $rhi->getRow()->get("price");
	}
	if ($count) {
		$avg = $sum/$count;
	}
	&send("Average price: ", (defined $avg? $avg: "Undefined"), "\n");
}

while(&readLine) {
	chomp;
	my @data = split(/,/);
	$uTrades->makeArrayCall($tWindow->getInputLabel(), @data);
	&printAverage();
	undef $rLastMod; # clear for the next iteration
	$uTrades->drainFrame(); # just in case, for completeness
}
</pre>

		<para>
		And an example of its work, with the input lines shown in bold:
		</para>

<exdump>
> OP_INSERT,1,AAA,10,10
Contents:
  id="1" symbol="AAA" price="10" size="10" 
Average price: 10
> OP_INSERT,2,BBB,100,100
Contents:
  id="2" symbol="BBB" price="100" size="100" 
Average price: 100
> OP_INSERT,3,AAA,20,20
Contents:
  id="1" symbol="AAA" price="10" size="10" 
  id="3" symbol="AAA" price="20" size="20" 
Average price: 15
> OP_INSERT,4,BBB,200,200
Contents:
  id="2" symbol="BBB" price="100" size="100" 
  id="4" symbol="BBB" price="200" size="200" 
Average price: 150
> OP_INSERT,5,AAA,30,30
Contents:
  id="3" symbol="AAA" price="20" size="20" 
  id="5" symbol="AAA" price="30" size="30" 
Average price: 25
> OP_INSERT,6,BBB,300,300
Contents:
  id="4" symbol="BBB" price="200" size="200" 
  id="6" symbol="BBB" price="300" size="300" 
Average price: 250
> OP_DELETE,3
Contents:
  id="5" symbol="AAA" price="30" size="30" 
Average price: 30
> OP_DELETE,5
Contents:
Average price: Undefined
</exdump>

		<para>
		The input has changed: now an extra column is prepended to it,
		containing the opcode for the row. The updates to the table are not
		printed any more, but the calculated average price is printed after the
		new contents of the group.
		</para>

		<para>
		In the code, the first obvious addition is the extra index in the table
		type. The label that used to print the updates is gone, and replaced
		with another one, that remembers the last modified row in a global
		variable.
		</para>

		<para>
		That last modified row is then used in the function <pre>printAverage()</pre>
		to find the group for iteration.
		Why? Could not we just remember the symbol from the input data? Not always.
		As you can see from the last two input rows with <pre>OP_DELETE</pre>, the
		trade id is the only field required to find and delete a row using the
		index <pre>byId</pre>. So these trade cancellation rows take a shortcut and
		only provide the trade id, not the rest of the fields. If we try to
		remember the symbol fields from them, we'd remember an <pre>undef</pre>.
		Can we just look up the row by id after the incoming rowop has been processed?
		Not after the deletion.
		If we try to find the symbol by looking up the row
		after the deletion, we will find nothing, because the row will already
		be deleted. We could look up the row in the table before the deletion,
		and remember it, and afterwards do the look-up of the group by
		it. But since on deletion the row with will come to the table's
		output label anyway, we can just ride the wave and remember it instead
		of doing the manual look-up. And this also spares the need of creating
		a row with the last symbol for searching: we get a ready pre-made row
		with the right symbol in it.
		</para>

		<para>
		Note that in this example, unlike the previous one, there are no two
		ways of finding the group any more: after deletion the row handle will
		not be in the table any more, and could not be used to jump directly to
		the beginning of its group. <pre>findIdx()</pre> has to be used to find the group.
		</para>

		<para>
		By the time <pre>printAverage()</pre> executes, it could happen that all the rows with that symbol
		will be gone, and the group will disappear. This situation is handled
		nicely in an automatic way: <pre>findIdx()</pre> will return a NULL row handle, for which then
		<pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> will also return a NULL row handle. The for-loop will
		immediately satisfy the condition of <pre>$rhi->same($rhEnd)</pre>, it will
		make no iterations, the <pre>$count</pre> and <pre>$avg</pre> will be left undefined.
		In result no rows will be printed and the average value will be printed
		as <quote>Undefined</quote>, as you can see in the reaction to the last input row
		in the sample output.
		</para>

		<para>
		The main loop becomes reduced to reading the input, splitting the line,
		separating the opcode, calling the table's input label, and printing
		the average. The auto-conversion from the opcode name is used when
		constructing the rowop. Normally it's not a good practice, since the
		program will die if it finds a bad rowop in the input, but good enough
		for a small example. The direct use of <pre>$uTrades->call()</pre> 
		guarantees that by the time it returns, the last modified row
		will be remembered in <pre>$rLastMod</pre>, available for <pre>printAverage()</pre>
		to use.
		</para>

		<para>
		After the average is calculated, <pre>$rLastMod</pre> is reset to prevent it from
		accidentally affecting the next row. If the next row is an attempt to
		delete a trade id that is not in the table any more, the DELTE operation
		will have no effect on the table, and nothing will be sent from the
		table's output label. <pre>$rLastMod</pre> will stay undefined, and
		<pre>printAverage()</pre> will check it and immediately return.
		An attempt to pass an <pre>undef</pre> argument to <pre>findIdx()</pre> would be an error.
		</para>

		<para>
		The final <pre>$uTrades->drainFrame()</pre> is there purely for
		completeness. In this case we know that nothing will be scheduled by
		the labels downstream from the table, and there will be nothing to
		drain.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>find</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>default</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>order</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>primary</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Now, an interesting question is: how does the table know, that to
		delete a row, it has to find it using the field <pre>id</pre>? Or, since
		the deletion internally uses <pre>find()</pre>, the more precise question is: how
		does <pre>find()</pre> know that it has to use the index <pre>byId</pre>? It doesn't
		use any magic. It simply goes by the first index defined in the table.
		That's why the index <pre>byId</pre> has been very carefully placed before
		<pre>bySymbol</pre>. The same principle applies to all the other functions
		like <pre>next()</pre>, that use an index but don't receive one as an argument:
		the first index is always the default index. There is a bit more detail to
		it, but that's the rough principle.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_sorted">
		<title>Sorted index</title>

		<para>
		The hashed index provides a way to store rows indexed by a key. It is fast
		but it has a price to pay for that speed: when iterating through it,
		the records come in an unpredictable (though repeatable, within a
		particular machine architecture) order determined by the hash function.
		If the order doesn't matter, that's fine. But often the order does
		matter, and is desirable even at the tradeoff of the reduced performance.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>sorted</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The sorted index provides a solution for this problem. It is created
		with:
		</para>

<pre>
$it = Triceps::IndexType->newPerlSorted($sortName,
  $initFunc, $compareFunc, @args);
</pre>

		<para>
		The <quote>Perl</quote> in <quote>newPerlSorted</quote> refers to the
		fact that the sorting order is specified as a Perl comparison function.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>$sortName</pre> is just a symbolic name for printouts. It's used when you
		call <pre>$it->print()</pre> (directly or as a recursive call from the table
		type print) to let you know what kind of index type it is, since it
		can't print the compiled comparison function. It is also used in the
		error messages if something dies inside the comparison function: the
		comparison is executed from deep inside the &Cpp; code, and by that time
		the <pre>$sortName</pre> is the only way to identify the source of the problems.
		It's not the same name as used to connect the index type into the table
		type hierarchy with <pre>addSubIndex()</pre>. As usual, an index type may be
		reused in multiple hierarchies, with different names, but in all cases
		it will also keep the same <pre>$sortName</pre>. This may be easier to show with an
		example:
		</para>

<!-- t/SortedIndexType.t -->
<pre>
$rt1 = Triceps::RowType->new(
	a => "int32",
	b => "string",
);

$it1 = Triceps::IndexType->newPerlSorted("basic", undef, \&compBasic);

$tt1 = Triceps::TableType->new($rt1)
	->addSubIndex("primary", $it1)
; 

$tt2 = Triceps::TableType->new($rt1)
	->addSubIndex("first", $it1)
; 

print $tt1->print(), "\n";
print $tt2->print(), "\n";
</pre>

		<para>
		The print calls in it will produce:
		</para>

<pre>
table (
  row {
    int32 a,
    string b,
  }
) {
  index PerlSortedIndex(basic) primary,
}
table (
  row {
    int32 a,
    string b,
  }
) {
  index PerlSortedIndex(basic) first,
}
</pre>

		<para>
		Both the name of the index type in the table type and the name of
		the sorted index type are printed, but in different spots.
		</para>

		<para>
		The <pre>$initFunc</pre> and/or <pre>$compareFunc</pre> function references 
		(or, as usual, they may be specified as source code strings) specify the sorting order.
		One of them may be left undefined but not both. <pre>@args</pre> are the optional
		arguments that will be passed to both functions.
		</para>

		<para>
		The easiest but least flexible way is to just use the
		<pre>$compareFunc</pre>. It gets two Rows (not RowHandles!) as arguments, plus
		whatever is specified in <pre>@args</pre>. It returns the usual Perl-style
		<quote>&lt;=&gt;</quote> result. For example:
		</para>

<pre>
sub compBasic # ($row1, $row2)
{
	return $_[0]->get("a") <=> $_[1]->get("a");
}
</pre>

		<para>
		Don't forget to use <quote>&lt;=&gt;</quote> for the numbers and <quote>cmp</quote> for the
		strings. The typical Perl idiom for sorting by more than one field is
		to connect them by <quote>||</quote>.
		</para>

		<para>
		Or, if we want to specify the field names as arguments, we could define
		a sort function that sorts first by a numeric field in ascending order,
		then by a string field in descending order:
		</para>

<pre>
sub compAscDesc # ($row1, $row2, $numFldAsc, $strFldDesc)
{
	my ($row1, $row2, $numf, $strf) = @_;
	return $row1->get($numf) <=> $row2->get($numf)
		|| $row2->get($strf) cmp $row1->get($strf); # backwards for descending
}

my $sit = Triceps::IndexType->newPerlSorted("by_a_b", undef,
	\&compAscDesc, "a", "b");
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>sticky error</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		This assumes that the row type will have a numeric field <quote>a</quote> and a
		string field <quote>b</quote>. If it doesn't then this will not
		be discovered until you create a table and try to insert some rows into
		it, which will finally call the comparison function. At which point
		the attempt to get a non-existing field will confess, this error
		will be caught by the table and set the sticky error in it. The insert
		operation will confess with this error, and any future operations
		on the table will also confess with this error (this is the meaning of
		<quote>sticky</quote>), the table will become
		unusable.
		</para>

		<para>
		The <pre>$initFunc</pre> provides a way to do that check and more up front.
		It is called at the table type initialization time. By this time all
		this extra information is known, and it gets the references to the
		table type, index type (itself, but with the class stripped back to
		Triceps::IndexType), row type, and whatever extra arguments that were
		passed. It can do all the checks once.
		</para>

		<para>
		The init function's return value is kind of backwards to everything
		else: on success it returns <pre>undef</pre>, on error it returns the error
		message. It could die too, but simply returning an error message is
		somewhat nicer. The returned error messages may contain multiple 
		lines separated by <quote>\n</quote>, so it should try to collect all the error
		information it can.
		</para>

		<para>
		The init function that would check the arguments for the
		last example can be defined as:
		</para>

<!-- t/xSnippets.t IndexType init -->
<pre>
sub initNumStr # ($tabt, $idxt, $rowt, @args)
{
	my ($tabt, $idxt, $rowt, @args) = @_;
	my %def = $rowt->getdef(); # the field definition
	my $errors; # collect as many errors as possible
	my $t;

	if ($#args != 1) {
		$errors .= "Received " . ($#args + 1) . " arguments, must be 2.\n"
	} else {
		$t = $def{$args[0]};
		if ($t !~ /int32$|int64$|float64$/) {
			$errors .= "Field '" . $args[0] . "' is not of numeric type.\n"
		}
		$t = $def{$args[1]};
		if ($t !~ /string$|uint8/) {
			$errors .= "Field '" . $args[1] . "' is not of string type.\n"
		}
	}

	if (defined $errors) {
		# help with diagnostics, append the row type to the error listing
		$errors .= "the row type is:\n";
		$errors .= $rowt->print();
	}
	return $errors;
}

my $sit = Triceps::IndexType->newPerlSorted("by_a_b", \&initNumStr,
	\&compAscDesc, "a", "b");
</pre>

		<para>
		The init function can do even better: it can create and set
		the comparison function. It's done with:
		</para>

<pre>
$idxt->setComparator($compareFunc);
</pre>

		<para>
		When the init function sets the comparator,
		the compare function argument in <pre>newPerlSorted()</pre>
		can be left undefined, because <pre>setComparator()</pre> would override
		it anyway. But one way or the other, the compare function
		must be set, or the index type initialization and with it
		the table type initialization will fail.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>aggregation</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		By the way, the sorted index type init function is <b>not</b> of the
		same kind as the aggregator type init function. The aggregator type
		could use an init function of this kind too, but at the time it looked
		like too much extra complexity. It probably will be added in the
		future. But more about aggregators later.
		</para>

		<para>
		A fancier example of the init function will be shown in the next
		section.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>hashed</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Internally the implementation of the sorted index shares much
		with the hashed index. They both are implemented as trees but they
		compare the rows in different ways. The hashed index is aimed
		for speed, the sorted index for flexibility. The common implementation
		means that they share certain traits. Both kinds have the unique keys,
		there can not be two rows with the same key in an index of either kind.
		Both kinds allow to nest other indexes in them.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The handling of the fatal errors (as in <pre>die()</pre>) in the initialization 
		and especially comparison functions is an interesting subject.
		The errors propagate properly through the table,
		and the table operations confess with the Perl handler's error message.
		But since an error in the comparison function means that things are going
		very, very wrong, after that the table becomes inoperative and will die
		on all the subsequent operations as well. You need to be very careful
		in writing these functions.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_ordered">
		<title>Ordered index</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>ordered</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>template</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>code generation</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		To specify the sorting order in a more SQL-like fashion, Triceps
		has the class SimpleOrderedIndex. It's implemented entirely in Perl, on
		top of the sorted index. Besides being useful by itself, it shows off
		two concepts: the initialization function of the sorted index, and the
		template with code generation on the fly.
		</para>

		<para>
		First, how to create an ordered index:
		</para>

<pre>
$it = Triceps::SimpleOrderedIndex->new($fieldName => $order, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		The arguments are the key fields. <pre>$order</pre> is one of
		<pre>"ASC"</pre> for ascending and <pre>"DESC"</pre> for descending.
		Here is an example of a table with this index:
		</para>

<pre>
my $tabType = Triceps::TableType->new($rowType)
	->addSubIndex("sorted", 
		Triceps::SimpleOrderedIndex->new(
			a => "ASC",
			b => "DESC",
		)
	);
</pre>

		<para>
		When it gets translated into a sorted index, the comparison function
		gets generated automatically. It's smart enough to generate the string
		comparisons for the <pre>string</pre> and <pre>uint8</pre> fields, and the numeric
		comparisons for the numeric fields. It's not smart enough to do the
		locale-specific comparisons for the strings and locale-agnostic for the
		<pre>uint8</pre>, it just uses whatever you have set up in <pre>cmp</pre> for both. It
		treats the NULL field values as numeric 0 or empty strings. It doesn't
		handle the array fields at all but can at least detect such attempts
		and flag them as errors.
		</para>

		<para>
		A weird artifact of the boundary between &Cpp; and Perl is that when you
		get the index type back from the table type like
		</para>

<pre>
$sortIdx = $tabType->findSubIndex("sorted");
</pre>

		<para>
		the reference stored in <pre>$sortIdx</pre> will be of the base type
		Triceps::IndexType. That's because the &Cpp; internals of the TableType
		object know nothing about any derived Perl types. But it's no big deal,
		since there are no other useful methods for SimpleOrderedIndex anyway.
		For the future, I have an idea of a workaround, but it has to wait
		for the future.
		</para>

		<para>
		If you call <pre>$sortIdx->print()</pre>, it will give you an idea of how it
		was constructed:
		</para>

<pre>
PerlSortedIndex(SimpleOrder a ASC, b DESC, )
</pre>

		<para>
		The contents of the parenthesis is a sort name from the sorted index'es
		standpoint. It's an arbitrary string. But when the ordered index
		prepares this string to pass to the sorted index, it puts its
		arguments into it.
		</para>

		<para>
		Now the interesting part, I want to show the implementation of the
		ordered index. It's not too big and it shows the flexibility and the
		extensibility of Triceps:
		</para>

<!-- lib/Triceps/SimpleOrderedIndex.pm with "XXX" lines dropped  -->
<pre>
package Triceps::SimpleOrderedIndex;

our @ISA = qw(Triceps::IndexType);

# Create a new ordered index. The order is specified
# as pairs of (fieldName, direction) where direction is a string
# "ASC" or "DESC".
sub new # ($class, $fieldName => $direction...)
{
	my $class = shift;
	my @args = @_; # save a copy

	# build a descriptive sortName
	my $sortName = 'SimpleOrder ';
	while ($#_ >= 0) {
		my $fld = shift;
		my $dir = shift;
		$sortName .= quotemeta($fld) . ' ' . quotemeta($dir) . ', ';
	}

	$self = Triceps::IndexType->newPerlSorted(
		$sortName, '&Triceps::SimpleOrderedIndex::init(@_)', undef, @args
	);
	bless $self, $class;
	return $self;
}

# The initialization function that actually parses the args.
sub init # ($tabt, $idxt, $rowt, @args)
{
	my ($tabt, $idxt, $rowt, @args) = @_;
	my %def = $rowt->getdef(); # the field definition
	my $errors; # collect as many errors as possible
	my $compare = ""; # the generated comparison function
	my $connector = "return"; # what goes between the comparison operators

	while ($#args >= 0) {
		my $f = shift @args;
		my $dir = uc(shift @args);

		my ($left, $right); # order the operands depending on sorting direction
		if ($dir eq "ASC") {
			$left = 0; $right = 1;
		} elsif ($dir eq "DESC") {
			$left = 1; $right = 0;
		} else {
			$errors .= "unknown direction '$dir' for field '$f', use 'ASC' or 'DESC'\n";
			# keep going, may find more errors
		}
	
		my $type = $def{$f};
		if (!defined $type) {
			$errors .= "no field '$f' in the row type\n";
			next;
		}

		my $cmp = "<=>"; # the comparison operator
		if ($type eq "string"
		|| $type =~ /^uint8.*/) {
			$cmp = "cmp"; # string version
		} elsif($type =~ /\]$/) {
			$errors .= "can not order by the field '$f', it has an array type '$type', not supported yet\n";
			next;
		}

		my $getter = "->get(\"" . quotemeta($f) . "\")";

		$compare .= "  $connector \$_[$left]$getter $cmp \$_[$right]$getter\n";

		$connector = "||";
	}

	$compare .= "  ;\n";

	if (defined $errors) {
		# help with diagnostics, append the row type to the error listing
		$errors .= "the row type is:\n";
		$errors .= $rowt->print();
	} else {
		# set the comparison as source code
		#print STDERR "DEBUG Triceps::SimpleOrderedIndex::init: comparison function:\n$compare\n";
		$idxt->setComparator($compare);
	}
	return $errors;
}
</pre>

		<para>
		The class constructor simply builds the sort name from the arguments
		and offloads the rest of logic to the init function. It can't really do
		much more: when the index type object is constructed, it doesn't know
		yet, where it will be used and what row type it will get. It tries to
		enquote nicely the weird characters in the arguments when they go into
		the sort name. Not that much use is coming from it at the moment: the
		&Cpp; code that prints the table type information doesn't do the same, so
		there still is a chance of misbalanced quotes in the result. But
		perhaps the &Cpp; code will be fixed at some point too.
		</para>

		<para>
		The init function is called at the table type initialization time
		with all the needed information.
		It goes through all the arguments, looks up the fields in the row type,
		and checks them for correctness. It tries to collect as much of the
		error information as possible. The returned error messages may contain
		multiple lines separated by <quote>\n</quote>, and the ordered index makes use of
		it. The error messages get propagated back to the table type level,
		nicely indented and returned from the table initialization. If the init
		function finds any errors, it appends the printout of the row type too,
		to make finding what went wrong easier. A result of a particularly bad
		call to a table type initialization may look like this:
		</para>

<!-- t/SimpleOrderedIndex.t errors -->
<pre>
index error:
  nested index 1 'sorted':
    unknown direction 'XASC' for field 'z', use 'ASC' or 'DESC'
    no field 'z' in the row type
    can not order by the field 'd', it has an array type 'float64[]', not supported yet
    the row type is:
    row {
      uint8 a,
      uint8[] b,
      int64 c,
      float64[] d,
      string e,
    }
</pre>

		<para>
		Also as the init goes through the arguments, it constructs the text of
		the compare function in the variable <pre>$compare</pre>. Here the use of
		<pre>quotemeta()</pre> for the user-supplied strings is important to avoid the
		syntax errors in the generated code. If no errors are found in the
		arguments, the compare function gets compiled with <pre>eval</pre>. There
		should not be any errors, but it's always better to check. Finally the
		compiled compare function is set in the sorted index with
		</para>

<pre>
$idxt->setComparator($cmpfunc)
</pre>

		<para>
		If you uncomment the debugging printout line (and run <quote><pre>make</pre></quote>, and maybe
		<quote><pre>make install</pre></quote> afterwards), you can see the auto-generated code printed
		on stderr when you use the simple ordered index. It will look somewhat
		like this:
		</para>

<pre>
sub {
	return $_[0]-&gt;get("a") cmp $_[1]-&gt;get("a")
	|| $_[1]-&gt;get("c") &lt;=&gt; $_[0]-&gt;get("c")
	|| $_[0]-&gt;get("b") cmp $_[1]-&gt;get("b")
	;
}
</pre>

		<para>
		That's it! An entirely new piece of functionality added in a smallish Perl
		snippet. This is your typical Triceps template: collect the arguments,
		use them to build Perl code, and compile it. Of course, if you don't
		want to deal with the code generation and compilation, you can just
		call your class methods and whatnot to interpret the arguments. But if
		the code will be reused, the compilation is more efficient.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_indextree">
		<title>The index tree</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>leaf</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>non-leaf</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The index types in a table type can form a pretty much arbitrary tree.
		Following the common tree terminology, the index types that have no
		other index types nested in them, are called the <i>leaf</i> index
		types. Since there seems to be no good one-word naming for the index
		types that have more index types nested in them ("inner"? "nested" is
		too confusing), I simply call them <i>non-leaf</i>.
		</para>

		<para>
		At the moment the Hashed, Sorted and Ordered index types can be used
		only in both leaf and non-leaf positions. The FIFO index types must
		always be in the leaf position, they don't allow the further nesting.
		</para>

		<para>
		Now is the time to look deeper into what is going on inside a table.
		Note that I've been very carefully talking about <quote>index types</quote> and not
		<quote>indexes</quote>. In this section the difference matters. The index types are in
		the table type, the indexes are in the table. One index type may
		generate multiple indexes.
		</para>

		<para>
		This will become clearer after you see the illustrations. 
		First, the legend in the
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_legend" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<figure id="fig_idx_legend" >
			<title>Drawings legend.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-000-legend.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandle</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The nodes belonging to the table type are shown in red, the nodes
		belonging to the table are shown in blue, and the contents of the
		RowHandle is shown separately in yellow. The lines on the drawings
		represent not exactly pointers as such but more of the logical
		connections that may be more complicated than the simple pointers.
		</para>

		<para>
		The lines in the RowHandle don't mean anything at all, they just show
		that the parts go together. In reality a RowHandle is a chunk of
		memory, with various elements placed in that memory. As far as indexes
		are concerned, the RowHandle contains an iterator for every index where
		it belongs. This lets it know its position in the table, to iterate
		along every index, and, most importantly, to be removed quickly from
		every index. A RowHandle belongs to one index of each index type, and
		contains the matching number of iterators in it.
		</para>

		<para>
		The table type is shown as a normal flat tree. But the table itself is
		more complex and becomes 3-dimensional. Its <quote>view from above</quote> matches
		the table type's tree but the data grows <quote>up</quote> in the third dimension.
		</para>

		<para>
		Let's start with the simplest case: a table type with only one index
		type. Whether the index type is hash or FIFO, doesn't matter here.
		</para>

<pre>
TableType
+-IndexType "A"
</pre>

		<para>
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_one" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;
		shows the table structure.
		</para>

		<figure id="fig_idx_one" >
			<title>One index type.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-010-one.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>root</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The table here always contains exactly one index, matching the one
		defined index type, and the root index. The root index is very dumb,
		its only purpose is to tie together the multiple top-level indexes into
		a tree.
		</para>

		<para>
		The only index of type A provides an ordering of the records, and this
		ordering is used for the iteration on the table.
		</para>

		<para>
		For the next example let's look at the straight nesting in
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_nested" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

<pre>
TableType
+-IndexType "A"
  +-IndexType "B"
</pre>

		<figure id="fig_idx_nested" >
			<title>Straight nesting.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-020-nested.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<para>
		The stack of row references is shown visually divided to match the
		indexing, but in reality there is no special division. This was done
		purely to make the picture easier to read.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>group</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		There is still only one index of type A. And this is always the case
		with the top-level indexes, there is only one of them. This index
		divides the rows into 3 <i>groups</i>. Just like the rows in a leaf
		index, the groups in a non-leaf index are ordered in some 
		index-specific way.
		</para>

		<para>
		Each group then has its own second-level index of type B. Which then
		defines an order for the rows in it. To reiterate: the index of type A
		splits the rows by groups, then the group's index of type B defines the
		order of the rows in the group.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>iteration</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		So what happens when we iterate through the table and ask for the next
		row handle? The current row handle contains the iterators in the
		indexes of types A and B. The easy thing is to advance the iterator of
		type B. Yeah, but in <i>which</i> index? The 
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_nested" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;
		shows three indexes of
		type B, let's call them B1, B2 and B3. The iterator of type B in the
		row handle tells the relative position in the index, but it doesn't
		tell, which index it is. We need to step back and look at the index
		type A. It's the top-level index type, so there is always only one
		index for it. Then we take the iterator of type A and find this row's
		group in the index A. The group contains the index of type B, say B1.
		We can then take this index B1, take the iterator of type B from the
		row handle, and advance this iterator in this index. If the advance
		succeeded, then great, we've got the next row handle. But if the
		current row was the last row in B1, we need to step back to the index A
		again, advance the current row handle's iterator of type A there, find
		its index B2, and pick the first row handle of B2.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>default</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		This process is what happens when we use <pre>$rh->nextIdx($itB)</pre>. 
		The iteration goes by the leaf
		index type B, however it relies on all the index types in the path from
		the table type to B. If we do <pre>$rh->next()</pre>, the result is the same
		because the <i>first leaf</i> index type is used as the default index type for
		the iteration.
		</para>

		<para>
		If we do <pre>$rh->next($itA)</pre>, the semantics is still the same:
		return the next row handle (not the next group). There is no way to get
		to the row handle without going all the way through a leaf index. So
		when a non-leaf index type is used for the iteration, it gets
		implicitly extended to its first nested leaf index type. 
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>insert</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		What would happen if a new row gets inserted, and the index type A
		determines that it does not belong to any of the existing groups? A new
		group will be created and inserted in the appropriate position in A's
		order. This group will have a new index of type B created, and the new
		row inserted in that index.
		</para>

		<para>
		What would happen if both rows in B1 are removed? B1 will become empty
		and will be collapsed. The index A will delete the B1's group and B1
		itself, and will remain with only two groups. The effect propagates
		upwards: if all the rows are removed, the last index of type B will
		collapse, then the index A will become empty and also collapse and be
		deleted. The only thing left will be the root index that stays in the
		existence no matter what.
		</para>

		<para>
		When a table is first created, it has only the root index. The rest of
		the indexes pop into the existence as the rows get inserted. If you
		wonder, yes, this does apply to a table type with only one index type
		as well. Just this point has not been brought up until now.
		</para>

		<para>
		Among all this froth of creation and collapse the iterators stay
		stable. Once a row is inserted, the indexes leading to it are not going
		anywhere (at least until that row gets removed). But since other rows
		and groups may be inserted around it, the notion of what row is next,
		will change over time.
		</para>

		<para>
		Let's go through how the other index-related operations work.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>iteration</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The iteration through the whole table starts with <pre>begin()</pre> or
		<pre>beginIdx()</pre>, the first being a form of the second that always uses the
		first leaf index type. <pre>beginIdx()</pre> is fairly straightforward: it just
		follows the path from the root to the leaf, picking the first position
		in each index along the way, until it hits the RowHandle, as is shown in
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_nested_begin" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;.
		That found RowHandle becomes its result. If the table is
		empty, it returns the NULL row handle.
		</para>

		<figure id="fig_idx_nested_begin" >
			<title><pre>begin()</pre>, <pre>beginIdx($itA)</pre> and <pre>beginIdx($itB)</pre> work the same for this table.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-021-nested-begin.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>find</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The next pair is <pre>find()</pre> and <pre>findIdx()</pre> (and
		<pre>findBy()</pre> and <pre>findIdxBy()</pre> are wrappers around those). 
		As usual, <pre>find()</pre> is the same
		thing as <pre>findIdx()</pre> on the table's first leaf index type. It also
		follows the path from the root to the target index type. On each step
		it tries to find a matching position in the current index. If the
		position could not be found, the search fails and a NULL row handle is
		returned. If found, it is used to progress to the next index.
		</para>

		<para>
		As has been mentioned in
		<xref linkend="sc_table_RowHandle" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;, 
		the search always works internally on a
		RowHandle argument. If a plain Row is used as an argument, a new
		temporary RowHandle will be created for it, searched, and then freed
		after the search. This works well for two reasons. First, the indexes
		already have the functions for comparing two row handles to build their
		ordering. The same functions are reused for the search. Second, the row
		handles contain not only the index iterators but also the cached
		information from the rows, to make the comparisons faster. The exact
		kind of cached information varies by the index type. The FIFO,
		Sorted and Ordered indexes
		use none. The Hashed indexes calculate a hash of the key field values,
		that will be used as a quick differentiator for the search. This
		information gets created when the row handle gets created. Whether the
		row handle is then used to insert into the table or to search in it,
		the hash is then used in the same way, to speed up the comparisons.
		</para>

		<para>
		In <pre>findIdx()</pre>, the non-leaf index type arguments behave differently
		than the leaf ones: up to and including the index of the target type,
		the search works as usual. But then at the next level the logic
		switches to the same as in <pre>beginIdx()</pre>, going for the first row handle
		of the first leaf sub-index. This lets you find the first row handle of
		the matching group under the target index type.
		</para>

		<para>
		If you use <pre>$table->findIdx($itA, $rh)</pre>, on 
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_nested_findidx" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;
		it will go through
		the root index to the index A. There it will try to find the matching
		position. If none is found, the search ends and returns a NULL row
		handle. If the position is found, the search progresses towards the
		first leaf sub-index type. Which is the index type B, and which
		conveniently sits in this case right under A. The position in the index
		A determines, which index of type B will be used for the next step.
		Suppose it's the second position, so the second index of type B is
		used. Since we're now past the target index A, the logic used is the
		same as for <pre>beginIdx()</pre>, and the first position in B2 is picked. Which
		then leads to the first row handle of the second sub-stack of handles.
		</para>

		<figure id="fig_idx_nested_findidx" >
			<title><pre>findIdx($itA, $rh)</pre> goes through A and then switches to the <pre>beginIdx()</pre> logic.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-022-nested-findidx.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<para>
		The method <pre>firstOfGroupIdx()</pre> allows to navigate within a group, to jump
		from some row somewhere in the group to the first one, and then from
		there iterate through the group. The example in
		<xref linkend="sc_table_fifo" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		made use of it.
		</para>

		<para>
		The 
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_nested_firstOfGroupIdx" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;
		shows an example of <pre>$table->firstOfGroupIdx($itB, $rh)</pre>,
		where <pre>$rh</pre> is pointing to the third record in B2. What it needs to do is
		go back to B2, and then execute the <pre>begin()</pre> logic from there on.
		However, remember, the row handle does not have a pointer to the
		indexes in the path, it only has the iterators. So, to find B2, the
		method does not really back up from the original row. It has to start
		all the way back from the root and follow the path to B2 using the iterators in
		<pre>$rh</pre>. Since it uses the ready iterators, this works fast and requires no
		row comparisons. But logically it's equivalent to backing up by one level,
		and I'll continue calling it that for simpicity.
		Once B2 (an index of type B) is reached, the <pre>begin()</pre> logic goes for
		the first row in there.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>firstOfGroupIdx()</pre> works on both leaf and non-leaf index type arguments
		in the same way: it backs up from the reference row to the index of
		that type and executes the <pre>begin()</pre> logic from there. Obviously, if you
		use it on a non-leaf index type, the <pre>begin()</pre>-like part will follow its
		first leaf index type.
		</para>

		<figure id="fig_idx_nested_firstOfGroupIdx" >
			<title><pre>firstOfGroupIdx($itB, $rh)</pre>.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-023-nested-firstOfGroupIdx.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<para>
		The method <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> jumps to the first row of the next group,
		according to the argument index type. To do that, it has to retrace one
		level higher than <pre>firstOfGroupIdx()</pre>. 
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_nested_nextGroupIdx" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;
		shows that
		<pre>$table->nextGroupIdx($itB, $rh)</pre> that starts from the same row handle
		as in
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_nested_firstOfGroupIdx" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;,
		has to logically back up to the index A, go to the next
		iterator there, and then follow to the first row of B3.
		</para>

		<figure id="fig_idx_nested_nextGroupIdx" >
			<title><pre>nextGroupIdx($itB, $rh)</pre>.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-024-nested-nextGroupIdx.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<para>
		As before, in reality there is no backing up, just the path is retraced
		from the root using the iterators in the row handle. Once the parent of
		index type B is reached (which is the index of type A), the path
		follows not the iterator from the row handle but the next one (yes,
		copied from the row handle, increased, followed). This gives the index
		of type B that contains the next group. And from there the same
		<pre>begin()</pre>-like logic finds its first row.
		</para>

		<para>
		Same as <pre>firstOfGroupIdx()</pre>, <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> may be used on both the leaf
		and non-leaf indexes, with the same logic.
		</para>

		<para>
		It's kind of annoying that <pre>firstOfGroupIdx()</pre> and <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> take
		the index type inside the group while <pre>findIdx()</pre> uses takes the parent
		index type to act on the same group. But as you can see, each of them
		follows its own internal logic, and I'm not sure if they can be
		reconciled to be more consistent.
		</para>

		<para>
		At the moment the only navigation is forward. There is no matching
		<pre>last()</pre>, <pre>prev()</pre> or <pre>lastGroupIdx()</pre> or <pre>prevGroupIdx()</pre>. They are in the
		plan, but so far they are the victims of corner-cutting. Though there is a version of
		<pre>last()</pre> in the AggregatorContext, since it happens to be particularly important
		for the aggregation.
		</para>

		<para>
		Continuing our excursion into the index nesting topologies, the next
		example is of two parallel leaf index types:
		</para>

<pre>
TableType
+-IndexType A
+-IndexType B
</pre>

		<para>
		The resulting internal arrangement is shown in
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_2pri" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<figure id="fig_idx_2pri" >
			<title>Two top-level index types.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-030-2pri.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<para>
		Each index type produces exactly one index under the root (since the
		top-level index types always produce one index). Both indexes contain
		the same number of rows, and exactly the same rows. When a row is added
		to the table, it's added to all the leaf index types (one actual index
		of each type). When a row is deleted from the table, it's deleted from
		all the leaf index types. So the total is always the same. However the
		order of rows in the indexes may differ. The drawing shows the row
		references stacked in the same order as the index A because the index A
		is of the first leaf index type, and as such is the default one for the
		iteration.
		</para>

		<para>
		The row handle contains the iterators for both paths, A and B. It's
		pretty normal to find a row through one index type and then iterate
		from there using the other index type.
		</para>

		<para>
		The next example in
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_prisec" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;
		has a <quote>primary</quote> index with a unique key and a 
		<quote>secondary</quote> index that groups the records:
		</para>

<pre>
TableType
+-IndexType A
+-IndexType B
  +-IndexType C
</pre>

		<figure id="fig_idx_prisec" >
			<title>A <quote>primary</quote> and <quote>secondary</quote> index type.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-040-prisec.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<para>
		The index type A still produces one index and references all the rows
		directly. The index of type B produces the groups, with each group
		getting an index of type C. The total set of rows referrable through A
		and through B is still the same but through B they are split into
		multiple groups.
		</para>

		<para>
		And 
		<xref linkend="fig_idx_nestfork" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;
		shows two leaf index types nested under one non-leaf.
		</para>

<pre>
TableType
+-IndexType A
  +-IndexType B
  +-IndexType C
</pre>

		<figure id="fig_idx_nestfork" >
			<title>Two index types nested under one.</title>
			<xi:include href="file:///FIGS/idx-050-nestfork.xml"/> 
		</figure>

		<para>
		As usual, there is only one index of type A, and it splits the rows
		into groups. The new item in this picture is that each group has two
		indexes in it: one of type B and one of type C. Both indexes in the
		group contain the same rows. They don't decide, which rows they get.
		The index A decides, which rows go into which group. Then if the group
		1 contains two rows, indexes B1 and C1, would both contain two rows
		each, the exact same set. The stack of row references has been visually
		split by groups to make this point more clear.
		</para>

		<para>
		This happens to be a pretty useful arrangement: for example, B might be
		a hash index type, or a sorted index type, allowing to
		find the records by the key (and for the sorted index, to iterate in
		the order of keys), while C might be a FIFO index, keeping the
		insertion order, and maybe keeping the window size limited.
		</para>

		<para>
		That's pretty much it for the basic index topologies. Some much more
		complex index trees can be created, but they would be the combinations
		of the examples shown. Also, don't forget that every extra index type
		adds overhead in both memory and CPU time, so avoid adding indexes that
		are not needed.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>table</primary>
			<secondary>replacement</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		One more fine point has to do with the replacement policies. Consider
		that we have a table that contains the rows with a single field:
		</para>

<pre>
id int32
</pre>

		<para>
		And the table type has two indexes:
		</para>

<pre>
TableType
+-IndexType "A" HashIndex key=(id)
+-IndexType "B" FifoIndex limit=3
</pre>

		<para>
		And we send there the rowops:
		</para>

<pre>
INSERT id=1
INSERT id=2
INSERT id=3
INSERT id=2
</pre>

		<para>
		The last rowop that inserts the row with id=2 for the second time
		triggers the replacement policy in both index
		types. In the index A it is a duplicate key and will cause the removal
		of the previous row with id=2. In the index B it overflows the limit
		and pushes out the oldest row, the one with id=1. If both records get
		deleted, the resulting table contents will be 2 rows (shown in FIFO
		order):
		</para>

<pre>
id=3
id=2
</pre>

		<para>
		Which is probably not the best outcome. It might be tolerable with a
		FIFO index and a hashed index but gets even more annoying if there are
		two FIFO index types in the table: one top-level limiting the total
		number of rows, another one nested under a hashed index, limiting the
		number of rows per group, and they start conflicting this way with each
		other.
		</para>

		<para>
		The Triceps FIFO index is actually smart enough to avoid such problems: it
		looks at what the preceding indexes have decided to remove, checks if
		any of these rows belong to its group, and adjusts its calculation
		accordingly. In this example the index B will find out that the row
		with id=2 is already displaced by the index A. That leaves only 2 rows
		in the index B, so adding a new one will need no displacement. The
		resulting table contents will be
		</para>

<pre>
id=1
id=3
id=2
</pre>

		<para>
		However here the order of index types is important. If the table were
		to be defined as
		</para>

<pre>
TableType
+-IndexType "B" FifoIndex limit=3
+-IndexType "A" HashIndex key=(id)
</pre>

		<para>
		then the replacement policy of the index type B would run first, find
		that nothing has been displaced yet, and displace the row id=1. After
		that the replacement policy of the index type A will run, and being a
		hashed index, it doesn't have a choice, it has to replace the row id=2.
		And both rows end up displaced.
		</para>

		<para>
		If the situations with automatic replacement of rows by the keyed
		indexes may arise, always make sure to put the keyed leaf index types
		before the FIFO leaf index types. However if you always diligently send
		a DELETE before the INSERT of the new version of the recond, then this
		problem won't occur and the order of index types will not matter.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_idx_intro">
		<title>Table and index type introspection</title>

		<para>
		A lot of information about a table type and the index types in it 
		can be read back from them.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $tabType->isInitialized();
$result = $idxType->isInitialized();
</pre>

		<para>
		return whether a table or index type has been initialized.
		The index type gets initialized when the table type where it belongs
		gets initialized.  After a table or index type has been initialized, it can not
		be changed any more, and any methods that change it will return an
		error.
		When an index type becomes initialized, it becomes tied to a particular
		table type. This table type can be read with:
		</para>

<pre>
$tabType = $idxType->getTabtype();
$tabType = $idxType->getTabtypeSafe();
</pre>

		<para>
		The difference between these methods is what happens if the index type
		was not set into a table type yet. <pre>getTabtype()</pre> would
		confess while <pre>getTabtypeSafe()</pre> would return an <pre>undef</pre>.
		Which method to use, depends on the circumstances: if this situation
		is valid and you're ready to check for it and handle it, use
		<pre>getTabtypeSafe()</pre>, otherwise use <pre>getTabtype()</pre>.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>copy</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Even though an initialized index type can't be tied to another table,
		when you add it to another table or index type, a deep copy with
		all its sub-indexes will be made automatically, and that copy will 
		be uninitialized. So it will be able to get initialized and tied to 
		the new table. However if you want to add more sub-indexes to it,
		do a manual copy first:
		</para>

<pre>
$idxTypeCopy = $idxType->copy();
</pre>

		<para>
		The information about the nested indexes can be found with:
		</para>

<pre>
$itSub = $tabType->findSubIndex("indexName");
$itSub = $tabType->findSubIndexSafe("indexName");
@itSubs = $tabType->getSubIndexes();

$itSub = $idxType->findSubIndex("indexName");
$itSub = $idxType->findSubIndexSafe("indexName");
@itSubs = $idxType->getSubIndexes();
</pre>

		<para>
		The <pre>findSubIndex()</pre> has been already shown in
		<xref linkend="sc_table_secondary" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		It allows to find the index types on the next level of nesting, starting
		down from the table, and going recursively into the sub-indexes.
		The <pre>Safe</pre> versions return <pre>undef</pre> if the index is not
		found, instead of confessing.
		<pre>getSubIndexes()</pre> returns the information about the index types of the
		next level at once, as the name => value pairs. The result array
		can be placed into a hash but that would lose the order
		of the sub-indexes, and the order is important for the logic.
		</para>

		<para>
		This finds the index types step by step. An easier way to find an index
		type in a table type by the <quote>path of the index</quote> is with
		</para>

<pre>
$idxType = $tabType->findIndexPath(\@idxNames);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>path</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The arguments in the array form a path of names in the index type tree. If the path
		is not found, the function would confess.
		An empty path is also illegal and would cause the same result.
		Yes, the argument is not an array but a reference to array. This
		array is used essentially as a path object. For example the
		index from the
		<xref linkend="sc_table_secondary" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		could be found as:
		</para>

<pre>
$itLast2 = $ttWindow->findIndexPath([ "bySymbol", "last2" ]);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>key</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The key (the set of fields that uniquely identify the rows) of the index type 
		can be found with
		</para>

<pre>
@keys = $it->getKey();
</pre>

		<para>
		It can be used on any kind of index types but actually returns the data
		only for the Hashed index types.  On the other index types it returns an 
		empty array, though a better support will be available for the 
		Sorted and Ordered indexes in the future.
		</para>

		<para>
		A fairly common need is to find an index by its name path, and also all the
		key fields that are used by all the indexes in this path. It's used
		for such purposes as joins, and it allows to treat a nested index
		pretty much as a composition of all the indexes in its path.
		The method
		</para>

<pre>
($idxType, @keys) = $tabType->findIndexKeyPath(\@path);
</pre>

		<para>
		solves this problem and
		finds by path an index type that allows the direct look-up by key
		fields. It requires that every index type in the path returns a
		non-empty array of fields in <pre>getKey()</pre>. In practice it means that every
		index in the path must be a Hashed index. Otherwise the method
		confesses. When the Sorted and maybe other index types will support
		<pre>getKey()</pre>, they will be usable with this method too.
		</para>

		<para>
		Besides checking that each index type in the path works by keys, this
		method builds and returns the list of all the key fields required for a
		look-up in this index. Note that <pre>@keys</pre> is an actual array and not a
		reference to array. The return protocol of this method is a little
		weird: it returns an array of values, with the first value being the
		reference to the index type, and the rest of them the names of the key
		fields. If the table type were defined as
		</para>

<pre>
$tt = Triceps::TableType->new($rt)
	->addSubIndex("byCcy1",
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "ccy1" ])
		->addSubIndex("byCcy12",
			Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "ccy2" ])
		)
	)
	->addSubIndex("byCcy2",
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "ccy2" ])
		->addSubIndex("grouping", Triceps::IndexType->newFifo())
	)
;
</pre>

		<para>
		then <pre>$tt->findIndexKeyPath([ "byCcy1", "byCcy12" ])</pre> would return 
		<pre>($ixtref, "ccy1", "ccy2")</pre>, 
		where <pre>$ixtref</pre> is the reference to the index type. When
		assigned to <pre>($ixt, @keys)</pre>, <pre>$ixtref</pre> would go into <pre>$ixt</pre>, and 
		<pre>("ccy1", "ccy2")</pre> would go into <pre>@keys</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The key field names in the result go in the order they occurred in the
		definition, from the outermost to the innermost index. The key fields
		must not duplicate.  It's possible to define the index types where the
		key fields duplicate in the path, say:
		</para>

<pre>
$tt = Triceps::TableType->new($rt)
	->addSubIndex("byCcy1",
		Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "ccy1" ])
		->addSubIndex("byCcy12",
			Triceps::IndexType->newHashed(key => [ "ccy2", "ccy1" ])
		)
	)
;
</pre>

		<para>
		And they would even work fine, with just a little extra overhead from
		duplication. But <pre>findIndexKeyPath()</pre> will refuse such indexes and
		confess.
		</para>

		<para>
		Yet another way to find an index is by the keys. Think of an SQL
		query: having a WHERE condition, you would want to find if there
		is an index on the fields in the condition, allowing to find the
		records quickly. Triceps is not quite up to this level of automatic
		query planning yet but it does some for the joins.
		If you know, by which fields you want to join,
		it's nice to find the correct index automatically. 
		The finding of an index by key is done with the method:
		</para>

<pre>
@idxPath = $tableType->findIndexPathForKeys(@keyFields);
</pre>

		<para>
		It returns the array that represents the path to an index type that
		matches these key fields. And then having the path you can find the
		index type as such. The index type and all the types in the path
		still have to be of the Hashed variety. If the correct index cannot
		be found, an empty array is returned. If you specify the fields that
		aren't present in the row type in the first place, this is simply
		treated the same as being unable to find an index for these fields.
		If more that one index would match, the first one found in the direct
		order of the index tree walk is returned.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>type id</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The kind of the index type is also known as the type id. It can be found
		for an index type with
		</para>

<pre>
$id = $idxType->getIndexId();
</pre>

		<para>
		It's an integer constant, matching one of the values:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>constants</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<pre>&Triceps::IT_HASHED</pre>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<pre>&Triceps::IT_FIFO</pre>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<pre>&Triceps::IT_SORTED</pre>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		There is no different id for the ordered index, because it's
		built on top of the sorted index, and would return <pre>&Triceps::IT_SORTED</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The conversion between the strings and constants for index type ids is done with
		</para>

<pre>
$intId = &Triceps::stringIndexId($stringId);
$stringId = &Triceps::indexIdString($intId);
</pre>

		<para>
		If an invalid value is supplied, the conversion functions will return <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is also a way to find the first index type of a particular kind.
		It's called somewhat confusingly
		</para>

<pre>
$itSub = $idxType->findSubIndexById($indexTypeId);
</pre>

		<para>
		where <pre>$indexTypeId</pre> is one of either of Triceps constants or the
		matching strings <pre>"IT_HASHED"</pre>, <pre>"IT_FIFO"</pre>, <pre>"IT_SORTED"</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		Technically, there is also IT_ROOT but it's of little use for this
		situation since it's the root of the index type tree hidden inside the
		table type, and would never be a sub-index type. It's possible to
		iterate through all the possible index type ids as
		</para>

<pre>
for ($i = 0; $i < &Triceps::IT_LAST; $i++) { ... }
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>index</primary>
			<secondary>default</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The first leaf sub-index type, that is the default for iteration,
		can be found explicitly as
		</para>

<pre>
$itSub = $tabType->getFirstLeaf();
$itSub = $idxType->getFirstLeaf();
</pre>

		<para>
		If an index is already a leaf, <pre>getFirstLeaf()</pre> on it
		will return itself.
		The <quote>leaf-ness</quote> of an index type can be found with:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $idxType->isLeaf();
</pre>

		<para>
		The usual reference comparison methods are:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $tabType1->same($tabType2);
$result = $tabType1->equals($tabType2);
$result = $tabType1->match($tabType2); 

$result = $idxType1->same($idxType2);
$result = $idxType1->equals($idxType2);
$result = $idxType1->match($idxType2); 
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>TableType</primary>
			<secondary>equals</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Two table types are considered equal when they have the equal row types,
		and exactly the same set of index types, with the same names.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>TableType</primary>
			<secondary>match</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Two table types are considered matching when they have the matching row types,
		and matching set of index types, although the names of the index types
		may be different.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>IndexType</primary>
			<secondary>equals</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Two index types are considered equal when they are of the same kind
		(type id), their type-specific parameters are equal, they have the
		same number of sub-indexes, with the same names, and equal pair-wise.
		They must also have the equal aggregators, which will be described in
		detail in the 
		<xref linkend="ch_aggregation" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>IndexType</primary>
			<secondary>match</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Two index types are considered matching when they are of the same kind,
		have matching type-specific parameters, they have the same number of
		sub-indexes, which are matching pair-wise, and the matching aggregators.
		The names of the sub-indexes may differ.
		As far as the type-specific parameters are concerned, it depends on the
		kind of the index type. The FIFO type considers any parameters matching.
		For a Hashed index the key fields must be the same. For a Sorted index
		the sorted condition must also be the same, and by extension this
		means the same condition for the Ordered index.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_copy_tray">
		<title>The copy tray</title>

		<para>
		The table methods <pre>insert()</pre>, <pre>remove()</pre> and <pre>deleteRow()</pre> have an extra
		optional argument: the copy tray.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>copy tray</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>tray</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		If used, it will put a copy of all the rowops produced during the
		operation (including the output of the aggregators, which will be
		described in 
		<xref linkend="ch_aggregation" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		) into that tray. The
		idea here is to use it in cases if you don't want to connect the output
		labels of the table directly, but instead collect and process the rows
		from the tray manually afterwards. Like this:
		</para>

<pre>
$ctr = $unit->makeTray();
$table->insert($row, $ctr);
foreach my $rop ($ctr->toArray()) {
	...
}
</pre>

		<para>
		However in reality it didn't work out so well. The processing loop
		would have to have all the lengthy if-else sequences to branch first by
		the label (if there are any aggregators) and then by opcode. It looks
		too difficult. Well, it could work in the simple situations but not
		more than that.
		</para>

		<para>
		In the future this feature will likely be deprecated unless it proves
		itself useful, and I already have a better idea. Because of this, I see
		no point in going into the more extended examples.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_table_wrapup">
		<title>Table wrap-up</title>

		<para>
		Not all of the table's features have been shown yet. The table
		class is the cornerstone of Triceps, and everything is connected
		to it.  The aggregators
		work with the tables and are a whole separate big subject with their
		own 
		<xref linkend="ch_aggregation" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		The features that take advantage of the streaming functions are
		described in 
		<xref linkend="sc_strf_tables" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		There also are many more options and small methods that
		haven't been touched upon yet. They are enumerated in the reference
		chapter, please refer there.
		</para>
	</sect1>

</chapter>
