<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_code">
		<title>Code helpers reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>code</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>compile</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		As described in
		<xref linkend="sc_code" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;,
		many Triceps method accept the code references or source code snippets
		as arguments. The user-defined templates are encouraged to do the same.
		These code snippets can be compiled with the helper function:
		</para>

<pre>
$code = Triceps::Code::compile($code_ref_or_source);
$code = Triceps::Code::compile($code_ref_or_source, $description);
</pre>

		<para>
		It takes either a code reference or a source code string as an argument
		and returns the reference to the compiled code. If the argument was a
		code reference, it just passes through unchanged. If it was a source
		code snippet, it gets compiled (the text
		gets the <pre>sub { ... }</pre> wrapper added around it implicitly).
		</para>

		<para>
		If the argument was an <pre>undef</pre>, it also passes through unchanged. This is
		convenient in case if the code is optional. But if it isn't then the
		caller should check for <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		If the compilation fails, the method confesses, and includes the error
		and the source code into the message, in the same way as the XS methods
		do.
		</para>

		<para>
		The optional second argument can be used to provide information
		about the meaning of the code for the error messages. If it's undefined
		then the default is <quote>Code snippet</quote>.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>numalign</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The error messages reported by <pre>compile()</pre> include the
		printout of the code with the line numbering. This printout
		can also be produced directly with the method <pre>Triceps::Code::numalign()</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
$formatted_text = Triceps::Code::numalign($source_text, $indent);
$formatted_text = Triceps::Code::numalign($source_text, $indent, $tabrepl);
</pre>

		<para>
		<pre>$source_text</pre> is the source code to be formatted. <pre>$indent</pre> is the indentation
		to be prepended to each line of the formatted code (before the line numbers,
		and since the line numbers are printed as 4 characters, this might add
		a bit extra visual indentation). The tab characters are replaced with
		two spaces by default, or <pre>$tabrepl</pre> can be used to specify any other replacement
		for them.
		</para>

		<para>
		The code is also beautified a bit to make it more readable. The following
		is done to it:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			The empty lines at the front will be removed. <pre>numalign()</pre> is smart
			enough to take the removed lines into account and show the numbers
			as they were in the original code snippet.
			You can also get the number of the removed
			lines afterwards, from the global variable
			<pre>$Triceps::Code::align_removed_lines</pre>.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			The <quote>\n</quote> at the end of the snippet will be chomped. But only one, the
			rest of the empty lines at the end will be left alone.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			Then the <quote>baseline</quote> indenting of the code will be determined by
			looking at the first three and last two lines. The shortest
			non-empty indenting will be taken as the baseline. If some lines
			examined start with spaces and some start with tabs, the lines
			starting with tabs will be preferred as the baseline indenting.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			The baseline indenting will be removed from the front of all lines.
			If some lines in the middle of the code have a shorter indenting,
			they will be left unchanged.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			The tabs will be replaced by either the third argument or two spaces.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			The line numbers will be prepended to the lines.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			The indenting from the second argument of the function will be
			prepended to the lines.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		Here is an example of use:
		</para>

<pre>
confess "$myname: error in compilation of the generated function:\n  $@function text:\n"
. Triceps::Code::numalign($gencode, "  ") . "\n";
</pre>

		<para>
		It can produce an error message like this (with a deliberately introduced syntax error):
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::Fields::makeTranslation: error in compilation of the generated function:
  syntax error at (eval 27) line 13, near "})
"
function text:
     2 sub { # (@rows)
     3   use strict;
     4   use Carp;
     5   confess "template internal error in Triceps::Fields::makeTranslation: result translation expected 1 row args, received " . ($#_+1)
     6     unless ($#_ == 0);
     7   # $result_rt comes at compile time from Triceps::Fields::makeTranslation
     8   return $result_rt->makeRowArray(
     9     $_[0]->get("one"),
    10     $_[0]->get("two"),
    11   );
    12 })
 at /home/babkin/w/triceps/trunk/perl/Triceps/blib/lib/Triceps/Fields.pm line 219
    Triceps::Fields::makeTranslation('rowTypes', 'ARRAY(0x2943cb0)', 'filterPairs', 'ARRAY(0x2943b30)', '_simulateCodeError', 1) called at t/Fields.t line 205
    eval {...} called at t/Fields.t line 204
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>alignsrc</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The method <pre>Triceps::Code::alignsrc()</pre> is just like <pre>numalign()</pre>,
		except that it doesn't prepend the line numbers but only improves the
		alignment of the code lines:
		</para>

<pre>
$formatted_text = Triceps::Code::alignsrc($source_text, $indent);
$formatted_text = Triceps::Code::alignsrc($source_text, $indent, $tabrepl);
</pre>

	</sect1>
