<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_unit">
		<title>Unit and FrameMark reference</title>

		<para>
		The Unit class represents an execution unit and
		keeps the state of the Triceps execution for one
		thread. Each thread running Triceps must have its own execution unit.
		</para>

		<para>
		It's perfectly possible to have multiple execution units in the
		same thread. This is typically done when there is some permanent
		model plus some small intermittent sub-models created on demand to handle
		the user requests. These small sub-models would be created in the
		separate units, to be destroyed when their work is done.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>unit</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A unit is created as:
		</para>

<pre>
$myUnit = Triceps::Unit->new($name);
</pre>

		<para>
		The <pre>$name</pre> argument will be used in the error messages, making easier
		to find, which exact part of the model is having troubles.
		By convention the name should be the same as the name of the unit variable
		(<quote>myUnit</quote> in this case). When a Unit is created as a part of
		Triead (a Triceps thread object), it will be given the same name as
		the Triead.
		</para>

		<para>
		The name can be read back:
		</para>

<pre>
$name = $myUnit->getName();
</pre>

		<para>
		Also, as usual, the variable <pre>$myUnit</pre> here contains a reference to the
		actual unit object, and two references can be compared for whether they
		refer to the same object:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $unit1->same($unit2);
</pre>

		<para>
		A unit also keeps an empty row type (one with no fields), primarily for the
		creation of the clearing labels (discussed in
		<xref linkend="sc_memory_labels" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		and
		<xref linkend="sc_Label_construction" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;),
		but you can use it for any other purposes
		too. You can get it with the method:
		</para>

<pre>
$rt = $unit->getEmptyRowType();
</pre>

		<para>
		Each unit has its own instance of an empty row type that can be used
		to create the objects that don't process any data (for which
		just the fact of a rowop passing through is important). The
		creation of an empty row type in each unit instead of having
		a single global one is purely for the conveniece of memory management
		in the threads, they are all equivalent. You could also create
		your own empty row type.
		</para>

		<para>
		The rowops are enqueued with the calls:
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->call(@rowops_or_trays);
$unit->fork(@rowops_or_trays);
$unit->schedule(@rowops_or_trays); 
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>enqueue</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		<quote>Enqueued</quote> is an ugly word but since I've already used the
		word <quote>schedule</quote> for a specific purpose, I needed another word to name
		all these operations together. Hence <quote>enqueue</quote>.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>Call()</pre> executes the rowop immediately, <pre>fork()</pre> puts it onto the current
		stack frame to be executed after the current label returns, and <pre>schedule()</pre> 
		puts the rowop onto the outermost frame, to be executed when the model
		becomes idle.
		</para>

		<para>
		Calling these functions with multiple arguments produces the same
		result as doing multiple calls with one argument at a time. The
		rowop and tray arguments may be mixed arbitrarily.
		</para>

		<para>
		Also there is a call that selects the enqueueing mode by argument:
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->enqueque($mode, @rowops_or_trays);
</pre>

		<para>
		The calling rules are exactly the same for the other enqueueing methods,
		may have multiple rowops or trays as arguments, no need to check the result.
		The <pre>$mode</pre> argument is one of:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>constants</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<pre>&Triceps::EM_CALL</pre> or <pre>"EM_CALL"</pre>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<pre>&Triceps::EM_FORK</pre> or <pre>"EM_FORK"</pre>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<pre>&Triceps::EM_SCHEDULE</pre> or <pre>"EM_SCHEDULE"</pre>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<pre>&Triceps::EM_IGNORE</pre> or <pre>"EM_IGNORE"</pre>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		The <pre>EM_IGNORE</pre> is a <quote>no-op</quote> among the enqueueing
		methods. It means that the rowop will be simply ignored and not executed at all. 
		It is very rarely used in practice.
		</para>

		<para>
		As usual, there are calls to convert between the integer constant and
		string representations:
		</para>

<pre>
$string = &Triceps::emString($value);
$value = &Triceps::stringEm($string);
$string = &Triceps::emStringSafe($value);
$value = &Triceps::stringEmSafe($string);
</pre>

		<para>
		And as usual, if the value can not be translated, the functions
		with <pre>Safe</pre> return <pre>undef</pre>, the functions without
		it confess.
		</para>

		<para>
		The frame marks for looping are created as their own class:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>frame mark</primary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
$mark = Triceps::FrameMark->new($name);
</pre>

		<para>
		The name can be obtained back from the mark:
		</para>

<pre>
$name = $mark->getName();
</pre>

		<para>
		Other than that, the frame marks are completely opaque, and can be used
		only for the loop scheduling. Not even the <pre>same()</pre> method is supported
		for them at the moment, though it probably will be in the future. The
		mark gets set and used as:
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->setMark($mark);
$unit->loopAt($mark, @rowops_or_trays);
</pre>

		<para>
		<pre>setMark</pre> must be called in the first label of the loop,
		normally before doing anything else. <pre>loopAt()</pre> is called
		in any label inside the loop that wants to send a rowop back to the
		start of the loop.
		The rowop or tray arguments of the <pre>loopAt()</pre> are the same as for the
		other enqueueing functions.
		</para>

		<para>
		The examples of the <pre>loopAt()</pre> operation are presented in
		<xref linkend="sc_sched_topo_loops" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;,
		and the details of its internal works are in 
		<xref linkend="sc_sched_loop" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		There also are the convenience methods that create the rowops
		from the field values and immediately enqueue them:
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->makeHashCall($label, $opcode, 
	$fieldName => $fieldValue, ...);
$unit->makeArrayCall($label, $opcode, @fieldValues);

$unit->makeHashSchedule($label, $opcode, 
	$fieldName => $fieldValue, ...);
$unit->makeArraySchedule($label, $opcode, @fieldValues);

$unit->makeHashLoopAt($mark, $label, $opcode, 
	$fieldName => $fieldValue, ...);
$unit->makeArrayLoopAt($mark, $label, $opcode, @fieldValues);
</pre>

		<para>
		These are essentially the shorter ways to make the rowops and enqueue
		them without the three-deep calls. Only the methods for the most 
		frequently used enqueueing modes are provided, not for all of them.
		</para>

		<para>
		The Unit also serves as a factory for creation of the objects
		associated with it:
		</para>

<pre>
$label = $unit->makeDummyLabel($rowType, "name");

$label = $unit->makeLabel($rowType, "name", $clearSub, $execSub, @args);

$label = $unit->makeClearingLabel("name", @args);

$table = $unit->makeTable($tableType, "name");

$tray = $unit->makeTray(@rowops); 
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>memory management</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>DummyLabel</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>ClearingLabel</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A special thing about the labels is that when a unit creates
		a label, it keeps a reference to it, for clearing. A label keeps a pointer
		back to the unit but not a reference (if you call <pre>getUnit()</pre>
		on a label, the returned value becomes a reference). For a table
		or a tray, the unit doesn't keep a reference to them. Instead,
		they keep a reference to the unit. 
		The references are at the &Cpp; level, not Perl level.
		</para>

		<para>
		With the tables, the references can get
		pretty involved: A table has labels associated with it.
		When a table is created, it also creates these labels.
		The unit keeps references of these labels. The table also
		keeps references of these labels. The table keeps a reference
		of the unit. The labels 
		have pointers to the unit and the
		table but not references, to avoid the reference cycles.
		</para>

		<para>
		See more on the memory management and label clearing in the
		<xref linkend="ch_memory" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		The convenience methods to create the whole front part of the 
		topological loop are:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>scheduling</primary>
			<secondary>loop</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>loop</primary>
			<secondary>scheduling</secondary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
($label, $frameMark) = $unit->makeLoopHead(
	$rowType, $name, $clearSub, $execSub, @args);

($label, $frameMark) = $unit->makeLoopAround(
	$name, $labelFirst);
</pre>

		<para>
		You don't have to use them, you can create the loops manually. These
		methods merely make it more convenient. Remember also that a procedural
		loop is usually much easier to write, debug, and read later than a
		topological one.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>makeLoopHead()</pre> creates the front part of the loop that starts
		with a Perl label. It gets the arguments for that label and
		creates it among the other things. <pre>makeLoopAround()</pre> creates
		the front part of the loop around an existing label that
		will be the first one executed in the loop. <pre>makeLoopHead()</pre> 
		is really redundant and can be replaced with a combination
		of <pre>makeLabel()</pre> and <pre>makeLoopAround()</pre>,
		but as-is it's slightly more efficient.
		</para>

		<para>
		They both return the same results, a pair:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		The label that will be the real start of the loop, where you
		send a rowop to both initiate the loop and to do the next iteration of the
		loop with <pre>loopAt</pre>.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		The frame mark that you use in <pre>loopAt()</pre>. You don't need to
		set the frame mark, it will be set for you in the wrapper logic.
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		The name argument will become the name of the created label. The FrameMark
		object also has a name, useful for diagnostics, that gets created by adding
		a suffix to the argument: <quote><i>name</i>.mark</quote>.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>makeLoopAround()</pre> takes the row type for its wrpper label
		from <pre>$labelFirst</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The unit can be checked for the emptiness of its queues:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $unit->empty();
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether all the frames are empty.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $unit->isFrameEmpty();
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>TrieadOwner</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Check whether the current inner frame is empty.  This
		method is useful if you run multiple units in the same thread, with
		some potentially complicated cross-unit scheduling. It's what
		<pre>TrieadOwner::nextXtray()</pre> does with a multi-unit Triead, repeatedly calling
		<pre>drainFrame()</pre> for all the units that are found not empty. In this
		situation the simple <pre>empty()</pre> cannot be used because the current inner
		frame might not be the outer frame, and draining the inner frame can be
		repeated forever while the outer frame will still contain rowops. The
		more precise check of <pre>isFrameEmpty()</pre> prevents the possibility of such
		endless loops.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $unit->isInOuterFrame();
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the unit's current inner frame is the same as its outer
		frame, which means that the unit is not in the middle of a call.
		</para>

		<para>
		The functions for execution from the queues are:
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->callNext();
$unit->drainFrame();
</pre>

		<para>
		<pre>callNext()</pre> takes one label from the top (innermost) stack frame queue and calls it.
		If the inner frame happens to be empty, it does nothing. 
		<pre>drainFrame()</pre> calls the rowops from the top stack frame until it becomes
		empty. This includes any rowops that may be created and enqueued as
		part of the execution of the previous rowops. But it doesn't pop the
		frame from the stack.  And of course the method
		<pre>call()</pre> causes the argument rowops to be executed immediately, without
		even being technically enqueued.
		</para>

		<para>
		The recursive calls may be enabled per-unit with the methods:
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->setMaxStackDepth($n);
$unit->setMaxRecursionDepth($n);
</pre>

		<para>
		<pre>setMaxStackDepth()</pre> sets the limit on the total depth of the
		unit's call stack. That's the maximal length of the call chain, whether
		it goes straight or in loops.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>setMaxRecursionDepth()</pre> sets the limit on the 
		number of times each particular label may appear on
		the call stack. So if you have a recursive code fragment 
		(a simple-minded loop or a recursive streaming function), this
		is the limit on its recursive reentrances.
		</para>

		<para>
		You can change them at any time, even when the unit is running (but
		they will be enforced only on the next attempt to execute a rowop).
		Both these limits accept the 0 and negative values to mean <quote>unlimited</quote>.
		The default is: unlimited stack depth, recursion
		depth of 1.
		</para>

		<para>
		You can read the current limits with:
		</para>

<pre>
$n = $unit->maxStackDepth();
$n = $unit->maxRecursionDepth();
</pre>

		<para>
		Also the current depth of the call stack (the number of the
		stack frames on the queue) can be found with:
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $unit->getStackDepth();
</pre>

		<para>
		It isn't of any use for the model logic as such but comes handy
		for debugging, to check in the loops that you haven't accidentally
		created a stack growing with iterations. When the unit is not
		running, the stack depth is 1, since the outermost frame always
		stays on the stack. When a rowop is being executed, the stack
		depth is at least 2.
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->clearLabels();
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>UnitClearingTrigger</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Clear all the labels in the unit, then drop the references from unit to them.
		Normally should be called only when the unit is about to be destroyed,
		and is called automatically when the unit gets destroyed. However
		in case of cyclic references to the unit, it may need to be called
		manually or through a UnitClearingTrigger object to break these
		cycles. For more information, see
		<xref linkend="sc_ref_cycles" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		In case if any errors are found during the clearing of the labels
		(such as a bug in the user code in the label clearing routine),
		they get printed to stderr. The reason for that is that the
		clearing is normally called from the object destructors, and
		there just isn't any proper way to report an error from a destructor.
		The only thing that can be done is printing them.
		</para>

<pre>
$trigger = $unit->makeClearingTrigger();
</pre>

		<para>
		Create a unit clearing trigger object. When this object gets destroyed
		(at exiting the block, or when its encompassing object gets destroyed)
		it will cause the clearing of the unit.
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->setTracer($tracer); 
$oldTracer = $unit->getTracer();
</pre>

		<para>
		Set and read back a tracer object that will be called before and after
		each rowop executes in the unit. An <pre>undef</pre> means <quote>no tracer</quote>. 
		See more information in
		<xref linkend="sc_sched_tracing" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

<pre>
$unit->callBound($rowop_or_tray, $fnreturn => $fnbinding, ...);
$unit->callBound([@rowops], $fnreturn => $fnbinding, ...);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>streaming function</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		An encapsulation of a streaming function call.
		The first argument is a rowop or a tray or a reference to an array of rowops 
		(but the trays are not allowed in the array). The rest are the pairs
		of FnReturns and FnBindings. The bindings are pushed onto the FnReturns,
		then the rowops are called, then the bindings are popped. It replaces
		a whole block that would contain an AutoFnBind (described in
		<xref linkend="sc_ref_autofnbind" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;)
		and the call:
		</para>

<pre>
{
	my $ab = Triceps::AutoFnBind->new(
		$fnreturn => $fnbinding, ...
	);
	$unit->call($rowop_or_tray);
}
</pre>

		<para>
		Only <pre>callBound()</pre> does its work in &Cpp;, so it's more efficient
		than a Perl block, and it's shorter to write too.
		</para>

	</sect1>
