<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_table_type"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>TableType reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>TableType</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		The TableType is the information about the structure of a Table.
		It can be used to create multiple Tables in the same mold.
		</para>

<pre>
$tt = Triceps::TableType->new($rowType);
</pre>

		<para>
		Constructs the TableType. The TableType is anonymous, it has no string name.
		After that it can be configured by adding the index types. Eventually
		it has to be initialized and that freezes the table type and makes it
		immutable. All the steps up to and including the initialization must be
		done from a single thread, after initialization a table type may be
		shared between multiple threads.
		</para>

<pre>
$tt->addSubIndex("indexName", $indexType);
</pre>

		<para>
		Adds an index type, naming it within the scope of the table type.  
		The result is the same table type (unless it's an
		<pre>undef</pre> signifying an error), so the index type additions can be
		chained with each other and with the construction:
		</para>

<pre>
$tt = Triceps::TableType->new($rowType) 
	->addSubIndex("indexName1", $indexType1) 
	->addSubIndex("indexName2", $indexType2)
;
</pre>

		<para>
		The table type initialization freezes not only the table type
		itself but also all the index types in it. Also, the index types
		become permanently tied to this one table type.  That would make things
		difficult if the same index type is added to two table types. To avoid
		these issues, <pre>addSubIndex()</pre> adds not the actual argument index type but
		first creates a fresh uninitialized deep copy of it, and then adds it.
		</para>

<pre>
$tt->initialize();
</pre>

		<para>
		Initializes the table type.
		The index types check most of their arguments at the initialization
		time, so that's where most of the errors will be reported. Calling
		<pre>initialize()</pre> repeatedly will have no effect and just return the same
		result again and again. 
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $tt->isInitialized();
</pre>

		<para>
		Checks whether the table type has been initialized.
		</para>

<pre>
$rowType = $tt->rowType();
$rowType = $tt->getRowType();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the row type. One method name is historic, the other has been added
		for consistency.
		</para>

<pre>
$indexType = $tt->findSubIndex("indexName");
$indexType = $tt->findSubIndexSafe("indexName");
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds an index type by name.
		This is symmetric with <pre>addSubIndex()</pre>, so it works only for the
		top-level index types. To get the nested ones, repeat the same call on
		the found index types or see the following methods.
		The <pre>Safe</pre> version returns <pre>undef</pre> if the index is not
		found, instead of confessing.
		</para>

<pre>
$indexType = $tt->findIndexPath( ["indexName", "nestedIndexName"] );
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds an index type by the path of names leading to it in the index type tree.
		If the path is not found, the function would confess.
		An empty path is also illegal and would cause the same result.
		The argument is not an array but a reference to array of names.
		</para>

<pre>
($indexType, @keys) = $tt->findIndexKeyPath( ["indexName", "nestedIndexName"] );
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds by path an index type that allows the direct look-up by key
		fields. It requires that every index type in the path returns a
		non-empty array of fields in <pre>getKey()</pre>. In practice it means that every
		index in the path must be a Hashed index. Otherwise the method
		confesses. When the Sorted and maybe other index types will support
		<pre>getKey()</pre>, they will be usable with this method too.
		The argument is not an array but a reference to array of names.
		</para>

		<para>
		Besides checking that each index type in the path works by keys, this
		method builds and returns the list of all the key fields required for a
		look-up in this index. Note that <pre>@keys</pre> is an actual array and not a
		reference to array. The return protocol of this method is a little
		weird: it returns an array of values, with the first value being the
		reference to the index type, and the rest of them the names of the key
		fields.
		</para>

<pre>
@idxPath = $tt->findIndexPathForKeys(@keyFields);
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds an index path that matches the set of key fields.
		It returns the array that represents the path.
		And then having the path you can find the
		index type as such. The index type and all the types in the path
		have to be of the Hashed variety (returning their set of keys
		with the method <pre>getKey()</pre>). If the correct index cannot
		be found, an empty array is returned. If you specify the fields that
		aren't present in the row type in the first place, this is simply
		treated the same as being unable to find an index for these fields.
		If more that one index would match, the first one found in the direct
		order of the index tree walk is returned.
		</para>

<pre>
$indexType = $tt-findSubIndexById($indexTypeId);
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds the first top-level index type of a particular kind. The <pre>$indexTypeId</pre>
		is one of the <pre>IT_*</pre> constants in integer or string form.
		</para>

<pre>
$indexType = $tt->getFirstLeaf();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the first leaf index type (the one used for the default
		look-ups and iteration on the tables of this type).
		</para>

<pre>
@indexTypes = $tt->getSubIndexes();
%indexTypes = $tt->getSubIndexes();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns all the top-level index types.  The resulting array contains
		the pairs of names and index types. If the order is not important but
		you want to perform the look-ups by name, the result can be stored
		directly into a hash. However if you plan to use the data to add index
		types to another table type, don't use the hash because the order of
		indexes is important and the hash loses it.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $tt1->same($tt2);
$result = $tt1->equals($tt2);
$result = $tt1->match($tt2); 
</pre>

		<para>
		The usual reference comparison methods.
		</para>

		<para>
		Two table types are considered equal when they have the equal row types,
		and exactly the same set of index types, with the same names.
		</para>

		<para>
		Two table types are considered matching when they have the matching row types,
		and matching set of index types, although the names of the index types
		may be different.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $tt->print();
</pre>

		<para>
		Presents the content of a table type as a human-readable description.
		Accepts the usual <pre>print()</pre> arguments.
		</para>

<pre>
$newtt = $tt->copy();
</pre>
		<para>
		Copy the table type, along with copying all the index types in
		it, since each table type must have its own instances of the index
		types. The copied table type is always uninitialized and thus can
		be further extended by defining more indexes and aggregators.
		</para>

		<para>
		In case if the table type collected errors, the errors aren't copied,
		and in general you should not copy such a table type. The errors
		will be detected again when you try to initialize the copy.
		</para>

<pre>
$newtt = $tt->copyFundamental();
$newtt = $tt->copyFundamental(@idx_type_paths);
$newtt = $tt->copyFundamental("NO_FIRST_LEAF", @idx_type_paths);
</pre>

		<para>
		Copy only the fundamental data organization of the table type:
		the row type and the primary index (the whole path to the
		first leaf index type), and leave alone the rest. All the aggregators
		on all the indexes, even on the primary one, are not included in the
		copy. This is a convenient way to create another table, usually
		in a different thread, that would add its own secondary indexes
		and aggregators. See
		<xref linkend="sc_mt_objects" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		for more detail.
		</para>

		<para>
		The optional index type paths can be used to include the secondary
		indexes into the copy. Each path is a reference to an array of index names,
		such as <pre>[ "byDate", "byAddress", "fifo" ]</pre>. The path must
		lead all the way to a leaf index. A special path element <pre>"+"</pre>
		can be used last with the meaning <quote>the first leaf index from this point</quote>.
		Multiple paths may overlap, their overlapping parts will be copied only once.
		A special string <pre>"NO_FIRST_LEAF"</pre> used as the first argument
		excludes the first leaf index
		from the copy, then only the explicitly specified index paths will be copied.
		</para>
	</sect1>
