<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_index_type"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>IndexType reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>IndexType</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		The IndexType is a part of TableType and defines the structuring
		of rows in the table. It provides the order of rows and optionally
		a way to find them quickly by the key. The configuration of the
		index type defines the parameters for each index instance, i.e.
		each row group in an index of this type, not for the whole table.
		The difference between indexes and index types is explained in the
		<xref linkend="sc_table_indextree" xrefstyle="select: label nopage"/>&xrsp;.
		The index types are connected in a table type to form a tree.
		</para>

		<para>
		The index types in Triceps are available in the following kinds:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Hashed</term>
			<listitem>
			Provides quick random access based on the key formed from the
			fields of the row in the table. May be leaf or non-leaf. The order
			of the rows in the index will be repeatable between the runs of the
			same program on the same machine architecture, but not easily
			predictable. Internally the rows are stored in a tree but the
			comparisons of the rows are accelerated by pre-calculating a hash
			value from the key fields and keeping it in the row handle.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>FIFO</term>
			<listitem>
			Keeps the rows in the order they were received. There is no
			efficient way to find a particular row in this index, the search in
			it works by going through all the rows sequentially and comparing
			the rows for exact equality. It provides the expiration policies
			based on the row count. It may only be a leaf.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>PerlSorted</term>
			<listitem>
			Provides random access based on the key field comparison, expressed
			as a Perl function. This results in a predictable order of rows but
			the execution of the Perl code makes it slower than the Hashed
			index. May be leaf or non-leaf. Often also called simply <quote>Sorted</quote>.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>SimpleOrdered</term>
			<listitem>
			A Perl template on top of the PerlSorted index,
			that allows to specify the keys in a more convenient way. 
			Often also called simply <quote>Ordered</quote>.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

<pre>
$it = Triceps::IndexType->newHashed($optionName => $optionValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a Hashed index type.  The only available and mandatory option is:
		</para>
		
		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>key => [ @fields ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The argument is a reference to an array of strings
			that specify the names of the key fields (<pre>key => ["f1", "f2"]</pre>).
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>


<pre>
$it = Triceps::IndexType->newFifo($optionName => $optionValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a FIFO index type.  The options are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>limit => $limit</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Sets the limit value for the replacement policy. Once the number of
			rows attempts to grow beyond this value, the older records get
			removed. Setting it to 0 disables the replacement policy.
			Don't try to set it to negative values, they will be
			treated as unsigned, and thus become some very large positive
			ones. Optional. Default: 0.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>jumping => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Determines the variation of the replacement policy in effect. If
			set to 0, implements the sliding window policy, removing
			the older rows one by one. If non-0, implements the jumping window
			policy, removing all the older rows when a new row causes the limit
			overflow. Optional. Default: 0.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>reverse => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Defines the iteration order. If non-0, the iteration on this index
			goes in the reverse order. However the expiration policy still
			works in the direct order! Optional. Default: 0.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

<pre>
$it = Triceps::IndexType->newPerlSorted($sortName, $initFunc,
	$compareFunc, @args...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a PerlSorted index type. The arguments are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>$sortName</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			a string describing the sorting order, used in <pre>print()</pre>
			and error messages. 
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>$initFunc</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			a function reference that can be used
			to generate the comparison function dynamically at the table type
			initialization time (or use <pre>undef</pre> with a fixed comparison
			function). 
			A source code string may be used instead of the function reference, see
			<xref linkend="sc_code" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;. 
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>$compareFunc</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			a function reference to the fixed comparison function, if preferred
			(or use <pre>undef</pre> if it will be generated dynamically by the init
			function). 
			A source code string may be used instead of the function reference, see
			<xref linkend="sc_code" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;. 
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>@args</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			optional extra arguments for the
			initialization and/or comparison function.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>
		See the details in
		<xref linkend="sc_table_sorted" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		The handling of the fatal errors (as in <pre>die()</pre>) in the initialization 
		and especially comparison functions is an interesting subject.
		The errors propagate properly through the table,
		and the table operations confess with the Perl handler's error message.
		But since an error in the comparison function means that things are going
		very, very wrong, after that the table becomes inoperative and will die
		on all the subsequent operations as well. You need to be very careful
		in writing these functions.
		</para>

<pre>
$it = Triceps::SimpleOrderedIndex->new($fieldName => $order, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a SimpleOrdered index type.
		The arguments are the key fields. <pre>$order</pre> is one of
		the constants <pre>"ASC"</pre> for ascending or <pre>"DESC"</pre> for
		descending.
		</para>

<pre>
$indexType2->addSubIndex("indexName", $indexType1);
</pre>

		<para>
		Attaches the nested <pre>$indexType1</pre> under <pre>$indexType2</pre>.
		More exactly, attaches an uninitialized deep copy of <pre>$indexType1</pre>,
		the same as when adding an index type under a table type.
		It returns the reference to the same <pre>$indexType2</pre>, so these calls can be
		conveniently chained, to add multiple sub-indexes under it. If
		<pre>$indexType2</pre> can not be non-leaf, the call will fail.
		</para>

<pre>
$itSub = $it->findSubIndex("indexName");
$itSub = $it->findSubIndexSafe("indexName");
$itSub = $it->findSubIndexById($indexTypeId);

@itSubs = $it->getSubIndexes();
$itSub = $it->getFirstLeaf();
</pre>

		<para>
		Perform the same actions as the same-named methods in the TableType.
		If the index type is already a leaf, <pre>getFirstLeaf()</pre> will return itself.
		</para>

<pre>
$it->setAggregator($aggType);
</pre>

		<para>
		Sets an aggregator type on an index type.  It will create aggregators that run on the
		rows stored withing the indexes of this type.
		The value returned is the same index type reference <pre>$it</pre>, allowing the
		chaining calls, along with the <pre>addSubIndex()</pre>. Only one aggregator type
		is allowed on an index type. Calling <pre>setAggregator()</pre> repeatedly will
		replace the aggregator type. 
		</para>

<pre>
$aggType = $it->getAggregator();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the aggregator type set on this index type.
		The returned value may be <pre>undef</pre> if no
		aggregator type has been set.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $it->isInitialized();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns, whether this type has been initialized.
		The index type gets initialized when the table type where it belongs
		gets initialized. After an index type has been initialized, it can not
		be changed any more, and any methods that change it will return an
		error.
		</para>

<pre>
$itCopy = $it->copy();
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a copy of the index type.
		The copy reverts to the un-initialized state. It's always a deep copy,
		with all the nested index and aggregator types copied. All of these
		copies are un-initialized.
		</para>

<pre>
$itCopy = $it->flatCopy();
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a copy of the index type object 
		itself, without any connected object hierarchies such as the nested
		indexes or aggregators.
		</para>

<pre>
$tabType = $it->getTabtype();
$tabType = $it->getTabtypeSafe();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the table type, to which this index type is tied.
		When an index type becomes initialized, it becomes tied to a particular table type.
		If the index type is not initialized yet,
		<pre>getTabtype()</pre> would confess while <pre>getTabtypeSafe()</pre> would 
		return an <pre>undef</pre>.
		Which method to use, depends on the circumstances: if this situation
		is valid and you're ready to check for it and handle it, use
		<pre>getTabtypeSafe()</pre>, otherwise use <pre>getTabtype()</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $it1->same($it2);
$result = $it1->equals($it2); 
$result = $it1->match($it2);
$result = $it->print();
</pre>

		<para>
		The usual sameness comparisons and print methods.
		</para>

		<para>
		Two index types are considered equal when they are of the same kind
		(type id), their type-specific parameters are equal, they have the
		same number of sub-indexes, with the same names, and equal pair-wise.
		They must also have the equal aggregators.
		</para>

		<para>
		Two index types are considered matching when they are of the same kind,
		have matching type-specific parameters, they have the same number of
		sub-indexes, which are matching pair-wise, and the matching aggregators.
		The names of the sub-indexes may differ.
		As far as the type-specific parameters are concerned, it depends on the
		kind of the index type. The FIFO type considers any parameters matching.
		For a Hashed index the key fields must be the same. For a Sorted index
		the sorted condition must also be the same, and by extension this
		means the same condition for the Ordered index.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $it->isLeaf();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns 1 if the index type is a leaf, 0 if not.
		</para>

<pre>
@keys = $it->getKey();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the array of field names forming the key of this index. 
		Currently works only on the Hashed index types. On the other index
		types it returns an empty array, though probably a better support would
		be available for the PerlSorted/SimpleOrdered indexes in the future.
		</para>

<pre>
$it->setComparator($compareFunc, @args...);
</pre>

		<para>
		A special method that works only on the PerlSorted index types.
		Sets an auto-generated comparator function and its optional
		arguments from an initializer function at the table initialization
		time. On success it returns 1. For all other index types this method
		confesses.
		A source code string may be used instead of the function reference, see
		<xref linkend="sc_code" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;. 
		</para>

	</sect1>
