<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_agg_type"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>AggregatorType reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>AggregatorType</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		The aggregator type describes an aggregation. It gets connected
		to an index type which defines the grouping for the aggregator.
		Whenever the aggregation is performed, the code from the
		aggregator type receives the group context as its argument.
		</para>

<pre>
$at = Triceps::AggregatorType->new($resultRowType, "aggName", $initFunc,
	$handlerFunc, @args);
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates an aggregator type.
		The rows created by the aggregator will be of <pre>$resultRowType</pre>. The
		aggregator name is used to name the aggregator result label in the
		table, <quote>tableName.aggName</quote>. It is also used to get the reference of
		that label from the table.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>$initFunc</pre> and <pre>$handlerFunc</pre> provide either references or
		source code strings for the init and handler functions (as usual, if the format
		is the source code, the <pre>sub { ... }</pre> wrapper will be added implicitly, see
		<xref linkend="sc_code" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;). 
		The init function is
		called when the row group (contained in an index of the type, on which
		this aggregator type is set) is created. It initializes the group's
		aggregation state. The handler function gets called on the
		changes to the group.  See the details in
		<xref linkend="sc_aggregation_optimized" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;,
		<xref linkend="sc_aggregation_additive" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		and
		<xref linkend="sc_aggregation_args" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		The optional <pre>@args</pre> are passed to both the init and handler functions.
		</para>

		<para>
		If any fatal errors (as in <pre>die()</pre>) occur in the 
		aggregator functions, they propagate properly through the table,
		and the table operations confess with the Perl handler's error message.
		But since an error in the aggregator function means that things are going
		very, very wrong, after that the table becomes inoperative and will die
		on all the subsequent operations as well. You need to be very careful
		in writing these functions.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $at1->same($at2);
$result = $at1->equals($at2);
$result = $at1->match($at2);
$result = $at->print(); 
$atCopy = $at->copy();
</pre>

		<para>
		The methods for comparison, printing and copying work similarly to the index types.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>IndexType</primary>
			<secondary>equals</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The equal aggregator types have the equal result row types, same names,
		same initialization and handler function references, same arguments.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>IndexType</primary>
			<secondary>match</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The matching aggregator types may differ in the aggregator name and in
		the field names of the result row type. However the function references
		and their arguments must still be the same.
		</para>

<pre>
$rt = $at->getRowType(); 
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the result row type.
		</para>
	</sect1>

