<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_table"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>Table reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Table</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		The Table provides the structured data storage in Triceps.
		</para>

<pre>
$t = $unit->makeTable($tabType, "tableName");
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a table of a given table type.
		The table type must be initialized before it can be used to create
		tables. The tables are strictly single-threaded.
		</para>

		<para>
		The table name is used for the error messages and as a base for the names of
		the table labels.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>sticky error</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A word needs to be said about the handling of the fatal errors (as in <pre>die()</pre>)
		in the custom Perl functions provided in the user elements of the table,
		such as the PerlSortedIndex and aggregators.
		The errors propagate properly through the table,
		and the table operations confess with the Perl handler's error message.
		But since an error in these functions means that things are going
		very, very wrong, after that the table becomes inoperative and will die
		on all the subsequent operations as well.
		This is known as a <quote>sticky error</quote>.  You need to be very careful
		in writing these functions.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $t1->same($t2);
</pre>

		<para>
		The usual comparison for sameness. (There is no comparison for equality
		and mathicng, use the table type for that; nor printing, use the table
		name and/or table type for that).
		</para>

<pre>
$lb = $t->getInputLabel();
$lb = $t->getPreLabel();
$lb = $t->getOutputLabel();
$lb = $t->getDumpLabel();
$lb = $t->getAggregatorLabel("aggName");
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the labels that are creates as a part of the table. With an invalid
		name for an argument, <pre>getAggregatorLabel()</pre> returns an <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
$tt = $t->getType();
$u = $t->getUnit();
$rt = $t->getRowType();
$name = $t->getName();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the information about the table configuration.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $t->size();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the number of rows in the table.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $t->makeRowHandle($row);
$rh = $t->makeNullRowHandle();
</pre>

		<para>
		Create the row handles.  The row must be of a matching type, and it will
		be cast to the table's row type: when read back from the row handle,
		the row will have the table's row type as its type. The casting does
		not involve any copying or modification of the row, it's still shared
		by reference counting. And the original row as it was would still
		return the same type. Basically, the row itself is untyped, its type
		is determined by the container where it is stored. The requirement
		for the matching types ensures that when a row is passed between the
		containers, they have a compatible notion of the row type.
		</para>

		<para>
		A NULL row
		handle is a handle without a row in it. It can not be placed into a
		table but this kind of row handle gets returned by table operations to
		indicate things not found. In case if you want to fool some of your
		code by slipping it a NULL handle, <pre>makeNullRowHandle()</pre> provides a way
		to do it. The row handles belong to a particular table and can not be
		mixed between them, even if the tables are of the same type.
		</para>

		<para>
		The table operations can be done by either sending the rowops to the
		table's input label or by calling the operations directly.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $t->insert($row_or_rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		Inserts a row or row handle into the table. The row handle must
		not be in the table before the call, it may be either freshly created
		or previously removed from the table. If a row is used as an argument,
		it is internally wrapped in a fresh row handle, and then that row
		handle inserted. An insert may trigger the replacement policy in the
		table's indexes and have some rows removed before the insert is done.
		Returns 1 on success, 0 if the insert can not be done (the row handle is already in
		the table or NULL).
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $t->remove($rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		Removes a row handle from the table. The row handle must be previously
		inserted in the table, and either found in it or a reference to it
		remembered from before. An attempt to remove a newly created row handle
		will have no effect. 
		The result is 1 on success (even if the row handle was not in the table).
		</para>

<pre>
$result= $t->deleteRow($row);
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds the handle of the matching row by the table's first leaf index
		and removes it. Returns 1 on success, 0 if the row was not found.
		Unlike <pre>insert()</pre>, the
		deletion methods for a row handle and a row are named differently to
		emphasize their difference. The method <pre>remove()</pre> must get a reference to
		the exactly same row handle that was previously inserted. The method
		<pre>deleteRow()</pre> does not have to get the same row as was previously
		inserted, instead it will find a row handle of the row that has the
		same key as the argument, according to the first leaf index.
		<pre>deleteRow()</pre> never deletes more than one row. If the index contains
		multiple matching rows (for example, if the first leaf is a FIFO
		index), only one of them will be removed, usually the first one (the
		exact choice depends on what row gets found by the index).
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $t->find($row_or_rh);
$rh = $t->findIdx($idxType, $row_or_rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		Find the row handle the table by indexes.  If the row is not found,
		return a NULL row handle. If the row is of an incorrect type or the
		index type is incorrect, confesses. The index type must be exactly
		the one belonging to the type of this table (not its copy nor the
		original from which it was copied into the table's type), so the
		only way to get it is to find it in the table's type after it
		has been constructed.
		The default <pre>find()</pre> works
		using the first leaf index type, i.e. the following two are equivalent:
		</para>

<pre>
$t->find($r);
$t->findIdx($t->getType()->getFirstLeaf(), $r);
</pre>

		<para>
		but the <pre>find()</pre> version is slightly more efficient because it handles
		the index types inside the &Cpp; code and does not create the Perl
		wrappers for them.
		</para>

		<para>
		The <pre>find()</pre> operation is also used internally by <pre>deleteRow()</pre> and to
		process the rowops received at the table's input label.
		</para>

		<para>
		If a row is used as an argument for <pre>find</pre>, a temporary row handle is
		internally created for it, and then the find is performed on it. Note
		that if you have a row handle that is already in the table, there is
		generally no use calling <pre>find</pre> on it, you will just get the same row
		handle back (well, except for the case of multi-valued indexes, then
		you will get back some matching row handle, usually the first one,
		which may be the same or not). 
		</para>

		<para>
		A <pre>findIdx()</pre> with a non-leaf index argument is a special case: it
		returns the first row handle of the group that has the key matching the
		argument. The order of <quote>first</quote> in this case is defined according to
		that index'es first leaf sub-index.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $t->findBy("fieldName" => $fieldValue, ...);
$rh = $t->findIdxBy($idxType, "fieldName" => $fieldValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Convenience methods that construct a row from the field arguments and then find it.
		They confess on incorrect arguments.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $t->begin();
$rh = $t->next($rh); 
$rh = $t->beginIdx($idxType);
$rh = $t->nextIdx($idxType, $rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		Iteration on the table. The methods <pre>next()</pre> and <pre>nextIdx()</pre> are equivalent
		to the same methods of the row handle.
		As usual, the versions without an explicit index type use the first
		leaf index type. The <pre>begin</pre> methods return the first row handle
		according to an index'es order, the <pre>next</pre> methods advance to the next
		row handle. When the end of the table is reached, these methods return
		a NULL row handle. The <pre>next</pre> methods also return a NULL row handle if their
		argument row handle is a NULL or not in the table. So, if you iterate
		and remove the row handles, make sure to advance the iterator first and
		only then remove the current row handle.
		</para>

		<para>
		If the index argument is non-leaf, it's equivalent to its first leaf. 
		</para>

<pre>
$endrh = $t->nextGroupIdx($subIdxType, $rh_in_group);
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds the first row handle of the next group, where <pre>$subIdxType</pre> is the
		first index inside the group (not its parent index!).  Confesses on errors.
		The result also works as the end marker handle of the current group. 
		</para>

		<para>
		To iterate through only a group, use <pre>findIdx()</pre> on the parent index type
		of the group to find the first row of the group. Then things become
		tricky: take the first index type one level below it to determine the
		iteration order (a group may have multiple indexes in it, defining
		different iteration orders, the first one will give the group's default
		order).  Use that index type with <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> to find the
		first row handle past the end of the group, and with the usual
		<pre>nextIdx()</pre> to advance the iterator. 
		However the end of the group will not be signaled by a NULL row handle. 
		It will be signaled by <pre>nextIdx()</pre> returning the same row
		handle as previously returned by <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre>
		(compare them with <pre>$endrh->same($itrh)</pre>).
		</para>

		<para>
		The value returned by <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> is actually the first row handle of the next group, so
		it can also be used to jump quickly to the next group, and essentially
		iterate by groups. After the last group, <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> will return a
		NULL row handle. Which is OK for iteration, because at the end of the
		last group <pre>nextIdx()</pre> will also return a NULL row handle.
		</para>

		<para>
		What if a group has a whole sub-tree of indexes in it, and you want to
		iterate it by the order of not the first sub-index? Still use <pre>findIdx()</pre>
		in the same way to find a row handle in the desired group. But then
		convert it to the first row handle in the desired order:
		</para>

<pre>
$beginrh = $t->firstOfGroupIdx($subIdxType, $rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		The <pre>$subIdxType</pre> is the same as used in <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre>.
		After that proceed as before: get the end marker with <pre>nextGroupIdx()</pre> on
		the same sub-index, and iterate with <pre>nextIdx()</pre> on it.
		</para>

		<para>
		This group iteration is somewhat messy and tricky, and maybe something
		better can be done with it in the future. If you look closely, you can
		also see that it doesn't allow to iterate the groups in every possible
		order. For example, if you have an index type hierarchy
		</para>

<pre>
A
+-B
| +-D
| | +-G
| | +-H 
| +-E 
+-C
</pre>

		<para>
		and you want to iterate on the group inside B, you can go in the order
		of D or G (which is the same as D, since G is the first leaf of D) or
		of E, but you can not go in the order of H. But for most of the
		practical purposes it should be good enough.
		</para>

<pre>
$size = $table->groupSizeIdx($idxType, $row_or_rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds the size of a group without iteration on it. <pre>$idxType</pre>
		is the parent index of the group (the same as would be used with
		<pre>findIdx()</pre>).  Naturally, it must be a non-leaf index. (Using
		a non-leaf index type is not an error but it always returns 0, because
		there are no groups under it).  Confesses on errors. The argument may
		be a row or row handle that identifies any row in the group.  If the
		argument is a row, it gets handled similarly to <pre>findIdx()</pre>: a
		temporary row handle gets created, used to find the result, and then
		destroyed.  If there is no such group in the table, the result will be
		0.  If the argument is a row handle, that handle may be in the table or
		not in the table, either will be handled transparently (though calling
		it for a row handle that is in the table is more efficient because the
		group would not need to be found first). 
		</para>

<pre>
$table->clear();
$table->clear($limit);
</pre>

		<para>
		Deletes the rows from the table.
		If <pre>$limit</pre> is absent or 0, the whole table gets cleared. If it's greater
		than 0, no more than this number of rows will be deleted. A negative
		limit is an error. The deletion happens in the usual order of the first
		leaf index, and the rowops are sent to the table's output label as
		usual. It's really the same thing as running a loop over all the row
		handles and removing them, only with a &Cpp; imnplementation it's more
		efficient than in Perl. There is no return value, the errors cause a
		confession.
		</para>

<pre>
$fret = $table->fnReturn();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns an FnReturn object connected to the output of this table.
		The FnReturn contains the labels <quote>pre</quote>, <quote>out</quote>, 
		<quote>dump</quote> (used with <pre>dumpAll</pre> methods) and the named labels for
		all aggregators.  The FnReturn object is created on the first call of
		this method and is kept in the table.  All the following calls return
		the same object. 
		This has some interesting consequences for the <quote>pre</quote>
		label: the rowop for the <quote>pre</quote> label doesn't get created at all if
		there is nothing chained from that label. But when the FnReturn gets
		created, one of its labels gets chained from the <quote>pre</quote> label. Which
		means that once you call <pre>$table->fnReturn()</pre> for the first time, you
		will see that table's <quote>pre</quote> label called in all the traces. It's not a
		huge extra overhead, but still something to keep in mind and not be
		surprised when calling <pre>fnReturn()</pre> changes all your traces.
		See more detail in
		<xref linkend="sc_strf_tables" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

<pre>
$table->dumpAll();
$table->dumpAll($opcode);
</pre>

		<para>
		Sends all the table's rows in their default order to the label <quote>dump</quote>.
		The opcode for the created rowops is OP_INSERT by default, or can be specified
		explicitly as an argument. The typical usage is to push a binding on the table's
		FnReturn to process these dumped rowops.
		</para>

<pre>
$table->dumpAllIdx($indexType);
$table->dumpAllIdx($indexType, $opcode);
</pre>

		<para>
		Similar to <pre>dumpAll()</pre>, only allows to send the rows in an order
		specified by another index type.
		As usual, the index type must belong to the exact type of this table.
		</para>
	</sect1>

