<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_rowhandle"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>RowHandle reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandle</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		A RowHandle is essentially the glue that keeps a row in the table. A
		row's handle keeps the position of the row in the table and allows to
		navigate from it in the direction of every index. It also keeps the
		helper information for the indexes. For example, the Hashed index
		calculates the has value for the row's fields once and remembers it in
		the handle. The table operates always on the handles, never directly on
		the rows. The table methods that accept rows as arguments, implicitly
		wrap them into handles before doing any operations.
		</para>

		<para>
		A row handle always belongs to a particular table, and can not be mixed
		between the tables, even if the tables are of the same type. Even
		before a row handle has been inserted into the table and after it has
		been removed, it still belongs to that table and can not be inserted
		into any other one.
		</para>

		<para>
		Just as the tables are single-threaded, the row handles are
		single-threaded.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $table->makeRowHandle($row);
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates the RowHandle.  The newly created row handle is not inserted in
		the table. The type of the argument row must be matching the table's
		row type.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $rh->isInTable();
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds out, whether the row handle is inserted in the table. If the
		row handle is NULL, it will quietly return 0.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $rh->isNull();
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds out if the RowHandle is NULL.  A RowHandle may be NULL
		to indicate the special conditions. It pretty much means that there is only the Perl wrapper
		layer of RowHandle but no actual RowHandle under it. This happens to be
		much more convenient than dealing with undefined values at Perl level.
		The NULL row handles are returned by the certain table calls to
		indicate that the requested data was not found in the table.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $table->makeNullRowHandle();
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a NULL RowHandle.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $rh1->same($rh2);
</pre>

		<para>
		The usual comparison for sameness.
		</para>

<pre>
$row = $rh->getRow();
$row = $rh->getRowSafe();
</pre>

		<para>
		Extracts the row from the handle. The row will have the type of the
		table's row type. A row can not be extracted from a NULL row handle,
		in this situation <pre>getRow()</pre> will confess and <pre>getRowSafe()</pre>
		will return <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $rh->next();
$rh = $rh->nextIdx($idxType);
$rh = $rh->firstOfGroupIdx($idxType);
$rh = $rh->nextGroupIdx($idxType);
</pre>

		<para>
		These methods work exactly the same as the same-named table methods.
		They are essentially syntactic sugar over
		the table methods.
		</para>

	</sect1>

