<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_aggcontext"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>AggregatorContext reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>AggregatorContext</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		AggregatorContext is one of the arguments passed to the aggregator
		computation function. It encapsulates the iteration through the
		aggregation group, in the order of the index on which the aggregator is
		defined. After the computation function returns, the context becomes
		invalidated and stops working, so there is no point in saving it
		between the calls. There is no way to construct the aggregator context
		directly.
		</para>

		<para>
		All the methods of the AggregatorContext confess on errors.
		</para>

		<para>
		An aggregator must never change the table. Any attempt to change the
		table is a fatal error.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $ctx->groupSize();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the number of rows in the group.
		</para>

<pre>
$rowType = $ctx->resultType();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the row type of the aggregation result.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $ctx->begin();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the first row handle of the iteration. In case of an empty
		group it would return a NULL handle.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $ctx->next($rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the next row handle in order. If the argument handle was the last row
		in the group, returns a NULL handle. So the iteration through the group
		with a context is similar to iteration through the whole table: it ends
		when <pre>begin()</pre> or <pre>next()</pre> returns a NULL handle. 
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $ctx->last();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the last row handle of the group. In case of an empty
		group it would return a NULL handle.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $ctx->beginIdx($idxType);
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the first row in the group, according to a specific index type's order.
		The index type must belong to the group, otherwise the result is
		undefined. If the group is empty, will return the same value as
		<pre>endIdx()</pre>. If <pre>$idxType</pre> is non-leaf, the effect is the same as if its
		first leaf were used. 
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $ctx->endIdx($idxType);
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the handle past the last row in the group, according to a specific
		index type's order. The index type must belong to the group, otherwise
		the result is undefined and might even result in an endless iteration
		loop.  If <pre>$idxType</pre> is non-leaf, the effect is the same as if its first
		leaf were used. This kind of iteration uses the table's
		<pre>$t->nextIdx($idxType, $rh)</pre> or <pre>$rh->next($idxType)</pre> to advance the
		position. 
		Unlike the general group iteration described in
		<xref linkend="sc_ref_table" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;, 
		the aggregator context does allow the iteration by every index in the group.
		You can pick any index in the group and iterate in its order.
		And aggregation is where this ability counts the most.
		</para>

		<para>
		If the group happens to be the last group of this index type (not of
		<pre>$idxType</pre> but of the index on which the aggregator is defined) in the
		table, <pre>endIdx()</pre> would return a NULL row handle. If it's also
		empty, <pre>beginIdx()</pre> would also return a NULL handle, and in general, for
		an empty group <pre>beginIdx()</pre> would return the same value as <pre>endIdx()</pre>. If
		the group is not the last one, <pre>endIdx()</pre> returns the handle of the first
		row in the next group.
		</para>

<pre>
$rh = $ctx->lastIdx($idxType);
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the last row in the group according to a particular index
		type's order. The index type must belong to the group, otherwise the
		result is undefined. If the group is empty, returns a NULL handle.
		</para>

<pre>
$ctx->send($opcode, $row);
</pre>

		<para>
		Constructs a result rowop for the aggregator and arranges for it to be
		sent to the aggregator's output label. The actual sending is
		delayed: it will be done only after all the aggregators run.
		The runs before and after the table modifications are separate.
		The aggregator's
		output label is not directly visible in the computation function, so the rowop
		can not be constructed directly. Instead <pre>send()</pre> takes care of it. The
		row must be of a type matching the aggregator's result type
		(and of course the normal practice is to use the aggregator's result
		type to construct the row). On success returns 1, on error returns
		<pre>undef</pre> and the error message.
		</para>

<pre>
$ctx->makeHashSend($opcode, $fieldName => $fieldValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		A convenience method that produces the row from pairs of field names
		and values and sends it. A combination of <pre>makeRowHash()</pre> and <pre>send()</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
$ctx->makeArraySend($opcode, @fields);
</pre>

		<para>
		A convenience function that produces the row from the array of field
		values and sends it. A combination of <pre>makeRowArray()</pre> and <pre>send()</pre>.
		</para>

	</sect1>

