<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_fields"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>Fields reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Fields</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		Triceps::Fields is a package with a set of functions that
		help with handling the variable sets of fields in the templates.
		</para>

<pre>
@fields = &Triceps::Fields::filter(
	$caller, \@inFields, \@translation);
</pre>

		<para>
		Filters and renames the incoming set of fields from <pre>\@inFields</pre> (usually
		coming from some row type) according to <pre>\@translation</pre>. Returns the array 
		of filtered names, positionally matching the names in the original
		array. When some field gets thrown away by filtering, its entry in the
		array will be <pre>undef</pre>. Confesses on errors. <pre>$caller</pre> is the
		caller's description for the error messages.
		</para>

		<para>
		See the description of the translation format in
		<xref linkend="sc_template_result" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		The option-processing functions <pre>Opt::drop()</pre> and <pre>Opt::dropExcept()</pre>
		can also be used to filter the field lists.
		</para>

<pre>
@pairs = &Triceps::Fields::filterToPairs(
	$caller, \@inFields, \@translation);
</pre>

		<para>
		Performs the same actions as <pre>filter()</pre> but returns the result in a different format:
		an array of pairs of field names, where the old field name is paired with the
		new one. The field names that gets thrown away by filtering do not appear in
		the result array.
		</para>

<pre>
($rowType, $projectFunc) = &Triceps::Fields::makeTranslation(
	$optName => $optValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Generates and compiles a function that performs the filtering of rows and
		creates the rows of the filtered type (a <quote>projection</quote> in SQL terms). 
		It accepts multiple input row types, each with its own translation specification,
		and creates the result row type by combining them all.
		Returns two elements: the result row type and the reference to the compiled
		function. The function can then be called to perform the projection and
		combining of the original rows:
		</para>

<pre>
$resultRow = &$projectFunc($origRow1, $origRow2, ..., $origRowN);
</pre>

		<para>
		If some of the original rows are not available, they may be passed as
		<pre>undef</pre>.  The options are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rowTypes => [ @rts ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array of row types for the original rows.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>filterPairs => [ @pairs ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array of arrays returned by <pre>filterPairs()</pre> for the
			original rows. Obviously, each of the original rows requires
			its own filter. The sizes of <quote>rowTypes</quote> and <quote>filterPairs</quote> arrays
			must match.  The field names in the results must not have
			any duplicates.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>saveCodeTo => \$code</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Optional. Reference to a scalar where to save the auto-generated source
			code of the projection function, for debugging.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

<pre>
$result = &Triceps::Fields::isArrayType($typeName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Checks whether a simple type is represented in Perl as an array.
		Since <pre>uint8[]</pre> is represented as a string, it will return 0.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = &Triceps::Fields::isStringType($typeName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Checks whether a simple type is represented in Perl as a string.
		<pre>string</pre>, <pre>uint8</pre> and <pre>uint8[]</pre> 
		will return 1.
		</para>
	</sect1>

