<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_lookupjoin"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>LookupJoin reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>LookupJoin</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		LookupJoin receives the incoming rows and looks up the matches for them
		from a table, producing the joined rows.
		</para>

<pre>
$joiner = Triceps::LookupJoin->new(optionName => optionValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Constructs the LookupJoin template. Confesses on any errors.
		The options are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>unit => $unit</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Scheduling unit object where this template belongs. 
			May be skipped if <quote>leftFromLabel</quote> is used.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>name => $name</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Name of this LookupJoin object. Will be used as a prefix to create
			the names of internal objects. The input label will be named
			<quote>name.in</quote> and the output label <quote>name.out</quote>.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>leftRowType => $rt</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Type of the rows that will be coming in at the left side of the
			join, and will be used for lookup.  Mutually exclusive with
			<quote>leftFromLabel</quote>, one must be present.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>leftFromLabel => $label</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Source of rows for the left side of the join; implies their type
			and the scheduling unit where this object belongs.  Mutually
			exclusive with <quote>leftRowType</quote>, one must be present.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rightTable => $table</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Table object where to do the look-ups.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rightIdxPath => [ @path ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Array reference containing the path name of index type in table
			used for the look-up. 
			The index absolutely must be a Hash (leaf or non-leaf), not of any
			other kind. Optional.
			Default: automatically found by the set of key fields. Whether
			explicitly specified or automatically found, the index must be available
			in the table.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>leftFields => [ @patterns ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array of patterns for the left-side fields to pass
			through. Syntax as described in <pre>Triceps::Fields::filter()</pre>. 
			Optional. If not defined then pass everything.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rightFields => [ @patterns ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array of patterns for the right-side fields to pass
			through. Syntax as described in <pre>Triceps::Fields::filter()</pre>. Optional.
			If not defined then pass everything (which is probably a bad idea since it
			would include the second copy of the key fields, so better
			override at least one of the <quote>leftFields</quote> or <quote>rightFields</quote>).
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>fieldsLeftFirst => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: in the resulting rows put the fields from the left side
			first, then from right side. If 0, then opposite. 
			Optional. Default: 1.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>fieldsMirrorKey => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: even if the join is an outer join and the row on one side is
			absent, when generating the result row, the key fields in it will
			still be present by mirroring them from the other side. Used by
			JoinTwo. Optional. Default: 0.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>fieldsDropRightKey => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: remove the key fields on the right side from the result.
			Convenient to avoid their duplication, especially if the key
			fields are named the same on both sides.
			Optional. Default: 0.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>by => [ @fields ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array containing pairs of field names used for
			look-up, <pre>[leftFld1, rightFld1, leftFld2, rightFld2, ...]</pre>.
			The set of right-side fields must match the keys of the index path
			from the option <quote>rightIdxPath</quote>, though possibly in a different order.
			Mutually exclusive with <quote>byLeft</quote>, one must be present.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>byLeft => [ @patterns ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array containing the patterns in the syntax of
			<pre>Triceps::Fields::filter()</pre>. It gets applied to the left-side fields,
			the fields that pass through become the key fields, and their
			translations are the names of the matching fields on the right
			side. The set of right-side fields must match the keys of the index
			path from  the option <pre>rightIdxPath</pre>, though possibly in a different
			order.
			Mutually exclusive with <quote>by</quote>, one must be present.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>isLeft => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: 1 for left outer join, 0 for inner join. Optional. Default: 1.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>limitOne => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: 1 to return no more than one row even
			if multiple rows have been found by the look-up, 0 to return all
			the found matches. 
			Optional. Default: 0 for the non-leaf right index, 1 for
			leaf right index. If the right index is leaf, this option will be
			always automatically set to 1, even if the user specified
			otherwise, since there is no way to look up more than one matching
			row in it.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>automatic => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: 1 means that the manual <pre>lookup()</pre> method will never be called.
			This allows to optimize the label handler code and always
			take the opcode into account when processing the rows. 0 means that
			<pre>lookup()</pre> will be used. Optional. Default: 1.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>oppositeOuter => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: 1 for the right outer join, 0 for inner join. If both options
			<quote>isLeft</quote> and <quote>oppositeOuter</quote> are set to 1, then this is a full outer
			join. If set to 1, each update that finds a match in the right
			table, may produce a DELETE-INSERT sequence that keeps the state of
			the right or full outer join consistent. The full outer or right
			outer join logic makes sense only if this LookupJoin is one of a
			pair in a bigger JoinTwo object. Each of these LookupJoins thinks
			of itself as <quote>left</quote> and of the other one as <quote>right</quote>, 
			while JoinTwo presents a consistent whole picture to the user.
			Used by JoinTwo.  May be used only when <quote>automatic</quote> is 1. 
			Optional. Default: 0.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>groupSizeCode => $func</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			Reference to a function that would compute the group size for this
			side's table.  Optional, used only when <quote>oppositeOuter</quote> is 1.
			</para>
			
			<para>
			The group size together with the opcode is then used
			to decide if a DELETE-INSERT sequence needs to be produced instead
			of a plain INSERT or DELETE. It is needed when this side's index
			(not visible here in LookupJoin but visible in the JoinTwo that
			envelopes it) is non-leaf, so multiple rows on this side
			may match each row on the other side. The DELETE-INSERT pair
			needs to be generated only if the current rowop was a deletion of
			the last matching row or insertion of the first matching row
			on this side. If <quote>groupSizeCode</quote> is not defined, the
			DELETE-INSERT pair is always generated (which is appropriate if
			this side's index is leaf, and every row is the last or first
			one). If <quote>groupSizeCode</quote> is defined, it should return the group
			size in the left table by the left index for the input row. If
			the operation is INSERT, the size of 1 would mean that
			the DELETE-INSERT pair needs to be generated. If the operation
			is DELETE, the size of 0  would mean that the DELETE-INSERT
			pair needs to be generated. Called as:
			</para>
			
<pre>
&$groupSizeCode($opcode, $leftRow)
</pre>

			<para>
			The default undefined <quote>groupSizeCode</quote> is equivalent to
			</para>
			
<pre>
sub { &Triceps::isInsert($_[0]); }
</pre>

			<para>
			but leaving it undefined is more efficient since allows to hardcode
			this logic at compile time instead of calling the function for
			every rowop.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>saveJoinerTo => \$code</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to a scalar where to save a copy of the joiner function
			source code.  Optional.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

<pre>
@rows = $joiner->lookup($leftRow);
</pre>

		<para>
		Looks up the matches for the <pre>$leftRow</pre> and return the array of the result
		rows. If the option <quote>isLeft</quote> is 0, the array may be empty. If the
		option <quote>limitOne</quote> is 1, the array will contain no more than one row,
		and may be assigned directly to a scalar. May be used only when the option
		<quote>automatic</quote> is 0.
		</para>

		<para>
		This method has become largely obsolete since addition of <pre>fnReturn()</pre>
		as described in
		<xref linkend="sc_strf_templates" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		but is still present in case if it comes useful.
		</para>

<pre>
$rt = $joiner->getResultRowType();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the row type of the join result.
		</para>

<pre>
$lb = $joiner->getInputLabel();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the input label of the joiner. The rowops sent there will be
		processed as coming on the left side of the join. The result will be
		produced on the output label.
		</para>

<pre>
$lb = $joiner->getOutputLabel();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the output label of the joiner. The results from processing of the
		input rowops come out here. Note that the results of the <pre>lookup()</pre> calls
		do not come out at the output label, they are only returned to the
		caller.
		</para>

<pre>
$fret = $joiner->fnReturn();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns an FnReturn object connected to the output of this joiner.
		The FnReturn contains one label <quote>out</quote>.
		The FnReturn is created on the first call of
		this method and is kept in the joiner object.  All the following calls return
		the same object. 
		See more detail in
		<xref linkend="sc_strf_templates" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $joiner->getUnit();
$res = $joiner->getName(); 
$res = $joiner->getLeftRowType(); 
$res = $joiner->getRightTable(); 
$res = $joiner->getRightIdxPath(); 
$res = $joiner->getLeftFields(); 
$res = $joiner->getRightFields(); 
$res = $joiner->getFieldsLeftFirst(); 
$res = $joiner->getFieldsMirrorKey(); 
$res = $joiner->getBy(); 
$res = $joiner->getByLeft(); 
$res = $joiner->getIsLeft(); 
$res = $joiner->getLimitOne(); 
$res = $joiner->getAutomatic(); 
$res = $joiner->getOppositeOuter(); 
$res = $joiner->getGroupSizeCode(); 
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the values of the options use to construct the object. 
		If such an option was not set,
		returns the default value, or the automatically calculated value.
		Sometimes an automatically calculated value may even override the
		user-specified value. There is no way to get back <quote>leftFromLabel</quote>, it
		is discarded after the LookupJoin is constructed and chained.
		</para>

	</sect1>
