<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_jointwo"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>JoinTwo reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>JoinTwo</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		JoinTwo is a template that joins two tables. As the tables are modified,
		the updates propagate through the join. The join itself keeps no state
		(other than the state of its input tables), so if it needs to be kept,
		it has to be saved into another table. There is no requirement of a
		primary key on either the input tables nor the join result. However if
		the result is saved into a table, that table would have to have a primary
		key, so by extension the join would have to produce the result with
		a primary key, or the table contents will become incorrect.
		The JoinTwo is internally implemented as a pair of LookupJoins.
		</para>

<pre>
$joiner = Triceps::JoinTwo->new(optionName => optionValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates the JoinTwo object. Confesses on any errors.
		The options are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>name => $name</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Name of this object. Will be used to create the names of internal objects.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>leftTable => $table</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Table object to join, for the left side. Both tables must be of the same unit.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rightTable => $table</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Table object to join, for the right side. Both tables must be of the same unit.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>leftFromLabel => $label</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			The label from which to receive the rows on
			the left side. 
			Optional. Default: the Output label of <quote>leftTable</quote> unless it's
			a self-join; for a self-join the Pre label of <quote>leftTable</quote>. 
			</para>

			<para>
			Can be used to introduce a label that would filter out some of the input. THIS IS
			DANGEROUS! To preserve consistency, always filter by the key
			field(s) only, and apply the same condition on the left and right.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rightFromLabel => $label</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			The label from which to receive the rows on the right side. 
			Optional. Default: the Output label of <quote>rightTable</quote>.
			</para>

			<para>
			Can be used to introduce a label that would filter out some of the input. THIS IS
			DANGEROUS! To preserve consistency, always filter by the key
			field(s) only, and apply the same condition on the left and right.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>leftIdxPath => [ @path ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			An array reference containing the path name of an index type in the
			left table used for look-up. The index absolutely must be a Hash
			(leaf or not), not of any other kind. The number and order of key
			fields in the left and right indexes must match, since indexes define
			the fields used for the join. The types of key fields have to
			match exactly unless the auto-casting is allowed by the option 
			<quote>overrideKeyTypes</quote> being set to 1.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rightIdxPath => [ @path ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			An array reference containing the path name of an index type in the
			right table used for look-up. The index absolutely must be a Hash
			(leaf or not), not of any other kind. The number and order of key
			fields in the left and right indexes must match, since indexes define
			the fields used for the join. The types of key fields have to
			match exactly unless the auto-casting is allowed by the option 
			<quote>overrideKeyTypes</quote> being set to 1.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>leftFields => [ @patterns ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array of patterns for the left-side fields to pass
			through to the result rows, with the syntax of
			<pre>Triceps::Fields::filter()</pre>. Optional. If not defined then pass everything.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rightFields => [ @patterns ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array of patterns for the right-side fields to pass
			through to the result rows, with the syntax of
			<pre>Triceps::Fields::filter()</pre>. Optional. If not defined then pass everything.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>fieldsLeftFirst => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: if 1, in the result rows put the fields from the left side
			first, then from the right side; if 0, then in the opposite order.
			Optional. Default: 1.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>fieldsUniqKey => $enum</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			Controls the logic that prevents the duplication of the key fields
			in the result rows (since by definition their originals are present
			in both the left and right tables). Optional.
			</para>

			<para>
			This is done by setting the
			option <quote>fieldsMirrorKey</quote> of the underlying LookupJoins to 1 and by
			manipulating the left/rightFields options: one side is
			left unchanged, and thus lets the user pass the key fields as
			usual, while the other side gets <pre>'!key'</pre> specs prepended to the
			front of it for each key field, thus blocking these fields
			and removing the duplication.
			</para>

			<para>
			The enumerated values of this option are one of: 
			</para>

			<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><quote>none</quote></term>
				<listitem>
				Do not change either of the <quote>left/rightFields</quote>,
				and do not enable the key mirroring at all.
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><quote>manual</quote></term>
				<listitem>
				Enable the key mirroring; do not change either of the
				<quote>left/rightFields</quote>, leaving the full control to
				the user.
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><quote>left</quote></term>
				<listitem>
				Enable the key mirroring; do not change <quote>leftFields</quote> (and thus
				pass the key fields in there), block the keys from
				<quote>rightFields</quote>.
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><quote>right</quote></term>
				<listitem>
				Enable the key mirroring; do not change <quote>rightFields</quote> (and thus
				pass the key fields in there), block the keys from
				<quote>leftFields</quote>.
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><quote>first</quote></term>
				<listitem>
				The default value. Enable the key mirroring; do not change
				whatever side goes first according to the option
				<quote>fieldsLeftFirst</quote> (and thus pass the key in there), block the
				keys from the other side.
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>by => [ @fields ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array containing pairs of field names
			used for look-up, <pre>[leftFld1, rightFld1, leftFld2, rightFld2, ...]</pre>. 
			Optional.
			The options <quote>by</quote> and <quote>byLeft</quote> are mutually exclusive. If none of
			them is used, by default the field lists are taken from the
			index type keys, matched up in the order they appear in the
			indexes. But if a different order is desired, this option can be
			used to override it. The fields must still be the same, just
			the order may change. 
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>byLeft => [ @patterns ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to an array containing the patterns in the syntax of
			<pre>Triceps::Fields::filter()</pre>. It gets applied to the left-side fields,
			the fields that pass through  become the key fields, and their
			translations are the names of the  matching fields on the right
			side.
			Optional.
			The options <quote>by</quote> and <quote>byLeft</quote> are mutually exclusive. If none of
			them is used, by default the field lists are taken from the
			index type keys, matched up in the order they appear in the
			indexes. But if a different order is desired, this option can be
			used to override it. The fields must still be the same, just
			the order may change. 
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>type => $enum</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The type of join from the inner/outer classification, one of:
			<quote>inner</quote>, <quote>left</quote> for left outer, 
			<quote>right</quote> for right outer, <quote>outer</quote>
			for full outer. Optional. Default: <quote>inner</quote>.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>leftSaveJoinerTo => \$code</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to a scalar where to save a copy of the joiner
			function source code for the left side. Optional.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rightSaveJoinerTo => \$code</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Reference to a scalar where to save a copy of the joiner
			function source code for the right side. Optional.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>overrideSimpleMinded => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: if 1, do not try to create the correct DELETE-INSERT sequence
			for the updates, just produce the rows with the same opcode as the
			incoming ones. The only possible usage of this option might be to
			simulate the CEP systems that do not support the opcodes and treat
			averything as an INSERT. The data produced is outright garbage. It
			can also be used for the entertainment value, to show, why it's
			garbage. Optional. Default: 0.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>overrideKeyTypes => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: if 1, allow the key field types to be not exactly the same.
			Optional. Default: 0.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

<pre>
$rt = $joiner->getResultRowType();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the row type of the join result.
		</para>

<pre>
$lb = $joiner->getOutputLabel();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the output label of the joiner. The results from processing of
		the  input rowops come out here. Note that there is no input label, the
		join is fed by connecting to the tables (with the possible override
		with the options <quote>left/rightFromLabel</quote>).
		</para>

<pre>
$fret = $joiner->fnReturn();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns an FnReturn object connected to the output of this joiner.
		The FnReturn contains one label <quote>out</quote>.
		The FnReturn is created on the first call of
		this method and is kept in the joiner object.  All the following calls return
		the same object. 
		See more detail in
		<xref linkend="sc_strf_templates" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $joiner->getUnit();
$res = $joiner->getName();
$res = $joiner->getLeftTable();
$res = $joiner->getRightTable();
$res = $joiner->getLeftIdxPath();
$res = $joiner->getRightIdxPath();
$res = $joiner->getLeftFields();
$res = $joiner->getRightFields();
$res = $joiner->getFieldsLeftFirst();
$res = $joiner->getFieldsUniqKey();
$res = $joiner->getBy();
$res = $joiner->getByLeft();
$res = $joiner->getType();
$res = $joiner->getOverrideSimpleMinded();
$res = $joiner->getOverrideKeyTypes();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the values of the options use to construct the object. 
		If such an option was not set,
		returns the default value, or the automatically calculated value.
		Sometimes an automatically calculated value may even override the
		user-specified value. There is no way to get back
		<quote>left/rightFromLabel</quote>, they are discarded after the JoinTwo is
		constructed and chained.
		</para>
	</sect1>
