<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_collapse"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>Collapse reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Collapse</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		The Collapse template collapses multiple sequential modifications
		per primary key into one. On flush it sends out that single modification.
		</para>

<pre>
$collapse = Triceps::Collapse->new($optName => $optValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a new Collapse object. The options are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>name</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Name of this object. Will be used to create the names of internal objects.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>unit</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The unit where this object belongs.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>data</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The data set description. Each data set has an input label and an
			output label, and collapses one stream of modifications. Currently
			only one data set is supported, the options have been structured
			like this to allow for the future extension. This option's value
			is a reference to an array (not a hash!) that is itself structured
			as the nested option-value pairs.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>
		The nested options in <quote>data</quote> are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>name</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The name of the data set. Used for the error messages. Put it
			first, this would let the constructor report nicely the errors
			in the other data set options.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rowType</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The row type of the data in this set. 
			Mutually exclusive with <quote>fromLabel</quote>, one must
			be used.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>fromLabel</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The source label for the data set, its input will be chained
			to this label.
			Mutually exclusive with <quote>rowType</quote>, one must
			be used.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>key</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The primary key of the data. A reference to an array of strings
			with field names, same as for the Hash index type.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

<pre>
$collapse->flush();
</pre>

		<para>
		Sends out the collected modifications to the output label(s)
		and clears the state of the collapse.
		</para>

<pre>
$lb = $collapse->getInputLabel($setName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the input label of a data set. Confesses if there is no
		data set with this name.
		</para>

<pre>
$lb = $collapse->getOutputLabel($setName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the output label of a data set. Confesses if there is no
		data set with this name.
		</para>

<pre>
@setNames = $collapse->getDatasets();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the names of all the data sets (though since currently only one
		data set is supported, only one name will be returned).
		</para>

<pre>
$fret = $collapse->fnReturn();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns an FnReturn object connected to the output of this collapser.
		The FnReturn contains a label for each data set, named accordingly.
		The order of the labels matches the specified order of data sets.
		The FnReturn is created on the first call of
		this method and is kept in the collapser object.  All the following calls return
		the same object. 
		See more detail in
		<xref linkend="sc_strf_templates" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

	</sect1>
