<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_fnbinding">
		<title>FnBinding reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>FnBinding</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		An FnBinding represents a single call of a streaming function.
		It forwards the stream of rowops coming out of an FnReturn to the
		logic in the caller.
		</para>

<pre>
$fbind = Triceps::FnBinding->new($optName => $optValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Construct an FnBinding object. The object may be reused for multiple
		calls. It's very much like a function call in a procedural language:
		present once in the program text but can be executed many times.
		The options are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>name => $name</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Name of this object. Will be used to create the names of the labels in it.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>unit => $unit</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The unit where the labels specified as Perl inline code will be created.
			If no labels are specified in this format, this option is not required.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>on => $fret</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The FnReturn on which this binding is defined. It determines what labels
			are available for binding. The created FnBinding may be used not only with that
			particular FnReturn but also with any FnReturn of a matching type.
			If that other FnReturn has not an equal but only a matching type, the 
			labels will be connected by the order in which they were defined in their
			respective FnReturns.
			It's a bit tricky: when an FnBinding is created, the labels in it get
			connected to the FnReturn on which it's defined by name. But at this
			point each of them gets assigned a number, in order the labels went
			in that original FnReturn. After that only this number matters: if
			this FnBinding gets connected to another matching FnReturn, it will get
			the data from the FnReturn's label with the same number, not the same
			name.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>labels => [ @definitions ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			Definition of the labels in the FnBinding, that will be connected to the
			labels in FnReturn when the FnBinding is pushed on the FnReturn.
			The label names within an
			FnBinding must match the names from FnReturn. They may go in any order
			but internally will be reordered to match the label order from FnReturn.
			The value for this option is an array
			reference, with the labels defined as name-value pairs in the array, in
			one of two forms:
			</para>

<pre>
labels => [
	$name1 => $label1,
	$name2 => sub { ... },
	...
]
</pre>

			<para>
			If the second element in the pair is a function reference
			or a source code snippet in a string, a label will be automatically created using the unit from the
			option <quote>unit</quote>, the row type from the matching label in
			FnReturn, and the provided function as the label's code. It's a 
			convenient way to make your code shorter.  The full names of these created
			labels will be <quote>binding_name.label_name</quote>. 
			</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Unit</primary>
		</indexterm>
			<para>
			The labels in an FnBinding may belong to a different unit than
			the labels of the FnReturn. The FnReturn-FnBinding pair is an official
			way to connect two units.
			</para>

			<para>
			It's also possible to include labels from multiple units into a single
			FnBinding. It's not particularly recommended but it happens to work.
			It creates complications when dealing with trays.
			</para>

			<para>
			The details of the label execution in a binding are described in
			<xref linkend="sc_strf_scheduling" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>withTray => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: Determines, whether the rowops coming into the FnBinding will be executed
			immediately (<pre>withTray => 0</pre>) or collected in a tray
			(<pre>withTray => 1</pre>). Optional, 0 by default.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>clearLabels => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			Flag: Determines whether the labels in FnBinding will be automatically cleared
			and forgotten in their unit when the FnBinding gets destroyed. This allows
			to create the temporary FnBindings dynamically and destroy them after the use,
			without leaking the labels. This option applies only to the labels specified
			as the label objects. The labels created by the FnBinding from the code
			references are always cleared and forgotten.
			</para>

			<para>
			Unlike the &Cpp; API, there is no way to set this option separately for
			each label, it's all or none. But normally all the labels need the same
			treatment anyway, so it just makes things easier.
			</para>

			<para>
			Optional, 0 by default. Even for the dynamically created and destroyed
			FnBindings, this option is usually best left at 0, since usually the Label objects
			given to it will not be dynamically created, they would stay fixed between
			their uses. The only exception is if you create the labels along with the
			FnBinding and destroy them together as well. If you're doing that, probably
			you'd be better off having FnBinding create the labels for you from the
			code snippets, and those are always cleared and forgotten after the FnBinding
			destruction, no matter what this option is set to.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>FnBinding::call</primary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
Triceps::FnBinding::call($optName => $optValue, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		A convenience function to create an FnBinding dynamically, do a single streaming
		function call with it, and destroy the FnBinding. This is not the most efficient
		way, since the FnBinding objects and its labels are constructed and destoryed
		on every call, but easy to use.
		</para>

		<para>
		The options largely match the FnBinding constructor, with the addition of
		the options that do the streaming function call.
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>name => $name</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Name of the FnBinding object that will be constructed and destoryed for
			this call. Will be used to create the names of the labels in it.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>unit => $unit</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The unit where the labels specified as Perl inline code will be created.
			If no labels are specified in this format, this option is not required.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>on => $fret</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			The FnReturn on which this binding is defined (see mode details on
			that in the description of FnBinding constructor) and also the FnReturn
			on which the call will be performed.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>labels => [ @definitions ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			Definition of the labels in the FnBinding, that will be connected to the
			labels in FnReturn when the FnBinding is pushed on the FnReturn.
			The format and meaning is the same as in the FnBinding constructor:
			</para>

<pre>
labels => [
	$name1 => $label1,
	$name2 => sub { ... },
	...
]
</pre>

			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>delayed => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: An analog of option <quote>withTray</quote> of the FnBinding constructor.
			Determines, whether the rowops coming into the FnBinding will be executed
			immediately (<pre>delayed => 0</pre>) or collected in a tray and the
			tray executed after the FnBinding is popped from FnReturn (but before FnBinding
			is destroyed). Since the FnBinding
			is created and destroyed inside the call, there is no way to get the tray
			out of it, instead the tray gets automatically executed.
			Optional, 0 by default.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>clearLabels => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: Determines whether the labels in FnBinding will be automatically cleared
			and forgotten in their unit when the FnBinding gets destroyed. The details
			are described with the constructor.
			Optional, 0 by default, and highly unlikely to be used.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rowop => $rowop</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			A reference to rowop to execute as the argument to the streaming function.
			Exactly one of options <quote>rowop</quote>, <quote>rowops</quote>,
			<quote>tray</quote>, <quote>code</quote> must be used.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>rowops => [ @rowops ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			A reference to an array of rowops (<pre>rowops => [ @rowops ]</pre>) to execute as the argument to the
			streaming function. This is just a convenient way to inline multiple
			rowops without constructing a Tray.
			Exactly one of options <quote>rowop</quote>, <quote>rowops</quote>,
			<quote>tray</quote>, <quote>code</quote> must be used.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>tray => $tray</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			A reference to tray to execute as the argument to the streaming function.
			Exactly one of options <quote>rowop</quote>, <quote>rowops</quote>,
			<quote>tray</quote>, <quote>code</quote> must be used.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>code => $code</pre></term>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>code => [ $code, @args ]</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			A code reference or snippet to execute that sends the arguments to the streaming function.
			The source code snippet in a string also works. This option may also specify
			a function reference (or, again, its source code) together with its arguments.
			In this case the value would be an array reference: <pre>code => [ $code, @args ]</pre>.
			Exactly one of options <quote>rowop</quote>, <quote>rowops</quote>,
			<quote>tray</quote>, <quote>code</quote> must be used.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

<pre>
$res = $fbind->same($fbind2);
</pre>

		<para>
		The usual check for two references referring to the same FnBinding object.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $fbind->equals($fret2);
$res = $fbind->equals($fbind2);
$res = $fbind->match($fret2);
$res = $fbind->match($fbind2);
</pre>

		<para>
		Compare the equality or match of types with an FnReturn or FnBinding.
		Since their type objects are not directly visible in the Perl API,
		the comparison has to be done on the FnReturns and FnBindings themselves.
		The types are considered equal if they contain the equal row
		types with equal names going in the same order. They are considered
		matching if they contain matching row types going in the same order,
		with any names. If the match condition seems surprising to you, think
		of it as <quote>nothing will break if one type is substituted for another at
		execution time</quote>.
		</para>

<pre>
$name = $fbind->getName();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the name of the binding.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $fbind->size();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the number of labels in the underlying FnReturn. That is, not just of the
		labels actually used in the binding but of all the labels that could be
		potentially used in it.
		</para>

<pre>
@names = $fbind->getLabelNames();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get an array of label names, in the same order as they were defined in 
		the underlying FnReturn.  This will include all the possible labels from
		the FnReturn, even those that were not used in FnBinding.
		</para>

<pre>
@names = $fbind->getDefinedLabelNames();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get an array of label names that are actually used in the FnBinding.
		The order is still the same as they were defined in FnReturn, only
		the ones not mentioned in FnBinding are skipped.
		</para>

<pre>
@labels = $fret->getLabels();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get an array of references to the FnBinding's labels, in the
		order they were defined in the FnReturn. 
		If some label name was defined
		in FnReturn but not used in FnBinding, that position will contain an
		<pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
%labels = $fret->getLabelHash();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the interspersed list of label names and references, suitable
		to initialize a hash.  If some label name was defined
		in FnReturn but not used in FnBinding,  the reference for it will
		be <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
%namemap = $fret->getLabelMapping();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the interspersed list of label names and their indexes in order
		starting from 0, suitable to initialize a hash. 
		This includes all the labels from FnReturn.
		</para>

<pre>
$label = $fret->getLabel($name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Get a label by name. Will confess if this name was not defined in FnReturn.
		If a label was defined in FnReturn but not used in FnBinding, returns
		an <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
$label = $fret->getLabelAt($idx);
</pre>

		<para>
		Get a label by index, starting from 0. The index range is as defined in the
		underlying FnReturn.  Will confess if the index is out of range.
		If a label was defined in FnReturn but not used in FnBinding, returns
		an <pre>undef</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
$idx = $fret->findLabel($name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Translate a label name to index. Will confess if this name was not defined.
		</para>

<pre>
%rts = $fret->getRowTypeHash();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the interspersed list of label names and references to their row types, suitable
		to initialize a hash.  This includes all the label names from FnReturn, even if
		they weren't used in the FnBinding.
		In Perl, this is the closest thing to the &Cpp; API's RowSetType.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $fbind->withTray();
$res = $fbind->withTray($on);
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back or change the value of <quote>withTray</quote> option. If the argument
		<pre>$on</pre> is used, it sets the new value.  The change
		can be done at any time. Either form returns the previous value of the option.
		Disabling the tray mode discards the current tray.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $fbind->traySize();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the size of the currently collected tray. If the tray is disabled, returns 0.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $fbind->trayEmpty();
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the tray is currently empty. Also returns 1 is the tray is disabled.
		</para>

<pre>
$tray = $fbind->swapTray();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the current tray out of the FnBinding, and replace it with an empty tray.
		If the tray contains a mix of rowops for different units (which might happen
		if the FnBinding refers to labels from different units), it will be detected
		at this point and the metod will confess. The Perl API doesn't support dealing
		with such mixed trays. It's still possible to deal with this situation in Perl
		by using <pre>callTray()</pre>. This method will also detect and confess if
		any of the rowops in the tray are destined for the cleared labels. Normally
		such rowops are simply ignored but this is a special case. It reduces the
		surprise if you accidentally clear the labels and then wonder why is the
		binding not working right.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $fbind->traySize();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the size of the currently collected tray. If the tray is disabled, returns 0.
		</para>

<pre>
$fbind->callTray();
</pre>

		<para>
		Logically, a combination of <pre>swapTray()</pre> and the call of that returned tray.
		However this method also does the correct handling of the trays that contain
		a mix of rowops for different units. Each rowop will be called in its proper unit.
		</para>

	</sect1>
