<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_autofnbind">
		<title>AutoFnBind reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>AutoFnBind</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		AutoFnBind provides a scoped way of pushing and popping of the
		FnBindings on the FnReturns. The pushing happens when an AutoFnBind
		object is constructed, the popping when it is destroyed (or on an
		explicit clearing).
		</para>

<pre>
$ab = AutoFnBind->new($ret1 => $binding1, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Create an AutoFnBind object. The arguments consist of pairs of FnReturns 
		and FnBindings to push on them. The pushing will happen in the constructor
		in the order specified, the popping in the destructor or <pre>clear()</pre>
		method in the opposite order.
		</para>

		<para>
		If any corruption of the call stack is detected at the popping time 
		(i.e. the binding on the top of the stack is not the one that was
		pushed on it), this error will be detected. However since there is
		no way to report an error from a Perl destructor, this error message will
		be printed on stderr and the whole program will exit with the code 1.
		If you care about the ability to catch this error, use the method
		<pre>clear()</pre> before destroying the AutoFnBind object.
		</para>

<pre>
$ab->clear();
</pre>

		<para>
		Pop the bindings, just as during the destruction, and discard the
		references to the FnReturn and FnBinding objects.  After the clearing is
		done once, the destructor will not pop anything any more, and the repeated
		clearings will have no effect.
		</para>

		<para>
		Any detected stack corruptions make this method confess. The popping
		will always go through the whole list of bindings, collecting the
		error reports along the way.  At the end of
		the run it will make sure that it doesn't have any references to
		anything any more, and only then confess if any errors were found.
		This cleans up the things as much as possible and as
		much as can be handled, but the end result will still not be
		particularly clean: the returns that got their stacks corrupted will
		still have their stacks corrupted, and some very serious
		application-level cleaning will be needed to continue. Probably a
		better choice would be to destroy everything and restart from scratch.
		But at least it allows to get safely to this point of restarting from
		scratch.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = $ab->same($ab2);
</pre>

		<para>
		The usual check for two references referring to the same object.
		</para>

	</sect1>
