<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_app">
		<title>App reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>App</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		An App represents a complete multithreaded Triceps application.
		There may be multiple applications running in the same process.
		</para>

	<sect2 id="sc_ref_app_inst_management">
		<title>App instance management</title>

		<para>
		The first part of the App API keeps track of all the
		App instances in the program, and allows to list and find them.
		It's global by necessity.
		</para>

<pre>
@apps = Triceps::App::listApps();
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the array of name-value pairs, values containing the App
		references, listing all the Apps in the program (more exactly, in this
		Triceps library, if you compile multiple Triceps libraries together by
		renaming them, each of them will have its own Apps list). The returned
		array can be placed into a hash.
		</para>

<pre>
$app = Triceps::App::find($name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Find an App by name. If an App with such a name does not exist, it will
		confess.
		</para>

<pre>
$app = Triceps::App:make($name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Create a new App, give it the specified name, and put it on the list.
		The names must not be duplicate with the other existing Apps, or the
		method will confess.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::drop($app);
Triceps::App::drop($appName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Drop the app, by reference or by name, from the list. The App is as
		usual reference-counted and will exist while there are references to
		it. The global list provides one of these references, so an App is
		guaranteed to exist while it's still on the list. When dropped, it will
		still be accessible through the existing references, but obviously will
		not be listed any more and could not be found by name.
		</para>

		<para>
		Moreover, a new App with the same name can be added to the list.
		Because of this, dropping an App by name requires some care in case if
		there could be a new App created again with the same name: it creates a
		potential for a race, and you might end up dropping the new App instead
		of the old one. Of course, if it's the same thread that drops the old
		one and creates the new one, then there is no race. Dropping an
		application by name that doesn't exist at the moment is an error and
		will confess.
		</para>

		<para>
		Dropping the App by reference theoretically allows to avoid the race: a
		specific object gets dropped, and if it already has been dropped, the
		call has no effect. Theoretically. However in practice Perl has a
		limitation on passing the object values between threads, and thus
		whenever each thread starts, first thing it does is finding its App by
		name. It's a very similar kind of race and is absolutely unavoidable
		except by making sure that all the App's threads have exited and joined
		(i.e. harvesting them). So make sure to complete the App's thread
		harvesting before dropping the App in the harvester thread, and by then
		it doesn't matter a whole lot if the App is dropped by name or by
		reference.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="sc_ref_app_resolution">
		<title>App resolution</title>

		<para>
		Many (but not all) of the App methods allow to specify the App either
		by reference or by name, and they automatically sort it out, doing the
		internal look-up by name if necessary. So the same method could be used
		as either of:
		</para>

<pre>
$app->method(...);
Triceps::App::method($app, ...);
Triceps::App::method($appName, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		Obviously, you cannot use the <quote><pre>-></pre></quote> syntax with a name, and obviously
		if the name is not in the app list, the method will confess. Below I'll
		show the calls that allow the dual formats as
		<pre>Triceps::App::method($appOrName, ...)</pre> but keep in mind that you can use
		the <quote><pre>-></pre></quote> form of them too with a reference.
		</para>

<pre>
$app = Triceps::App::resolve($appOrName); 
</pre>

		<para>
		Do just the
		automatically-sorting-out part: gets a reference or name and returns a
		reference either way. A newly created reference is returned in either
		case (not the argument reference). You can use this resolver before the
		methods that accept only a reference.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="sc_ref_app_introspection">
		<title>App introspection</title>

<pre>
$result = $app->same($app2);
</pre>

		<para>
		Check if two references are for the same App object. Here they both
		must be references and not names.
		</para>

<pre>
$name = $app->getName();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the name of the App, from a reference.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::declareTriead($appOrName, $trieadName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Declare a Triead (Triceps thread) in advance. Any attempts to look up
		the nexuses in that thread will then wait for the thread to become
		ready. (Attempts to look up in an undeclared and undefined thread are
		errors). This is necessary to prevent a race at the thread creation
		time.  For the most part, the method <pre>Triead::start()</pre> just does the
		right thing by calling this method automatically and you don't need the
		use it manually, except in some very special circumstances.
		Declaring a thread with the same name more than once or declaring an already
		defined thread is perfectly all right.
		</para>

<pre>
%trieads = Triceps::App::getTrieads($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the list of currently defined Trieads in the App, as name-value pairs. Keep in
		mind that the other threads may be modifying the list of Trieads, so if
		you do this call multiple times, you may get different results. However
		the Trieads are returned as references, so they are guaranteed to stay
		alive and readable even if they get removed from the App, or even if
		the App gets dropped.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="sc_ref_app_harvester">
		<title>App harvester control</title>

		<para>
		The harvester logic is a necessary part of an App. It manages the
		collection of the Trieads that died and allows the rest of the
		program find out when the App terminates. It runs in a designated
		thread (an OS/Perl thread, not a Triead, though in some special
		cases it may use a thread left over from a Triead).
		</para>

		<para>
		Normally the harvester thread runs in parallel with the rest of the
		App logic. To wait for the App's exit, wait for the harvester's thread
		to exit. In case of the small programs (such as the unit tests),
		the App's <quote>main Triead</quote> may share the thread with the
		harvester: first the main Triead method would run, and after it
		returns, the harvester. This obviously means that the threads that
		have exited will be sitting in the zombie state during the life
		of the App, until the harvester has a chance to run.
		</para>

		<para>
		The harvesting is an absolutely necessary part of the App life cycle,
		however in most of the usage patterns (such as with <pre>Triead::startHere()</pre>
		or <pre>App::build()</pre>) the harvester is called implicitly from the wrapping
		library functions, so you don't need to care about it.
		</para>

<pre>
$app->harvester(@options);
</pre>

		<para>
		Run the harvester in the current thread. The harvester gets
		notifications from the threads when they are about to exit, and joins
		them.  After all the threads have been joined, it automatically drops
		the App, and returns.
		</para>
		 
		<para>
		Note that if you're running the harvester manually, you must call
		it only after the first thread has been defined or at least declared.
		Otherwise it will find no threads in the App, consider it dead and
		immediately drop it.
		</para>

		<para>
		If the App was aborted, the harvester will normally confess after if
		had joined all the threads and disposed of the App, unless the option
		<quote>die_on_abort</quote> (see below) has been set to 0. This propagates the error
		to the caller. However there is a catch: if some of the threads don't
		react properly by exiting on an abort indication, the program will be
		stuck and you will see no error message until these threads get
		unstuck, possibly forever.
		</para>

		<para>
		Options:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>die_on_abort => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: If the App was aborted, the harvester will normally
			confess after if had joined all the threads and disposed of the
			App.  Setting this option to 0 will make the aborts silently
			ignored. This option does not affect the errors in joining the
			threads: if any of those are detected, harvester will still confess
			after it had disposed of the app. Optional. Default: 1.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>


<pre>
$dead = $app->harvestOnce();
</pre>

		<para>
		Do one run of the harvesting.  Joins all the threads that have exited
		since its last call. If no threads have exited since then, returns
		immediately. Returns 1 if all the threads have exited (and thus the App
		is dead), 0 otherwise.  If a thread join fails, immediately confesses
		(if multiple threads were ready for joining, the ones queued after the
		failed one won't be joined, call <pre>harvestOnce()</pre> once more to join them).
		</para>

<pre>
$app->waitNeedHarvest();
</pre>

		<para>
		Wait for at least one thread to become ready for harvesting. If the App
		is already dead (i.e. all its threads have exited), returns
		immediately.
		</para>

		<para>
		These two methods allow to write the custom harvesters if you're not
		happy with the default one. The basic harvester logic can be written
		as:
		</para>

<pre>
do {
  $app->waitNeedHarvest()
} while(!$app->harvestOnce());
$app->drop();
</pre>

		<para>
		However the real harvester also does some smarter things around the
		error handling. You can look it up in the source code in
		<pre>cpp/app/App.cpp</pre>.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="sc_ref_app_state">
		<title>App state management</title>

<pre>
$res = Triceps::App::isDead($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns 1 if the App is dead (i.e. it has no alive Trieads, all the
		defined and declared threads have exited). Right after the App is
		created, before the first Triead is created, the App is also considered
		dead, and becomes alive when the first Triead is declared or defined.
		If an App becomes dead later, when all the Trieads exit, it can still
		be brought back alive by creating more Trieads. But this is considered
		bad practice, and will cause a race with the harvester (if you want to
		do this, you have to make your own custom harvester).
		</para>

		<para>
		Calling this method with a name for the argument is probably a bad
		idea, since the App may be dropped quickly quickly after it
		becomes dead, and you may end up with this method confessing when it
		could not find the dropped App.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = Triceps::App::isShutdown($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns 1 if the App has been requested to shut down, either normally
		or by being aborted.  The Trieads might
		still run for some time, until they properly detect and process the
		shutdown, and exit. So this condition is not equivalent to Dead,
		althouh they are connected. If any new Trieads get started, they will
		be shut down right away and won't run.
		</para>

		<para>
		To reiterate: if all the Trieads just exit by themselves, the App
		becomes dead but not shut down. You could still start more Trieads and
		bring the App back alive. If the App had been shut down, it won't
		become immediately dead, but it will send the shutdown indication to
		all the Trieads, and after all of them eventually exit, the App will
		become dead too. And after shutdown there is no way to bring the App
		back alive, since any new Trieads will be shut down right away.
		There might be a short period until they detect the shutdown, so the
		App could spike as alive for a short time, but then will become dead
		again.
		</para>

<pre>
$res = Triceps::App::isAborted($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns 1 if the App has been aborted. The App may be aborted
		explicitly by calling the method <pre>abortBy()</pre>, or the thread wrapper logic
		automatically converts any unexpected deaths in the App's threads to
		the aborts. If any thread dies, this aborts the App, which in turn
		requests the other threads to die on their next thread-related call.
		Eventually the harvester collects them all and confesses, normally
		making the whole program die with an error.
		</para>

<pre>
($tname, $message) = Triceps::App::getAborted($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the App abort information: name of the thread that caused the
		abort, and its error message.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::abortBy($appOrName, $tname, $msg);
</pre>

		<para>
		Abort the application. The thread name and message will be remembered,
		and returned later by <pre>getAborted()</pre> or in the harvester. If <pre>abortBy()</pre> is
		called multiple times, only the first pair of thread name and message
		gets remembered. The reason is that on abort all the threads get
		interrupted in a fairly rough manner (all their ongoing and following
		calls to the threading API die), which typically causes them to call
		<pre>abortBy()</pre> as well, and there is no point in collecting these spurious
		messages.
		</para>

		<para>
		The thread name here doesn't have to be the name of the actual thread
		that reports the issue. For example, if the thread creation as such
		fails (maybe because of the OS limit on the thread count) that gets
		detected by the parent thread but reported in the name of the thread
		whose creation has failed. And in general you can pass just any string
		as the thread name, App itself doesn't care, just make it something
		that makes sense to you.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::waitDead($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Will wait for the App to become dead and return after that. Make sure
		to not call <pre>waitDead()</pre> from any of App's Trieads: that would cause a
		deadlock.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::shutdown($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Shut down the App. The shutdown state is sticky, so any repeated calls
		will have no effect. The call returns immediately and doesn't wait for
		the App to die. If you want to wait, call <pre>waitDead()</pre> afterwards. Make
		sure to not call <pre>waitDead()</pre> from a Triead: that would cause a deadlock.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::shutdownFragment($appOrName, $fragName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Shut down a named fragment. This does not shut down the whole App, it
		just selectively shuts down the Trieads belonging to this fragment.
		See the explanation of the fragments in
		<xref linkend="sc_mt_dynamic_server" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		The fragment shutdown is not sticky: after a fragment has been shut
		down, it's possible to create another fragment with the same name. To
		avoid races, a fragment may be shut down only after all its Trieads are
		ready. So the caller Triead must call <pre>readyReady()</pre> before it calls
		<pre>shutdownFragment()</pre>. If any of the fragment's Trieads are not ready, the
		call will confess.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="sc_ref_app_drain">
		<title>App drain control</title>

		<para>
		The next few methods have to do with the drains. Generally, using the
		AutoDrain class to automatically limit the scope of the drains is a
		better idea. But if the automatic scoping is not desired, the App
		methods can be used directly.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::requestDrain($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Request a shared drain. Does not wait for the drain to complete. This
		method may be called repeatedly, potentially from multiple threads,
		which will keep the drain active and increase the recursion count. The
		drain will be released when <pre>undrain()</pre> is called the matching number of
		times.
		</para>

		<para>
		If an exclusive drain by another thread is active when <pre>requestDrain()</pre>
		is called, the call will be stuck until the exclusive drain becomes
		released (and potentially more exclusive drains might be queued up
		before the shared drain, using the POSIX read-write-lock
		implementation). Otherwise the call will set the appropriate state and
		return immediately.
		</para>

		<para>
		If this thread has requested an exclusive drain previously (and didn't
		release it yet), an attempt to get a shared drain in the same thread
		will likely deadlock. The same applies in the opposite order as well.
		</para>

		<para>
		Once the shared drain is requested, the input-only threads will be
		blocked from sending more data (any their attempts to flush their write
		facets will get stuck until release), and the rest of the threads will
		continue churning through the data buffered in the nexuses until all
		the nexuses are empty and there is no more data to process (yes, these
		threads will continue writing to their write facets).
		</para>

		<para>
		It is important to not request a shared drain from an input-only thread
		and then try to write more data into an output facet, that would
		deadlock. The whole concept is doable, but an exclusive drain must be
		used instead (<quote>exclusive</quote> means that a designated input-only thread is
		excluded from blocking).
		</para>

		<para>
		If the new Trieads are
		created while a drain is active, these Trieads will be notified of the
		drain. This means that the input-only Trieads won't be able to send any
		data until the drain is released. However the Trieads in the middle of
		the model will follow the normal protocol for such threads: the drain
		will become incomplete after the Triead is marked as ready and until it
		blocks on the following <pre>TrieadOwner::nextXtray()</pre>. Normally this should be a very
		short amount of time. However such Trieads should take care to 
		check <pre>TrieadOwner::isRdDrain()</pre> and never
		send any rowops on their own before reading from <pre>nextXtray()</pre> if they
		find that <pre>isRdDrain()</pre> returns true. Otherwise they may
		introduce the data into the model at a very inconvenient moment, when
		some logic expects that no data is changing, and cause a corruption.
		This is the same caveat as for using <pre>nextXtray()</pre> varieties with the
		timeouts: if you want to send data on a timeout, always check
		<pre>isRqDrain()</pre>, and never send any data on timeouts if <pre>isRqDrain()</pre> returns
		true.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::waitDrain($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Wait for the requested shared drain to complete. This means that all
		the queues in all the nexuses have become empty.
		</para>

		<para>
		The effect of <pre>waitDrain()</pre> without a preceding <pre>requestDrain()</pre> is
		undefined. If you definitely know that some other thread has requested
		a drain and didn't release yet, it will work as normal, so you can have
		any number of threads wait for drain in parallel. (And the semantics,
		shared or exclusive, will match that currently active request). If no
		thread requested a drain, it might either return immediately
		irrespective of the state of the nexuses or might wait for some other
		thread to request a drain and succeed.
		</para>

		<para>
		This call may also be used with an exclusive (or shared) drain
		requested through a TrieadOwner or any drain requested through an
		AutoDrain (though a better style is to use the same object as used for
		requesting the drain).
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::drain($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		A combination of <pre>requestDrain()</pre> and <pre>waitDrain()</pre> in one call.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::undrain($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Release the drain and let the normal processing continue. Make sure to
		call it exactly the same number of times as the <pre>requestDrain()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		This call may also be used with a drain requested through a TrieadOwner
		(though a better style is to use the same object as used for requesting
		the drain).
		</para>

<pre>
$result = Triceps::App::isDrained($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the App is currently drained (i.e. all the nexuses are
		empty), without waiting for it. Returns 1 if drained, 0 if not. If no
		drain is active during this call, the result is undefined, not even in
		the <quote>best effort</quote> sense: it may return 1 even if there are millions of
		records queued up. The only reliable way is to request a drain first.
		</para>

		<para>
		This call may also be used with a drain requested through a TrieadOwner
		or through an AutoDrain.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="sc_ref_app_start_timeout">
		<title>App start timeout</title>

		<para>
		Even though Triceps is quite eager in
		watching for deadlocks in the threads topology, it's still possible to
		get some threads, and with them the whole program, stuck during
		initialization. For example, if you declare a thread and then never
		define it. These situations are very unpleasant because you start the
		program and expect it to work but it doesn't, without any indication to
		why. So Triceps imposes an initialization timeout. The App (and thus
		all its threads) must become ready within the timeout after the
		definition or declaration of the last Triead. If not, the App will be
		aborted (and the error message will tell, which thread did not
		initialize in time). The same applies to the creation of Trieads
		(usually in the fragments) after the App is already running: all the
		threads must become ready within the timeout since the last thread has
		been defined or declared.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::setTimeout($appOrName, $main_to_sec);
Triceps::App::setTimeout($appOrName, $main_to_sec, $frag_to_sec);
</pre>

		<para>
		Set the readiness timeout.
		</para>

		<para>
		The default timeout is 30 seconds, or symbolically
		</para>

<pre>
&Triceps::App::DEFAULT_TIMEOUT
</pre>

		<para>
		(subject to possible changes of the exact value in the future).
		</para>

		<para>
		But the timeout can be changed. Technically, there are two timeouts:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			one starts when the App is created
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			one restarts when any Triead is defined or declared
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		For the App to be aborted, both timeouts must expire. By default they
		are set to the same length, so only the second timeout really matters,
		since it will always be the last one to start and last one to end. But
		if you set the first timeout to be longer, you can allow for a longer
		initialization period at the App start (<quote>main timeout</quote>) than later when
		more threads are added to a running App (<quote>fragment timeout</quote>, since the
		threads added later are typically the threads in fragments).
		</para>

		<para>
		The one-argument form of <pre>setTimeout()</pre> sets both timeouts to the same
		value, the two-argument form sets these timeouts separately.
		</para>

		<para>
		The timeouts may be set only before the first thread has been created.
		This is largely due to the historical reasons of implementation, with
		the current implementation it should actually be safe to allow changing
		the timeouts at a later point as well, and this limitation may be
		removed in the future.
		</para>

		<para>
		The timeout values are represented as integer whole seconds.
		</para>

		<para>
		Note that it's still possible to get the initialization stuck without
		any indication if it gets stuck in the other libraries. The reason is
		that the harvester waits for all the threads to be joined before it
		propagates the error, so if a thread doesn't get aborted properly
		and doesn't get joined, the harvester
		will be stuck. For example, if you open a file on NFS as a part of
		Triead initialization, and the NFS server doesn't respond, this thread
		will be stuck for a long time if not forever. The App will detect a
		timeout and try to interrupt the threads but the NFS operations are
		often not interruptable, so the harvester will wait for this thread to
		complete this operation and exit before it propagates the error, and
		thus the whole program will be silently stuck forever (and to avoid
		this, the NFS mounts should be done in the <quote>soft</quote> mode but it's a
		separate story). This will likely be improved in the future but it
		needs more thinking about how to do it right.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::setDeadline($appOrName, $deadline_sec);
</pre>

		<para>
		Set the <quote>main</quote> timeout in the form of an absolute deadline. This is
		actually closer to the way it works internally: the limit is expressed
		as a deadline, and <pre>setTimeout()</pre> just adds the timeout value to the
		current time to compute the deadline, while <pre>setDeadline()</pre> sets it
		straight. Like <pre>setTimeout()</pre>, this may be called only before any Trieads
		were created.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>now</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The time is represented as floating-point seconds since epoch.
		<pre>Triceps::now()</pre> can be used to get the current time with the fractional
		seconds (or if you don't care about the fractional seconds, you can
		always use the stock <pre>time()</pre>).
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::refreshDeadline($appOrName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Restart the <quote>fragment</quote> timeout. Same as when a Triead is defined or
		declared, only without involving a Triead. 
		This method can be called at any time.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="sc_ref_app_fd">
		<title>File descriptor transfer through an App</title>

		<para>
		Perl doesn't allow the sharing or transfers of the file handles
		between the threads. So Triceps works around this limitation
		by passing the underlying file descriptors through the App.
		After that the receiving Triead may construct a new file
		handle from the descriptor.
		</para>

		<para>
		The concepts are described in detail in
		<xref linkend="sc_mt_files" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;,
		this is just a short reference. This API works under the hood
		of <pre>TrieadOwner::trackGetFile()</pre> and friends
		but can also be used directly.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::storeFd($appOrName, $name, $fd, $fileClassName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Store a file descriptor in the App object, allowing to load it into
		other threads, and thus pass it around between the threads. $name is
		the name for this descriptor that will later be used to get the file
		descriptor back (generally, you want to generate a unique name for each
		file descriptor stored to avoid confusion, and then pass this name to
		the target thread). <pre>$fd</pre> is the file descriptor, an integer number,
		normally received from <pre>fileno()</pre>. The file descriptor is dupped before
		it gets stored, so the original will continue to exist, and if you have
		no other use for it, you should close it. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The <pre>$fileClassName</pre> allows to pass through the information
		about the class of the Perl file handle (such as IO::Handle or
		IO::Socket::INET) that owned this descriptor originally, and re-create
		the correct object later when loading the descriptor back. It's a plain
		string, and an empty string can be used for the plain files.
		</para>

		<para>
		If a file descriptor with this name already exists in the App, this
		call will confess.
		</para>

<pre>
($fd, $fileClassName) = Triceps::App::loadFd($appOrName, $name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Load back the file descriptor that was previously stored. The file handle
		class name is loaded back along with it.  If no
		descriptor with such a name is stored in the App, it will confess. The
		descriptor will keep existing in the App, so to keep things consistent,
		there are two options:
		</para>

		<para>
		One is to let your code take over the ownership of the file descriptor,
		and tell the App to forget about it with <pre>forgetFd()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The other one is to never close the received descriptor in your code (a
		good example would be to dup it right away for the future use and then
		leave the original alone), and let App keep its ownership.
		</para>

<pre>
($fd, $fileClassName) = Triceps::App::loadDupFd($appOrName, $name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Very much the same as <pre>loadFd()</pre>, only does the dupping for you and
		returns the dupped descriptor. In this case your code is responsible
		for closing that descriptor. Which method is more suitable, <pre>loadFd()</pre> or
		<pre>loadDupFd()</pre>, depends on the nature of the code that will use the file
		descriptor and whether you want to leave the descriptor in the App for
		more threads to load.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::forgetFd($appOrName, $name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Forget the file descriptor in the App. It doesn't get closed, so
		closing it becomes your responsibility, or it will leak. If no
		descriptor with this name exists, the call will confess.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::closeFd($appOrName, $name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Close and forget the file descriptor in the App. If no descriptor with
		this name exists, the call will confess.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::storeFile($appOrName, $name, FILE);
</pre>

		<para>
		A convenience wrapper for <pre>closeFd()</pre>, calls <pre>fileno()</pre> on the file and
		stores the resulting file descriptor. The name of the class of the
		file handle is stored along with the descriptor.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::storeCloseFile($appOrName, $name, FILE);
</pre>

		<para>
		Stores the file descriptor extracted from the file, and closes the
		original file (since the file descriptor gets dupped on store, that
		copy continues to exist in the App).
		</para>

<pre>
$file = Triceps::App::loadDupFile($appOrName, $name, $mode);
</pre>

		<para>
		Load a file descriptor and build a file handle object from it,
		using the stored file handle class name.
		The mode string may be specified in either the <pre>open()</pre> format
		(<pre></>/>>/+</+>/+>></pre>) or the C stdio format (<pre>r/w/a/r+/w+/a+</pre>). Note that
		the mode must match or be a subset of the mode used to originally open
		the file descriptor. If you open a file read-only, store its
		descriptor, and load back as a write-only file, you will have a bad
		time.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is no corresponding <pre>loadFile()</pre>, since <pre>loadFd()</pre> is a more
		dangerous method that is useful for the low-level operations but
		doesn't make much sense for the higher level.
		</para>

<pre>
$file = Triceps::App::loadDupFileClass($appOrName, $name, $mode, $fileClassName);
</pre>

		<para>
		Load a file descriptor and build an arbitrary handle object from it,
		overriding the stored class name. The
		class (specified by its name) should normally be a subclass of
		IO::Handle, or at the very least must implement the method
		<pre>new_from_fd()</pre> similar to IO::Handle.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="sc_ref_app_build">
		<title>App build</title>
		<para>
		There are multiple ways to build an App:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			Create the App manually with <pre>App::make()</pre>, then manually
			create its Trieads and start the harvester. To wait for the app
			completion, wait for the harvester thread to exit.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			Create the App with <pre>App::build()</pre>, as described below.
			The Trieads get constructed from the function that is passed as an
			argument to <pre>build()</pre>. After running the thread construction,
			<pre>build()</pre> runs the harvester automatically, and returns after the harvester
			exits. 
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			Create the App with <pre>Triead::startHere()</pre>. It's very much like
			<pre>App::build()</pre>, except that the code started from it is an
			actual Triead, running in the context of the current thread. This is
			convenient for running the short-lived Apps that get started, run for 
			a short time and then need to return the results back to the calling
			thread. The harvester also runs automatically by <pre>Triead::startHere()</pre>
			but only after the the <quote>main</quote> Triead exits.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

<pre>
Triceps::App::build($name, $builder);
</pre>

		<para>
		Build an App instance. It creates the App instance, then the builder
		function is called to create the App's nexuses and threads, then the
		harvester is executed, that eventually destroys the App object after
		collecting all its threads. For a very basic example:
		</para>

<!-- t/App.t -->
<pre>
Triceps::App::build "a1", sub {
	Triceps::App::globalNexus(
		name => "types",
		rowTypes => [
			rt1 => $rt1,
		],
	);
	Triceps::Triead::start(
		app => $Triceps::App::name,
		thread => "t1",
		main => sub {
			my $opts = {};
			&Triceps::Opt::parse("t1 main", $opts, {@Triceps::Triead::opts}, @_);
			my $to = $opts->{owner};
			$to->importNexus(
				from => "global/types",
				import => "writer", # if importing just for the types, use "writer"!
			);
			$to->readyReady();
		},
	);
};
</pre>

		<para>
		The builder function runs in the current Perl thread, however from the
		logical standpoint it runs in the App's first Triead named <quote>global</quote>
		(this Triead name is hardcoded in <pre>build()</pre>). This frees you from the
		worry about the App being technically dead until the first Triead is
		created: by the time the builder function is called, the first Triead
		is already created. However it also means that you can't change the
		readiness timeouts. After the builder function returns, the global
		Triead exits, and the harvester starts in the same current Perl thread.
		</para>

		<para>
		The builder has access to a few global variables:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<pre>$Triceps::App::name</pre> is the App name, from the <pre>build()</pre> first argument.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			<pre>$Triceps::App::app</pre> is the reference to the App object.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			<pre>$Triceps::App::global</pre> is the reference to the TrieadOwner object of the global Triead.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		After the builder function exits, these variables become undefined.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::App::globalNexus(@nexusOptions);
</pre>

		<para>
		Creates a nexus with the import mode of <quote>none</quote>, on the global Triead.
		The arguments are the same options as for the normal nexus creation.
		This is a simple convenience wrapper for the nexus creation. Since the
		global thread is supposed to exit immediately, there is no point in
		importing this nexus into it.
		</para>

		<para>
		The global thread is found by this function from <pre>$Triceps::App::global</pre>,
		so this method can only be used from inside the builder function of
		<pre>build()</pre>. 
		</para>
	</sect2>
	</sect1>
