<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_triead">
		<title>Triead reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Triead</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The Triead class is the public interface of a Triceps thread, i.e. what
		of it is visible to the other threads. It's intended pretty much for
		introspection only, and all its method are only for reading the state.
		They are all synchronized, but of course the thread may change its state
		at any moment. The Triead objects can be obtained by calling
		<pre>App::getTrieads()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The class also contains some static methods that are used to construct
		the Trieads.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $t->same($t2);
</pre>

		<para>
		Check that two Triead references point to the same Triead object.
		</para>

<pre>
$name = $t->getName();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the Triead's name.
		</para>

<pre>
$fragment = $t->fragment();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the name of the Triead's fragment. If the Triead doesn't belong to
		a fragment, returns an empty string <quote></quote>.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $t->isConstructed();
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the Triead has been constructed. For the explanation of
		the Triead lifecycle states, see
		<xref linkend="sc_mt_triead_life" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $t->isReady();
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the Triead is ready.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $t->isDead();
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the Triead is dead.
		</para>

<pre>
$result = $t->isInputOnly();
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the Triead is input-only, that is, it has no reader nexuses
		imported into it. When the Triead is created, this flag starts its life
		as <pre>false</pre> (0 for Perl), and then its correct value is computed when the
		Triead becomes ready. So, to check this flag correctly, you must first
		check that the Triead is ready.
		</para>

<pre>
@nexuses = $t->exports();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the list of nexuses exported from this Triead, as name-value
		pairs, suitable to be assigned into a hash. The values are the
		references to nexus objects.
		</para>

<pre>
@nexuses = $t->imports();
@nexuses = $t->readerImports();
@nexuses = $t->writerImports();
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the list of nexuses imported into this Triead, as name-value pairs.
		The <pre>imports()</pre> returns the full list, without the ability to tell, which
		nexuses are imported for reading and which for writing, while
		<pre>readImports()</pre> and <pre>writeImports()</pre> return these subsets separately.
		</para>

		<para>
		The names here are the <quote>as-names</quote> used for the import (the full names
		of the Nexuses can be obtained from the Nexus objects). The values are
		the references to nexus objects.
		</para>

		<para>
		The next part of the API is the static construction methods. They
		really are wrappers of the TrieadOwner methods but Triead is a shorter
		name, and thus more convenient.
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::Triead::start(@options);
</pre>

		<para>
		Start a new Triead in a new Perl thread. The options are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>app => $appname</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Name of the App that owns the new Triead. The App object will be
			looked up by name for the actual construction.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>thread => $threadname</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Name of the new Triead.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>fragment => $fragname</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Name of the new Triead's fragment. Optional. Default: <quote></quote>, which means no
			fragment.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>immed => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Flag: when the new thread imports its nexuses, it should import
			them in the immediate mode. This flag is purely advisory, and the
			thread's main function is free to use or ignore it depending on its
			logic. It's provided as a convenience, since it's a typical concern
			for the helper threads. Optional. Default: 0.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>main => $code</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			The main function of the thread that will be called with all the
			options of <pre>start()</pre> plus some more:
			</para>

<pre>
&$func(@opts, owner => $ownerObj)
</pre>

			<para>
			The extra option of the main is:
			</para>

			<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><pre>owner => $ownerObj</pre></term>
				<listitem>
				The TrieadOwner object constructed for this thread, through which
				its state can be controlled.
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>

			<para>
			Also, any other options may be added, and they will be forwarded to the
			main function without parsing. The main function is then free to parse
			them by itself, and if it finds any unknown options, it will fail.
			</para>

			<para>
			For the convenience of writing the main functions, the set of
			<quote>standard</quote> options is provided in the global variable
			</para>

<pre>
@Triceps::Triead::opts
</pre>

			<para>
			The main function then uses this variable as a preamble for any of
			its own options, for example:
			</para>

<pre>
sub listenerT          
{
    my $opts = {}; 
    &Triceps::Opt::parse("listenerT", $opts, {@Triceps::Triead::opts,
        socketName => [ undef, \&Triceps::Opt::ck_mandatory ],
    }, @_);
    ...
}
</pre>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>
		Another convenience method is:
		</para>

<pre>
Triceps::Triead::startHere(@options);
</pre>

		<para>
		It's very much the same as <pre>start()</pre> but starts the Triead in the current
		Perl thread. It's intended for the short-lived Apps that perform some
		computation and then have to return the result into the original
		thread. The unit tests are a good example of such apps.
		</para>

		<para>
		And because of the typical usage, this method has some extra
		functionality compared to the plain <pre>start()</pre>: unless told otherwise, it
		will first create the App (with the name specified by the option
		<quote>app</quote>), then construct and run it, and after the main function of this
		thread exits, run the harvester and drop the App. So it just does the
		whole package, similar to <pre>App::build()</pre>, only typically the Triead
		started here runs as a normal real Triead, collects the results of
		computations and places them into some variables (global or referenced
		by the user-specific options of the main function).
		</para>

		<para>
		This extra functionality can be disabled by the additional options
		(disable by setting them to 0):
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>harvest => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			After the main function exits, automatically run the harvesrer. If
			you set it to 0, don't forget to call the harvester after this
			function returns. Optional. Default: 1.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term><pre>makeApp => 0/1</pre></term>
			<listitem>
			Before doing anything, create the App.  Obviously, this App must
			not exist yet. Optional. Default: 1.
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>
		These options are not passed through to the main function, unlike all
		the others. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
