<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_ref_autodrain" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
		<title>AutoDrain reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>AutoDrain</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The AutoDrain class creates the drains on an App with the automatic
		scoping. When the returned AutoDrain object gets destroyed, the drain
		becomes released. So placing the object into a lexically-scoped
		variable in a block with cause the release on the block exit. Placing
		it into another object will cause the release on deletion of that
		object. And just not storing the object anywhere works as a barrier:
		the drain gets completed and then immediately released, guaranteeing
		that all the previously sent data is processed and then continuing with
		the processing of the new data.
		</para>

		<para>
		All the drain caveats described in the App class apply to the automatic
		drains too.
		</para>

<pre>
$ad = Triceps::AutoDrain::makeShared($app);
$ad = Triceps::AutoDrain::makeShared($to);
</pre>

		<para>
		Create a shared drain and wait for it to complete. A drain may be
		created from either an App or a TrieadOwner object. Returns the
		AutoDrain object.
		</para>

<pre>
$ad = Triceps::AutoDrain::makeSharedNoWait($app);
$ad = Triceps::AutoDrain::makeSharedNoWait($to);
</pre>

		<para>
		Same as <pre>makeShared()</pre> but doesn't wait for the drain to complete before
		returning. May still sleep if an exclusive drain is currently active.
		</para>

<pre>
$ad = Triceps::AutoDrain::makeExclusive($to);
</pre>

		<para>
		Create an exclusive drain on a TrieadOwner and wait for it to complete.
		Returns the AutoDrain object. Normally the excluded thread (the current one,
		idendified by the TrieadOwner) should be
		input-only. Such an input-only thread is allowed to send more data in
		without blocking. To wait for the app become drained again after that,
		use the method <pre>wait()</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
$ad = Triceps::AutoDrain::makeExclusiveNoWait($to);
</pre>

		<para>
		Same as <pre>makeExclusive()</pre> but doesn't wait for the drain to complete
		before returning. May still sleep if a shared or another exclusive
		drain is currently active.
		</para>

<pre>
$ad->wait();
</pre>

		<para>
		Wait for the drain to complete. Particularly useful after the <pre>NoWait</pre>
		creation, but can also be used to wait for the App to become drained
		again after injecting some rowops through the excluded Triead of the
		exclusive drain.
		</para>

<pre>
$ad->same($ad2);
</pre>

		<para>
		Check that two AutoDrain references point to the same object. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
