<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

<chapter id="ch_cpp_ref" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Triceps &Cpp; API Reference</title>

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_intro">
		<title>&Cpp; API Introduction</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>C++</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Fundamentally, the &Cpp; and Perl APIs are shaped similarly. So I won't
		be making a version of all the examples in &Cpp;. Please read the
		Perl-based documentation first to understand the spirit and usage of
		Triceps. The &Cpp;-based documentation is more of the reference type and
		concentrates on the low-level specifics and differences from Perl
		necessitated by this specifics.
		</para>

		<para>
		In many cases just reading the descriptions of the methods in the <pre>.h</pre>
		files should be enough to understand the details and be able to use the
		API. However in some cases the class hierarchies differ, with the Perl
		API covering the complexities exposed in the &Cpp; API.
		</para>

		<para>
		Writing directly in &Cpp; is significantly harder than in Perl, so I
		highly recommend sticking with the Perl API unless you have a good
		reason to do otherwise. Even when the performance is important, it's
		usually enough to write a few critical elements in &Cpp; and then bind
		them together in Perl. (If you wonder about Java, and why I didn't use
		it instead, the answer is that Java successfully combines the drawbacks
		of both and adds some of its own).
		</para>

		<para>
		The &Cpp; Triceps API is much more sensitive to the errors. The Perl API
		checks all the arguments for consistency, it's principle is that the
		interpreter must never crash. The &Cpp; API is geared towards the
		efficiency of execution. It checks for errors when constructing the
		major elements but then does almost no checks at run time. The
		expectation is that the caller knows what he is doing. If the caller
		sends bad data, mislays the pointers etc., the program will crash. The
		idea here is that most likely the &Cpp; API will be used from another
		layer: either an interpreted one (like Perl) or a compiled one (like a
		possible future custom language). Either way that layer is responsible
		for detecting the user errors at either interpretation or compile time.
		By the time the data gets to the &Cpp; code, it's already checked and
		there is no need to check it again. Of course, if you write the
		programs manually in &Cpp;, that checking is upon you.
		</para>

		<para>
		The more high-level features are currently available only in Perl. For
		example, there are no joins in the &Cpp; API. If you want to do the joins
		in &Cpp;, you have to code your own. This will change over time, as these
		features will solidify and move to a &Cpp; implementation to become more
		efficient and available through all the APIs. But it's much easier to
		experiment with the initial implementations in Perl.
		</para>

		<para>
		The &Cpp; code is located in the <pre>cpp/</pre> subdirectory, and all
		the further descriptions refer to the subdirectories under it.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_const">
		<title>The const-ness in &Cpp;</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>const</primary>
		</indexterm>

		<para>
		I've been using the <pre>const</pre> keyword for two purposes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			To let the compiler optimize a little better the methods that do not
			change the state of the objects.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			To mark the fragments of the read-only object internal state returned
			by the methods. This is much more efficient than making copies of them.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		So if you get a <pre>const vector<> &</pre> returned from a method, this is a
		gentle reminder that you should not be modifying this vector. Of
		course, nothing can stop a determined programmer from doing a type cast
		and modifying it anyway, but be aware that such inconsistent
		modifications will likely cause the program to crash in the future. And
		if the vector contains references to other objects, these objects
		usually should not be modified either, even they might not be marked
		with const.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>const_iterator</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		However all this <pre>const</pre> stuff is not all rainbows and unicorns but also
		produces a sizable amount of suffering. One consequence is that you can
		not use the normal iterators on the <pre>const</pre> vectors, you have to use the
		const_iterators. Another is that once in a while you get something like
		a <pre>(const RowType *)</pre> from one method and need to pass it as an argument
		to another method that takes a <pre>(RowType *)</pre>. In this case make sure that
		you know what you are doing and then proceed boldly with using a
		<pre>const_cast</pre>. There is just no way to get all the const-ness
		self-consistent without ripping it out altogether. 
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/810autoref.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/811copy.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/812string.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/813perl.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/814errors.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/816exception.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/817init.xml"/>

	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/818types.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/81801simple.xml"/>

	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/820rowtype.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/822row.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/824tabtype.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/826nameset.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/828idxtype.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/829idx.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/830fifoidx.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/832hashidx.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/834sortidx.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/840gadget.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/842table.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/844rowhandle.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/848agg.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/850unit.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/852tracer.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/854label.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/856rowop.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/858tray.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/860fmark.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/862rowset.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/864fnreturn.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/866fnbind.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/868autofn.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/880app.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/882triead.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/884towner.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/886nexus.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/888facet.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/890autodrain.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/892sigusr2.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/894tjoin.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/896fileint.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="file:///DOCS/898basicpt.xml"/>

</chapter>
