<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_mem">
		<title>Memory management in the &Cpp; API and the Autoref reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>memory management</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The memory management fundamentals have been described in
		<xref linkend="sc_memory_fund" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;,
		and the application-level considerations have been descibed in
		<xref linkend="ch_memory" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		This section goes deeper into the issues specific to the &Cpp; API.
		</para>

		<para>
		The code related to the memory management is generally collected under <pre>mem/</pre>. 
		The memory management is done through the reference counting, which has two parts to it:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			The objects that can be managed by reference counting.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			The references that do the counting.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>AtomicInt</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>NSPR</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The managed objects come in two varieties: single-threaded and
		multi-threaded. The single-threaded objects lead their whole life in a
		single thread, so their reference counts don't need locking. The
		multi-threaded objects can be shared by multiple threads, so their
		reference counts are kept thread-safe by using the atomic integers (if
		the NSPR library is available) or by using a lock (if NSPR is not
		used). That whole implementation of atomic data with or without NSPR is
		encapsulated in the class AtomicInt in <pre>mem/Atomic.h</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The way a class selects whether it will be single-threaded or
		multi-threaded is by inheriting from the appropriate class:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Starget</term>
				<listitem>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Starget</primary>
		</indexterm>
				<para>
				for single-threaded (defined in <pre>mem/Starget.h</pre>).
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>Mtarget</term>
				<listitem>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Mtarget</primary>
		</indexterm>
				<para>
				for multi-threaded (defined in <pre>mem/Mtarget.h</pre>).
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>
		If you do the multiple inheritance, the [SM]target has to be inherited
		only once. Also, you can't change the choice along the inheritance
		chain. Once chosen, you're stuck with it. The only way around it is by
		encapsulating that inner class's object instead of inheriting from it.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Autoref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The references are created with the template <pre>Autoref<></pre>, defined in
		<pre>mem/Autoref.h</pre>. For example, if you have an object of class RowType, the
		reference to it will be <pre>Autoref<RowType></pre>. There are are some similar
		references in the Boost library, but I prefer to avoid the avoidable
		dependencies (and anyway, I've never used Boost much).
		</para>

		<para>
		The target objects are created in the constructors with the reference
		count of 0. The first time the object pointer is assigned to an
		Autoref, the count goes up to 1. After that it stays above 0 for the
		whole life of the object. As soon as it goes back to 0 (meaning that
		the last reference to it has disappeared), the object gets destroyed. No
		locks are held during the destruction itself. After all the references
		are gone, nobody should be using it, and destroying it is safe without
		any extra locks.
		</para>

		<para>
		Starget and Mtarget are independent classes but Autoref 
		can work transparently on both of them because Autoref
		doesn't modify the reference counters by itself. Instead the target
		class is expected to provide the methods 
		</para>

<pre>
void incref() const;
int decref() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		They are defined as const to allow the reference counting of even the
		const objects, but of course the reference counter field must be mutable.
		<pre>decref()</pre> returns the resulting counter value. When it goes down to 0,
		Autoref calls the destructor. 
		</para>

		<para>
		An important point is that to do all this, the Autoref must be able to
		execute the correct destructor when it destroys the object that ran out
		of references. Starget and Mtarget do not provide the virtual
		destructors. This allows to keep the reference-counted classes
		non-virtual, and save a little bit of memory in their objects,
		which might be important for the objects used in large numbers.
		If you don't use the polymorphism for some class, you
		don't have to use the virtual destructors. But if you do use it, i.e.
		create a class B inheriting from A, inheriting from [SM]target, and
		then assign something like
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<A> ref = new B;
</pre>

		<para>
		then the class A (and by extension all the classes inheriting from it)
		must have a virtual destructor to get everything working right.
		</para>

		<para>
		It's also possible to mess up the destruction with the use of pointers.
		For example, look at this sequence:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<RowType> rt = new RowType(...);
RowType *rtp = rt; // copies a reference to a pointer
rt = NULL; // reference cleared, count down to 0, object destroyed
Autoref <RowType> rt2 = rtp; // resurrects the dead pointer, corrupts memory
</pre>

		<para>
		The lesson here is that even though you can mix the references with
		pointers to reduce the overhead (the reference assignments change the
		reference counters, the pointer assignments don't), and I do it in my
		code, you need to be careful. A pointer may be used only when you know
		that there is a reference that holds the object in place. Once that
		reference is gone, the pointer can't be used any more, and especially
		can't be assigned to another reference. Be careful.
		</para>

		<para>
		There are more varieties of the Autoref template, also
		defined in <pre>mem/Autoref.h</pre>:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			Onceref
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			const_Autoref
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			const_Onceref
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Onceref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The Onceref is an attempt at optimization when passing the function
		arguments and results. It's supposed to work like the standard
		auto_ptr: you assign a value there once, and then when that value gets
		assigned to an Autoref or another Onceref, it moves to the new
		location, leaving the reference count unchanged and the original
		Onceref as NULL. This way you avoid a spurious extra increase-decrease.
		However in practice I haven't got around to implementing it yet, so for
		now it's a placeholder that is defined to be an alias of Autoref,
		and const_Onceref is an alias of const_Autoref.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>const_Autoref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>const_iterator</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		const_Autoref is a template defined over the Autoref template:
		</para>

<pre>
template <typename Target>
class const_Autoref : public Autoref<const Target>
</pre>

		<para>
		The const_Autoref is a reference to a constant object. As you can see,
		<pre>const_Autoref<T></pre> is equivalent to <pre>Autoref<const T></pre>, 
		only it handles the
		automatic type casts much better. The approach is patterned after the
		const_iterator. The only problem with const_Autoref is that when you
		try to assign a NULL to it, that blows the compiler's mind. So you have
		to write an explicit cast 
		of <pre>const_Autoref<T>::null()</pre> 
		or <pre>Autoref<T>::null()</pre> 
		or <pre>(T*)NULL</pre> of <pre>(const T*)NULL</pre> 
		to help it out. Either way would work as long as one or the other
		path for casting is selected (by default the compiler is
		confused by the presence of two possible paths).
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>const_Onceref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Finally, const_Onceref is the const version of Onceref. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The method prototypes of Autoref and all its varieties
		are (Target is the argument class of the
		Autoref template, Ptr is the pointer to it):
		</para>

<pre>
typedef Target *Ptr;
static Ptr null();
Autoref();
Autoref(Target *t);
Autoref(const Autoref &ar);
Autoref(const Autoref<OtherTarget> &ar);
Target &operator*() const;
Target *operator->() const;
Target *get() const;
operator Ptr() const; // type conversion to pointer
bool isNull() const;
Autoref &operator=(const Autoref &ar);
Autoref &operator=(const Autoref<OtherTarget> &ar);
bool operator==(const Autoref &ar);
bool operator!=(const Autoref &ar);
bool operator==(const Autoref<OtherTarget> &ar);
bool operator!=(const Autoref<OtherTarget> &ar);
void swap(Autoref &other);
</pre>

		<para>
		Since the typical usage might be hard to understand from the
		method prototypes, the examples follow.
		Autoref can be constructed with or assigned from another Autoref or a
		pointer, or with a NULL value:
		</para>

<pre>
T *ptr;
Autoref<T> ref1(ptr);
Autoref<T> ref2(ref1);
Autoref<T> ref3; // initialized as NULL by default
ref1 = ref2;
ref1 = ptr;
ref2 = NULL; // releases the reference
ref2 = Autoref<T>::null(); // another way to assign NULL
</pre>

		<para>
		The simple NULL usually works but there are cases with ambiguity,
		and the static method <pre>null()</pre> helps to create the NULL of the correct
		type and remove that ambiguity.
		</para>

		<para>
		The assignments work for exactly the same type and also for assignment
		to any parent in the class hierarchy:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<Label> = new DummyLabel(...);
</pre>

		<para>
		The automatic conversion to pointers works too:
		</para>

<pre>
ptr = ref1;
</pre>

		<para>
		Or a pointer can be extracted from an Autoref explicitly:
		</para>

<pre>
ptr = ref1.get();
</pre>

		<para>
		The dereferencing and arrow operations work like on a pointer:
		</para>

<pre>
T val = *ref1;
ref1->method();
</pre>

		<para>
		The Autorefs can also be compared for equality and inequality:
		</para>

<pre>
ref1 == ref2
ref1 != ref2
</pre>

		<para>
		To compare them to pointers, use <pre>get()</pre>. Except for one special case:
		the comparison to NULL happens so often that a special method is
		provided for it:
		</para>

<pre>
ref1.isNull()
</pre>

		<para>
		Two Autorefs may swap their values, without changing the reference
		counts of either value:
		</para>

<pre>
ref1.swap(ref2);
</pre>

		<para>
		There is also a special variety of Autoref for referring to rows,
		Rowref, described in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_row" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>
	</sect1>
