<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_copy">
		<title>The many ways to do a copy</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>memory management</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>copying</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The Triceps objects need occasionally to be copied. But as the objects
		are connected into the deep topologies, a question arises, how much of
		this topology needs to be copied along with the object?
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>IndexType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>TableType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The objects that are copied the most are the IndexType and TableType.
		The method <pre>copy()</pre>, in both Perl and &Cpp;, is the general way to copy them. 
		It copies the object, and as needed its
		components, but tries to share the referred objects that can be shared (such as
		the row types). But the multithreading support required more kinds of
		copying.
		</para>

		<para>
		The Perl method <pre>TableType::copyFundamental()</pre> copies a table type with
		only a limited subset of its index types, and excludes all the
		aggregators. It is implemented in Perl, and if you look in
		<pre>lib/Triceps/TableType.pm</pre>, you can find that it starts by making a new
		table type with the same row type, and then one by one adds the needed
		index types to it. It needs the index types without any aggregators or
		nested index types, and thus there is a special method for doing this
		kind of copies:
		</para>

<pre>
$idxtype2 = $idxtype->flatCopy();
</pre>

		<para>
		The <quote>flat</quote> means exactly what it looks like: copy just the object
		itself without any connected hierarchies.
		</para>

		<para>
		On the &Cpp; level there is no such method, instead there is an optional
		argument to <pre>IndexType::copy()</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual IndexType *copy(bool flat = false) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		So if you want a flat copy, you call
		</para>

<pre>
idxtype2 = idxtype->copy(true);
</pre>

		<para>
		There is no <pre>copyFundamental()</pre> on the &Cpp; level, though it probably
		should be, and should be added in the future. For now, if you really
		want it, you can make it yourself by copying the logic from Perl.
		</para>

		<para>
		In the implementation of the index types, this argument <pre>flat</pre> mostly
		just propagates to the base class, without a whole lot needed from the
		subclass. For example, this is how it works in the SortedIndexType:
		</para>

<!-- cpp/type/SortedIndexType.cpp -->
<pre>
IndexType *SortedIndexType::copy(bool flat) const
{
	return new SortedIndexType(*this, flat);
}

SortedIndexType::SortedIndexType(const SortedIndexType &orig, bool flat) :
	TreeIndexType(orig, flat),
	sc_(orig.sc_->copy())
{ }
</pre>

		<para>
		The base class TreeIndexType takes care of everything, all the subclass
		needs to do is carry the flat argument to it.
		</para>

		<para>
		The next kind of copying is exactly the opposite: it copies the whole
		table type or index type, including all the objects involved, including
		the row types or such. It is used for passing the table types through
		the nexus to the other threads.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>multithreading</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Remember that all these objects are reference-counted. Whenever a Row
		object is created or deleted in Perl, it increases or decreases the
		reference of the RowType to which that row belongs. 
		If the same RowType object is shared between
		multiple threads, they will have  a contention for this atomic counter,
		or at the very least will be shuttling the cache line with it back and
		forth between the CPUs. It's more efficient to give each thread its own
		copy of a RowType, and then it can stay stuck in one CPU's cache.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Nexus</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Facet</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		So wherever a table type is exported into a nexus, it's deep-copied
		(and when a row type is exported into a nexus, it's simply copied, and
		so are the row types of the labels in the nexus). Then when a nexus is
		imported, the types are again deep-copied into the thread's facet.
		</para>

		<para>
		But there is one more catch. Suppose we have a label and a table type
		that use the same row type. Whenever a row coming from a label is
		inserted into the table (in Perl), the row types of the row (i.e. the
		label's row type in this case) and of the table are checked for a
		match. If the row type is the same, this check is very quick. But if
		the same row type gets copied and then different copies are used for
		the label and for the table, the check will have to go and actually
		compare the contents of these row types, and will be much slower. To
		prevent this slowness, the deep copy has to be smart: it must be able
		to copy a bunch of things while preserving the identity of the
		underlying row types. If it's given a label and then a table type, both
		referring to the same row type, it will copy the row type from the
		label, but then when copying the table type it will realize that this row type had
		already been seen and copied, so it will reuse the same row type copy for the table type.
		And the same applies even within a table type: it may have multiple
		references to the same row type from the aggregators, and will be smart
		enough to figure out if they are the same, and copy the same row type
		only once.
		</para>

		<para>
		This smartness stays mostly undercover in Perl. When you import a
		facet, it will do all the proper copying, sharing the row types.
		(Though of course if you export the same row type through two separate
		nexuses, and then import them both into another thread, these facets
		will not share the types between them any more). There is a method
		<pre>TableType::deepCopy()</pre> but it was mostly intended for testing and it's
		self-contained: it will copy one table type with the correct row type
		sharing inside it but it won't do the sharing between two table types.
		It's not even documented in the TableType reference.
		</para>

		<para>
		All the interesting uses of the <pre>deepCopy()</pre> are at the &Cpp; level. It's
		used all over the place: for the TableType, IndexType, AggregatorType,
		SortedIndexCondition and RowSetType (the type of FnReturn and
		FnBinding). If you decide to create your own subclass of these classes,
		you need to implement the <pre>deepCopy()</pre> as well as the normal <pre>copy()</pre>
		for it.
		</para>

		<para>
		Its prototype generally looks like this (substitute the correct return
		type as needed):
		</para>

<pre>
virtual IndexType *deepCopy(HoldRowTypes *holder) const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>HoldRowTypes</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The HoldRowTypes object is what takes care of sharing the underlying
		row types. To copy a bunch of objects with sharing, you create a
		HoldRowTypes, copy the bunch, destroy the HoldRowTypes.
		</para>

		<para>
		For example, the Facet copies the row and table types from a Nexus like this:
		</para>

<!-- cpp/app/Facet.cpp fragment -->
<pre>
Autoref<HoldRowTypes> holder = new HoldRowTypes;

for (RowTypeMap::iterator it = nx->rowTypes_.begin();
		it != nx->rowTypes_.end(); ++it)
	rowTypes_[it->first] = holder->copy(it->second);
for (TableTypeMap::iterator it = nx->tableTypes_.begin();
		it != nx->tableTypes_.end(); ++it)
	tableTypes_[it->first] = it->second->deepCopy(holder);
</pre>

		<para>
		It also uses the same holder to copy the labels.
		A row type gets copied through a holder like this:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<RowType> rt2 = holder->copy(rt);
</pre>

		<para>
		For all the other purposes, HoldRowTypes is an opaque object.
		</para>

		<para>
		A special feature is that you can pass the holder pointer as NULL, and
		the deep copy will still work, only it obviously won't be able to share
		the underlying row types. So if you don't care about sharing, you can
		always use NULL as an argument. It even works for the direct copying:
		</para>

<pre>
HoldRowTypes *holder = NULL;
Autoref <RowType> rt2 = holder->copy(rt);
</pre>

		<para>
		Its method <pre>copy()</pre> is smart enough to recognize the <pre>this</pre> being NULL and
		do the correct thing.
		</para>

		<para>
		In the subclasses, the <pre>deepCopy()</pre> is typically implemented like this:
		</para>

<!-- cpp/type/SortedIndexType.cpp -->
<pre>
IndexType *SortedIndexType::deepCopy(HoldRowTypes *holder) const
{
	return new SortedIndexType(*this, holder);
}

SortedIndexType::SortedIndexType(const SortedIndexType &orig, HoldRowTypes *holder) :
	TreeIndexType(orig, holder),
	sc_(orig.sc_->deepCopy(holder))
{ }
</pre>

		<para>
		The wrapper passes the call to the deep-copy constructor with a holder
		which in turn propagates the deep-copying to all the components using
		their constructor with a holder. Of course, if some component doesn't
		have any RowType references in it, it doesn't need a constructor with a
		holder, and can be copied without it. But again, the idea of the
		<pre>deepCopy()</pre> it to copy as deep as it goes, without sharing any
		references with the original. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
