<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_string">
		<title>String utilities</title>

		<para>
		Triceps has a number of small helper functions for string handling
		that are used throughout the code. This description includes a few
		forward references but you don't really need to understand them to
		understand these functions.
		</para>

		<para>
		The first two are declared in <pre>common/Strprintf.h</pre>:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>strprintf</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>vstrprintf</primary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
string strprintf(const char *fmt, ...);
string vstrprintf(const char *fmt, va_list ap);
</pre>

		<para>
		They are entirely similar to <pre>sprintf()</pre> and <pre>vsprintf()</pre> with the
		difference that they place the result of formatting into a newly
		constructed string and return that string.
		</para>

		<para>
		The rest are defined in <pre>common/StringUtil.h</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
extern const string &NOINDENT;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>NOINDENT</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Type</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The special constant that when passed to the printing of the Type
		(see
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_types" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;)
		causes it to print without line breaks. Doesn't have any special effect
		on Errors, there it's simply treated as an empty string.
		</para>

<pre>
const string &nextindent(const string &indent, const string &subindent, string &target);
</pre>

		<para>
		Compute the indentation for the next level when printing a Type. The
		arguments are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><pre>indent</pre></term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
				indent string of the current level.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><pre>subindent</pre></term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
				characters to append for the next indent level.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><pre>target</pre></term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
				buffer to store the extended indent string.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>
		The passing of <pre>target</pre> as an argument allows to reuse the same string
		object and avoid the extra construction.
		</para>

		<para>
		The function returns the computed reference: if <pre>indent</pre> was NOINDENT,
		then reference to NOINDENT, otherwise reference to <pre>target</pre>. This
		particular calling pattern is strongly tied to how things are computed
		inside the type printing, but you're welcome to look inside it and do
		the same for any other purpose.
		</para>

<pre>
void newlineTo(string &res, const string &indent);
</pre>

		<para>
		Another helper function for the printing of Type, inserting a line
		break. The <pre>indent</pre> argument specifies the indentation, with the special
		handling of NOINDENT: if <pre>indent</pre> is NOINDENT, a single space is added,
		thus printing everything in one line; otherwise a <quote>\n</quote> and the contents
		of <pre>indent</pre> are added. The <pre>res</pre> argument is the result string, where the
		line break characters are added.
		</para>

<pre>
void hexdump(string &dest, const void *bytes, size_t n, const char *indent = "");
</pre>

		<para>
		Print a hex dump of a sequence of bytes (at address <pre>bytes</pre> and of length
		<pre>n</pre>), appending the dump to the destination string <pre>dest</pre>. The data will be
		nicely broken into lines, with 16 bytes printed per line. The first
		line is added directly to the end of the <pre>dest</pre> as-is,  but if <pre>n</pre> is over
		16, the other lines will follow after <quote>\n</quote>. The <pre>indent</pre> argument allows to
		add indentation at the start of each following line.
		</para>

<pre>
void hexdump(FILE *dest, const void *bytes, size_t n, const char *indent = "");
</pre>

		<para>
		Another version, sending the dumped data directly into a file descriptor.
		</para>

		<para>
		The next pair of functions provides a generic mechanism for converting
		enums between a string and integer representation:
		</para>

<pre>
struct Valname
{
    int val_;
    const char *name_;
};

int string2enum(const Valname *reft, const char *name);
const char *enum2string(const Valname *reft, int val, const char *def = "???");
</pre>

		<para>
		The reference table is defined with an array of Valnames, with the
		last element being <pre>{ -1, NULL }</pre>. Then it's passed as the argument <pre>reft</pre>
		of the conversion functions which do a sequential look-up by that
		table. If the argument is not found, <pre>string2enum()</pre> will return -1, and
		<pre>enum2string()</pre> will return the value of the <pre>def</pre> argument (which may be
		NULL).
		</para>

		<para>
		Here is an example of how it's used for the conversion of opcode flags:
		</para>

<pre>
Valname opcodeFlags[] = {
    { Rowop::OCF_INSERT, "OCF_INSERT" },
    { Rowop::OCF_DELETE, "OCF_DELETE" },
    { -1, NULL }
};

const char *Rowop::ocfString(int flag, const char *def)
{
    return enum2string(opcodeFlags, flag, def);
}

int Rowop::stringOcf(const char *flag)
{
    return string2enum(opcodeFlags, flag);
}
</pre>
	</sect1>

