<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_perl">
		<title>Perl wrapping for the &Cpp; objects</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>wrapper</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The subject of this section is not a part of the &Cpp; API as such but the
		connection between the &Cpp; and Perl APIs. You need to bother about it
		only if you want to write more of the components in &Cpp; and export them into
		Perl.
		</para>

		<para>
		When exporting the &Cpp; (or any compiled language) API into Perl (or
		into any scripting language) there are two things to consider:
		</para>

		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
			The script must never crash the interpterer. The interpreted program
			might die but the interpreter itself must never crash. If you've ever
			dealt with <pre>wksh</pre> (not thankfully long dead), you know how
			horrible is the debugging of such crashes.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			Perl has its memory management by reference counting, which needs to
			be married with the memory management at the &Cpp; level.
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>
		The solution to the second problem is fairly straightforward: have an
		intermediate wrapper structure. Perl has its reference counting for the
		pointer to this structure.  When you construct a Perl object, return
		the pointer to a newly allocated instance of this structure. When the
		Perl reference count goes down to zero, it calls the method <pre>DESTROY</pre> for
		this object, and then you destroy this structure.
		</para>

		<para>
		And inside this structure will be the &Cpp; reference to the actual
		&Cpp; object. When the wrapper structure gets created, it gets a new
		reference and when the wrapper structure gets destroyed, it releases
		this reference.
		</para>

		<para>
		Here is a small example of how the RowType object gets created and
		destroyed in the Perl XS code, using the wrapper structure WrapRowType:
		</para>

<!-- RowType.xs, edited -->
<pre>
WrapRowType *
Triceps::RowType::new(...)
	CODE:
		RETVAL = NULL; // shut up the warning
		try { do {
			RowType::FieldVec fld;

			clearErrMsg();
			...
			Onceref<RowType> rt = new CompactRowType(fld);
			Erref err = rt->getErrors();
			if (err->hasError()) {
				throw Exception::f(err, "Triceps::RowType::new: incorrect data");
			}

			RETVAL = new WrapRowType(rt);
		} while(0); } TRICEPS_CATCH_CROAK;
	OUTPUT:
		RETVAL

void
DESTROY(WrapRowType *self)
	CODE:
		// warn("RowType destroyed!");
		delete self;
</pre>

		<para>
		This example also shows the way the Triceps XS code deals with the conversion
		of the &Cpp; Exceptions to the Perl confessions. The <pre>while(0)</pre> part
		is a hold-over from the earlier implementation of error handling that allows
		to set the error message directly in a buffer and then do a <pre>break</pre> to jump
		to the end of the pseudo-loop. The new way is the throwing of Exceptions.
		The shown code is a hybrid that handles both. The handling itself is done
		in the macro <pre>TRICEPS_CATCH_CROAK</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		Now let's look more in-depth at the first problem. How does Perl know to call a particular XS
		method for a object? From the package this object is blessed to. If the
		package happens to be an XS package, the XS method will be called.
		However it's entirely possible to re-bless the object to a completely
		different package. If the user does this, a completely wrong method may
		be called and will crash when it tries to reach a wrong object at the
		pointer.
		</para>

		<para>
		Things get even worse for the other arguments of the methods. For
		example, the argument <pre>other</pre> here:
		</para>

<pre>
int
equals(WrapRowType *self, WrapRowType *other)
</pre>

		<para>
		Well, Perl lets you provide a code snippet for the <pre>typemap</pre> file
		that would check that the object is as expected. But how would that snippet
		know? Going just by the blessed package is unreliable.
		</para>

		<para>
		Triceps solves this problem by placing an 8-byte magic code at the
		front of every wrap object. Each class has its own magic value for this
		field. 8 bytes allow to have great many unique codes, and is quick to
		check because it's just one CPU word.
		</para>

		<para>
		This magic code is defined  in the &Cpp; part in <pre>wrap/Wrap.h</pre> as:
		</para>

<!-- wrap/Wrap.h -->
<pre>
struct WrapMagic {
	~WrapMagic()
	{
		(*(int64_t *)v_) = 0; // makes sure that it gets invalidated
	}

	char v_[8]; // 8 bytes to make a single 64-bit comparison

	bool operator!=(const WrapMagic &wm) const
	{
		return (*(int64_t *)v_) != (*(int64_t *)wm.v_);
	}
};
</pre>

		<para>
		Then the wrapper is implemented as follows:
		</para>

<!-- wrap/Wrap.h -->
<pre>
template<const WrapMagic &magic, class Class>
class Wrap
{
public:
	Wrap(Onceref<Class> r) :
		magic_(magic),
		ref_(r)
	{ }

	// returns true if the magic value is bad
	bool badMagic() const
	{
		return magic_ != magic;
	}

	Class *get() const
	{
		return ref_.get();
	}

	operator Class*() const
	{
		return ref_.get();
	}

public:
	WrapMagic magic_;
	Autoref<Class> ref_; // referenced value
private:
	Wrap();
};
</pre>

		<para>
		The check is done with the method <pre>badMagic()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		And the <pre>typemap</pre> entry is:
		</para>

<pre>
O_WRAP_OBJECT
	if( sv_isobject($arg) && (SvTYPE(SvRV($arg)) == SVt_PVMG) ) {
		$var = ($type)SvIV((SV*)SvRV( $arg ));
		if ($var == 0 || $var->badMagic()) {
			croakWithMsg( \"${Package}::$func_name(): $var has an incorrect magic for $ntype\" );
		}
	} else{
		croakWithMsg( \"${Package}::$func_name(): $var is not a blessed SV reference to $ntype\" );
	}
</pre>

		<para>
		It checks that this is an object, of an XS package, and then that the
		pointer to the C/&Cpp; object is not NULL, and that the value at this
		pointer starts with the right magic.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>croakWithMsg()</pre> is the Triceps function for building the confession
		trace and then croaking with it.
		</para>

		<para>
		The template shown above is normally used through a macro that
		substitutes the repeated values from one source.
		For example,  the definition for the RowType wrapper
		is:
		</para>

<pre>
DEFINE_WRAP(RowType);
</pre>

		<para>
		The static definition of the magic code that the macro passes to the
		template is defined in <pre>wrap/Wrap.cpp</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
WrapMagic magicWrapRowType = { "RowType" };
</pre>

		<para>
		Just make sure that the string contains no more than 7 characters.
		</para>

		<para>
		Some objects in Triceps are reached through the special references that
		know both the object and its type (such as rows and row handles). For
		them there is a separate template and a separate macro:
		</para>

<pre>
DEFINE_WRAP2(const RowType, Rowref, Row);
DEFINE_WRAP2(Table, Rhref, RowHandle);
</pre>

		<para>
		The arguments are the type class, the reference class and finally the
		object class itself.
		</para>

		<para>
		And there is one more twist: sometimes the objects are self-contained
		but when you use them, you must use them only with a correct parent
		object. Right now there is only one such class: the Tray must be used
		with its correct Unit, and the Perl code checks it. In this case the
		wrapper has the reference to both Tray and the Unit, and is defined as:
		</para>

<pre>
DEFINE_WRAP_IDENT(Unit, Tray); 
</pre>

		<para>
		Triceps has a substantial library of helper methods and objects
		for wrappig the &Cpp; objects, located in the Perl part of the code.
		Many of them are located in <pre>TricepsPerl.h</pre>. Feel free
		to refer to them if you need to, but for now they are out of scope
		of the documentation.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>multithreading</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>XS</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Just one more thing: Perl is not happy about sharing the objects
		between multiple threads. Even when a &Cpp; object is OK with multithreading,
		Perl requires the separate wrappers to be created for it from each thread.
		When a new Perl thread is started, Perl can not properly ask the XS
		code to split the wrappers, so instead all the objects need to be invalidated
		in the new thread. To do that, the XS package needs to define the method
		<pre>CLONE_SKIP</pre>:
		</para>

<!-- RowType.xs -->
<pre>
int
CLONE_SKIP(...)
	CODE:
		RETVAL = 1;
	OUTPUT:
		RETVAL
</pre>

	</sect1>
