<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_errors">
		<title>Error reporting and Errors reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
			<secondary>in &Cpp;</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		When building some kind of a language, the complicated errors often
		need to be reported. Often there are many errors at a time, or an error
		that needs to be tracked through multiple nested layers. And then these
		error messages need to be nicely printed, with the indentation by
		nested layers. Think of the errors from a &Cpp; compiler. Triceps is a
		kind of a language, so it has a class to represent such errors. It
		hasn't propagated to the Perl layer yet and is available only in the
		&Cpp; API.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Errors</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Erref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Autoref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The class is Errors, defined in <pre>common/Errors.h</pre>, and inheriting from
		Starget (for single-threaded reference counting). The references to it
		are used so often, that <pre>Autoref<Errors></pre> is defined to have its own
		name <pre>Erref</pre> (yes, that's double <pre>r</pre>, not triple), as well as
		a couple of helper methods on it.
		</para>

		<para>
		Triceps also has the exceptions (more on them in 
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_exception" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;)
		which also contain the Errors objects inside them.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Aleri</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		In general an Errors object contains messages, not all of which have to be errors.
		Some might be warnings. But in practice is has turned out that without
		a special dedicated compile stage it's hard to report the warnings.
		Even when there is a special compile stage, and the code gets compiled
		before it runs, as it was in Aleri, with the warnings written to a log file,
		still people rarely pay attention to the warnings. You would not
		believe, how may people would be calling support while the source of
		their problem is clearly described in the warnings in the log file.
		Even in C/&Cpp; it's difficult to pay attention to the warnings. I better
		like the approach of a separate lint tool for this purpose: at least
		when you run it, you're definitely looking for warnings.
		</para>

		<para>
		Because of this, the current Triceps approach is to not have warnings.
		If something looks possibly right but suspicious, report it as an error
		but provide an option to override that error (and tell about that
		option in the error message).
		</para>

		<para>
		In general, the Errors are built of two kinds of information:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			the error messages;
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			the nested Errors reports.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		More exactly, an Errors contains a sequence of elements, each of which
		may contain a string, a nested Errors object, or both. When both, the
		idea is that the string gives a high-level description and the location
		of the error in the high-level object while the nested Errors digs into
		the further detail. The string gets printed before the nested Errors.
		The nested Errors get printed with an indentation. The indentation gets
		added only when the errors get <quote>printed</quote>, i.e. the top-level Errors
		object gets converted to a string. Until then the elements may be
		nested every which way without incurring any extra overhead.
		</para>

		<para>
		Obviously, you must not try to nest an Errors object inside itself,
		directly or indirectly. Not only will it create a memory reference
		cycle, but also an endless recursion when printing.
		</para>

		<para>
		The most typical way to construct an Errors object
		is with the functions taking the printf-like arguments.
		They have been a relatively recent addition, so there is plenty of code in Triceps that
		uses the older ways, but this is the latest and greatest, and
		recommended for all the future use.
		</para>

		<para>
		The consistent theme in its usage is <quote>check if the Errors reference (Erref) is
		NULL, if it is, allocate a new Errors, and then add a formatted error
		message to it</quote>. So the printf-like methods are defined not on Errors but on
		Erref. They check if the Erref object is NULL, allocate a new Errors
		object into it if needed, and then format the arguments. The simplest
		one is:
		</para>

<pre>
void f(const char *fmt, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		It adds a simple formatted message, always marked as an error. It is used
		like this:
		</para>

<pre>
Erref e; // initially NULL by default
...
e.f("a message with integer %d", n);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Errors</primary>
			<secondary>multi-line</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The message may be multi-line, it will be split appropriately, to make
		it all render with the correct indenting level. If the error message
		contains a <quote>\n</quote> at the end, that <quote>\n</quote>
		will be discarded (since the line feed after each line is implicit).
		</para>

		<para>
		The next one is used to build the nested error messages:
		</para>

<pre>
bool fAppend(Autoref<Errors> clde, const char *fmt, ...);
</pre>

		<para>
		It first checks that the child errors object is not NULL and contains
		an error, and if it does then it goes through the dance of allocating a
		new Errors object if needed, appending the formatted message and the
		child errors. The message goes before the child errors, unlike the
		method signature. So you can use it blindly like this to do the right
		thing:
		</para>

<pre>
Erref checkSubObject(int idx);

Erref checkObject()
{
	Erref err; // initially NULL by default
	...
	for (int i = 0; i < sz; i++)
		err.fAppend(checkSubObject(i),  "error in the sub-object %d:", i);
	...
	return err; // NULL on success, Errors reference on error
}
</pre>

		<para>
		No additional <b>if</b>s are necessary to check the result of
		<pre>checkSubObject()</pre>, <pre>fAppend()</pre> contains this <b>if</b> inside it.
		Similar to <pre>f()</pre>, the error message may be multi-line.
		</para>

		<para>
		The more basic way to create an Errors is by calling one of
		the constructors:
		</para>

<pre>
Errors(bool e = false);
Errors(const char *msg);
Errors(const string &msg);
Errors(const string &msg, Autoref<Errors> clde);
</pre>

		<para>
		For example:
		</para>

<pre>
Erref err = Errors("error message");
</pre>

		<para>
		The default constructor creates an empty object, which then needs
		to be filled with the messages (or not, returning an empty Errors
		object is also possible, meaning that no errors were found, though
		returning NULL is more efficient).
		The argument <pre>e</pre> is an indicator than it contains an actual error.
		By default it's unset but will be set when an error message is added, or whan a nested Errors
		object with an error in it is added.
		</para>

		<para>
		The rest of the above are the convenience constructors that make one-off
		Errors from one element (though of course more elements can be added
		afterwards).
		In all of them the error flag is always set, and the multi-line messages
		are properly handled.
		</para>

		<para>
		After an Errors object is constructed, more elements can be added to it
		by one of the following methods.
		</para>

<pre>
void appendMsg(bool e, const string &msg);
</pre>

		<para>
		The argument <pre>e</pre> shows whether the message is an error message
		(and it will set the error flag in Errors),
		otherwise just a warning. 
		There are no special per-message indications whether it's an error
		or warning, the Errors keeps just a single flag per object, and the messages
		are eventually printed as-is. So if you want the user to recognize
		some message as a warning, prefix its text with something like
		<quote>warning:</quote>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The argument <pre>msg</pre> must be a single-line message, don't use a <quote>\n</quote> in it!
		If you want to append multiple lines, call <pre>appendMsg()</pre> once per line, or
		use <pre>appendMultiline()</pre> to append the whole multi-line message.
		</para>

<pre>
void appendMultiline(bool e, const string &msg);
</pre>

		<para>
		The same as <pre>appendMsg()</pre>, only it will safely break a multi-line message into
		multiple single-liners and will ignore the <quote>\n</quote> at the end.
		Inside the Errors object each line will become a separate message.
		</para>

<pre>
bool append(const string &msg, Autoref<Errors> clde);
</pre>

		<para>
		The <pre>append()</pre> method is somewhat like <pre>Erref::fAppend()</pre> but
		different, because they represent different ages of the API.
		When <pre>append()</pre> was written, the warnings were considered important,
		and a common way to return a no-error condition was by returning
		an Errors object with no contents. When <pre>fAppend()</pre> was written,
		I've pretty much given up on the use of warnings, and the preferred
		way to return the no-error condition had become by returning NULL.
		</para>

		<para>
		In <pre>append()</pre> the following situations are possible:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			The argument <pre>clde</pre> is NULL or empty (that is contains no
			messages nor sub-objects), and the error flag in it is false. In this case
			<pre>append()</pre> does nothing, and the message <pre>msg</pre> is thrown away.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			The argument <pre>clde</pre> is not empty but the error flag is false.
			Both <pre>msg</pre> and child object will be appended to the Errors.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			The argument <pre>clde</pre> is not empty and the error flag is true.
			Both <pre>msg</pre> and child object will be appended to the Errors,
			and the error flag will be set in it.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			The argument <pre>clde</pre> is empty and the error flag is true.
			The <pre>msg</pre> will be appended to the Errors and
			the error flag will be set in it. The child object will be thrown
			away (it's reference-counted, so it will be freed when the last
			reference is gone).
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		Just like <pre>appendMsg()</pre>, the argument <pre>msg</pre> must be a single-line message.
		</para>


		<para>
		The return value of <pre>append()</pre> will be true
		if the child element contained any data in it or an error indication
		flag. This can be used together with another method
		</para>


<pre>
void replaceMsg(const string &msg);
</pre>

		<para>
		to add a complex high-level description if a child element has reported
		an error. By now it has become old-fashioned, and <pre>Erref::fAppend()</pre> is
		a better choice. Before <pre>fAppend()</pre> came along, the typical way to
		create an error message was by calling <pre>strprintf()</pre> that formats a
		printf-like string into a &Cpp; string object. And it's kind of expensive
		to call <pre>strprintf()</pre> in any case, even if the child returned no error.
		So the optimization was to call <pre>append()</pre> with an empty string, and
		if it happened to actually append something, replace that empty
		message with the real one. As the following pattern shows:
		</para>

<pre>
Erref clde = someThing(...);
if (e.append("", clde)) {
    // ... generate msg in some complicated way
    e.replaceMsg(strprintf(...));
}
</pre>

		<para>
		The <pre>replaceMsg()</pre> replaces the string portion of the last element, which
		owns the last added child error.
		</para>

		<para>
		This pattern can still be used if the error message is truly
		difficult to generate, but usually <pre>fAppend()</pre> is a better choice.
		</para>

		<para>
		It's also possible to include the contents of another Errors directly,
		without nesting it:
		</para>

<pre>
bool absorb(Autoref<Errors> clde);
</pre>

		<para>
		The return value has the same meaning as with <pre>append()</pre> (but <pre>replaceMsg()</pre>
		can not be used with this method for anything reasonable). The argument
		<pre>clde</pre> may be NULL. The error flag propagates to the parent as usual.
		</para>

		<para>
		Finally, an
		Errors object can be cleared to its empty state:
		</para>

<pre>
void clear();
</pre>

		<para>
		Usually the clearing of an Errors object is not such a good idea.
		Remember, they are built into a tree. So if you later modify an
		Errors object, that would also modify what is seen by all the
		objects that refer to it. The proper approach is to treat an Errors
		object as append-only while it's being built. And after it has been
		completed and returned, treat it as read-only.
		</para>

		<para>
		To get the number of elements in Errors, use
		</para>

<pre>
size_t size() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Remember, a child object with its associated top-level error message
		counts as a single element, not two of them.
		</para>

		<para>
		However the more typical methods are:
		</para>

<pre>
bool isEmpty();
bool hasError();
</pre>

		<para>
		They check whether there is nothing at all or whether there is an
		error. The special convenience of these methods is that they can be
		called on NULL pointers. Quite a few Triceps methods return a NULL
		Erref if there was no error. In the following example, even if 
		<pre>er</pre> is NULL, these calls are still safe and officially supported. 
		But <b>not</b> <pre>er->size()</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
Erref er = NULL;
er->isEmpty();
er->hasError();
parent_er->append(msg, er);
parent_er->absorb(er);
parent_er.fAppend(er, msg);
</pre>

		<para>
		The data gets extracted from Erref by converting it to a string, either
		appending to an existing string, or creating a new one:
		</para>


<pre>
void printTo(string &res, const string &indent = "", const string &subindent = "  ");
string print(const string &indent = "", const string &subindent = "  ");
</pre>

		<para>
		The <pre>res</pre> argument provides the result string to append the error messages
		to. <pre>print()</pre> works by constructing a new string internally, calling <pre>printTo()</pre>
		on it, and then returning it, so <pre>print()</pre> is more expensive than <pre>printTo()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The messages will be separated by the newline characters <quote>\n</quote>,
		with the proper indentation after each of these characters.
		The <pre>indent</pre> argument specifies the initial indentation, <pre>subindent</pre> the
		additional indentation for each level. 
		</para>
		
		<para>
		The very first line will have nothing prepended to it, it's assumed that you've
		already done that indentation manually, or maybe you're appending to the end
		of some ongoing line. But all the following top-level lines will have
		the <pre>indent</pre> text following the <quote>\n</quote>. The nested error
		lines will have the concatenation of <pre>indent</pre> and one copy of <pre>subindent</pre>
		in front of them after <quote>\n</quote>, the second level of nesting will have
		an <pre>indent</pre> and two copies of <pre>subindent</pre>, and so on.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		All the lines are terminated by <quote>\n</quote> (except if the Errors object
		is empty, then nothing will be appended).
		</para>
		
		<indexterm>
			<primary>NOINDENT</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Note that the constant <pre>NOINDENT</pre> has no special effect on 
		the printing of Errors (unlike the printing of types), it's just treated 
		here as an empty string.
		</para>

	</sect1>
