<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_init">
		<title>Initialization templates</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
			<secondary>in &Cpp;</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>initialization</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Triceps has the common approach for building the complex objects in stages
		by the chained mehod calls (demonstrated here on a fictional class Object):
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<Object> o = Object::make()->addOption1(arg)->addOption2(arg);
</pre>

		<para>
		Here <pre>Object::make()</pre> is a convenience wrapper for <pre>new Object</pre>, 
		because the operator <pre>new</pre> has an inconvenient
		priority. The <pre>new</pre> or <pre>make()</pre> returns a pointer to
		the newly constructed object, and then each method in the chain returns
		the same pointer (<pre>this</pre>, from its standpoint) to facilitate
		the chaining.
		</para>

		<para>
		While the chain executes, the pointer stays a simple pointer, not a
		reference. So the methods in the chain can't throw any exceptions, or
		the memory will leak. Instead they collect the error messages in an
		Errors object that has to be checked afterwards, like:
		</para>

<pre>
if (o->getErrors()->hasError()) ...
</pre>

		<para>
		Note that a reference to the object gets created first, so that on
		an error the object would be properly destroyed.
		</para>

		<para>
		The convenience template <pre>checkOrThrow()</pre> allows to do the check along
		with the chain, and if an error is found, convert it to an Exception:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Exception</primary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
Autoref<Object> o = checkOrThrow(
	Object::make()->addOption1(arg)->addOption2(arg)
);
</pre>

		<para>
		It does all the right things with the references.
		</para>

		<para>
		Some objects  need to be initialized after all the options have been
		set, since it's much easier to check things once and get the
		interaction of the options right rather than check on every option. And
		since the initialization might create the references to the object, to
		get it right, it has to be done after the <quote>main</quote> reference is created.
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<Object> o = Object::make()->addOption1(arg)->addOption2(arg);
o->initialize();
</pre>

		<para>
		The template <pre>initialize()</pre> allows to do it in one expression:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<Object> o = initialize(
	Object::make()->addOption1(arg)->addOption2(arg)
);
</pre>

		<para>
		For some objects the initialization can't fail (nor any other errors
		can be created by the options). For the others, the errors needs to be
		checked afterwards, in the same way as shown above. 
		The template <pre>initializeOrThrow()</pre> takes care of the whole sequence of
		the initialization, the check, and Exception throwing on errors:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<Object> o = initializeOrThrow(
	Object::make()->addOption1(arg)->addOption2(arg)
);
</pre>

		<para>
		That's basically it. All these templates are defined in <pre>common/Initialize.h</pre>. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
