<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_types">
		<title>Types reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Type</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Fundamentally, Triceps is a language, even though it is piggybacking on
		the other languages. And as in pretty much any programming language,
		pretty much anything in it has a type. Only the tip of that type system
		is exposed in the Perl API, as the RowType and TableType. But the &Cpp;
		API has the whole depth. The types go all the way down to the simple
		types of the fields.
		</para>

		<para>
		The classes for types are generally defined in the subdirectory <pre>type/</pre>.
		The class Type, defined in <pre>type/Type.h</pre> is the common base class,
		inheriting from Mtarget. The types are gererally fullly constructed in one thread,
		and then they become read-only and accessible from multiple threads.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>TypeId</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The base class has a field that identifies, which kind of a type it is.
		Each subclass, every kind of type has its entry in the enum TypeId:
		</para>

<pre>
TT_VOID, // no value
TT_UINT8, // unsigned 8-bit integer (byte)
TT_INT32, // 32-bit integer
TT_INT64,
TT_FLOAT64, // 64-bit floating-point, what C calls "double"
TT_STRING, // a string: a special kind of byte array
TT_ROW, // a row of a table
TT_RH, // row handle: item through which all indexes in the table own a row
TT_TABLE, // data store of rows (AKA "window")
TT_INDEX, // a table contains one or more indexes for its rows
TT_AGGREGATOR, // user piece of code that does aggregation on the indexes
TT_ROWSET, // an ordered set of row types
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>FnReturn</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>FnBinding</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Nexus</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Facet</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Most of it is straightforward, and maps directly to the types described
		in the Perl API. TT_ROWSET is not directly exported to Perl, but
		internally and in the &Cpp; API it's the underlying type for anything
		that uses a set of row types: an FnReturn, FnBinding, Nexus or Facet.
		TT_VOID is pretty much a placeholder, in case if a void type
		would be needed later. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The TypeId gets hardcoded in the constructor of
		every Type subclass. It can be obtained back with the method
		</para>

<pre>
TypeId getTypeId() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Another method finds out if the type is the simple type of a field:
		</para>

<pre>
bool isSimple() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		It would be true for the types of ids TT_VOID, TT_UINT8,  TT_INT32,
		TT_INT64, TT_FLOAT64, TT_STRING.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>SimpleType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Generally, you can check the TypeId and then cast the Type pointer to
		its subclass. All the simple types have the common base class
		SimpleType, which is described in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_types_simple" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is also a static Type method that finds a simple type object by
		the type name (like "int32", "string" etc.):
		</para>

<pre>
static Onceref<const SimpleType> findSimpleType(const char *name);
</pre>

		<para>
		If the type name is incorrect and the type is not found,
		<pre>findSimpleType()</pre> will return NULL.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is not a whole lot of point in having many copies
		of the simple type objects (though if you want, you can). So there is
		one common copy of each simple type that can be found by name with
		<pre>findSimpleType()</pre>. If the type is known at the compilation time of the
		&Cpp; program, you can even avoid the look-up and refer to these
		objects directly:
		</para>

<pre>
static Autoref<const SimpleType> r_void;
static Autoref<const SimpleType> r_uint8;
static Autoref<const SimpleType> r_int32;
static Autoref<const SimpleType> r_int64;
static Autoref<const SimpleType> r_float64;
static Autoref<const SimpleType> r_string;
</pre>

		<para>
		All of them are defined in the class Type, so you refer to them like
		<pre>Type::r_string</pre>.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>error handling</primary>
			<secondary>in &Cpp;</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The type construction may cause errors. The construction is usually done either by a
		single constructor call with all the needed arguments, or a simple
		constructor, then additional methods to add the information in bits and
		pieces, then an initialization method. In both cases there is a problem
		of how to report the errors. They're not easy to return from a
		constructor and a pain to check in the bit-by-bit construction.
		</para>

		<para>
		Instead the error information gets internally collected in an Errors
		object, and can be read after the construction and/or initialization is
		completed:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual Erref getErrors() const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Exception</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>initialization</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		There also are the convenience templates that do the initialization,
		check the errors and throw an Exception on failure. They are described in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_init" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		A type with errors may not be used for anything other than reading the
		errors (and of course it can be destroyed by deleting all the references
		to it). Its behavior for anything else is undefined and may cause a crash.
		</para>

		<para>
		The rest of the common virtual methods has to do with the type
		comparison and print-outs. The comparison methods essentially check if
		two type objects are aliases for each other:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual bool equals(const Type *t) const;
virtual bool match(const Type *t) const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>equals</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>type</primary>
			<secondary>match</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The concept has been previously described with the Perl API in
		<xref linkend="sc_RowTypesEquiv" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;,
		but it really applies not only to the row types but to any types.
		The equal
		types are exactly the same. The matching types are the same except for
		the names of their elements, so it's generally safe to pass the values
		between these types.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>equals()</pre> is also available as <pre>operator==</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The print methods create a string representation of a type, used mostly
		for the error messages. There is no method to parse this string
		representation back, at least not yet.
		</para>

<pre>
virtual void printTo(string &res, const string &indent = "", const string &subindent = "  ") const = 0;
string print(const string &indent = "", const string &subindent = "  ") const;
</pre>

		<para>
		<pre>printTo()</pre> appends the information to an existing string. <pre>print()</pre>
		returns a new string with the message. <pre>print()</pre> is a wrapper around
		<pre>printTo()</pre> that creates an empty string, does <pre>printTo()</pre> into it and
		returns it.
		</para>

		<para>
		The printing is normally done in a multi-line format, nicely indented,
		and the arguments <pre>indent</pre> and <pre>subindent</pre> define the initial indent level
		and the additional indentation for every level.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>NOINDENT</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		There is also a way to print everything in one line: pass the special
		constant NOINDENT (defined in <pre>common/StringUtil.h</pre>) in the argument
		<pre>indent</pre>. This is similar to using an <b>undef</b> for the same purpose in the
		Perl API.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Type</primary>
			<secondary>all types</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>AllTypes</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The definitions of all the types are collected together in
		<pre>type/AllTypes.h</pre>. 
		</para>
	</sect1>

