<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_rowtype">
		<title>RowType reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		In the Perl API a row type is a collection of fields. Under the hood
		the things are more complicated. In the &Cpp; API Triceps allows for more
		flexibility, more ways to represent a row. The row type is represented
		by the abstract base class RowType that tells the logical structure of
		a row and by its concrete subclasses that define the concrete layout of
		data in a row. To create, read or manipulate a row, all you need to
		know is a reference to RowType. It would refer to a concrete row type
		object, and the concrete row operations are accessed by the virtual
		methods. But when you create a row type, you need to know the concrete
		row type subclass.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>CompactRowType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Currently the choice is easy: there is only one such concrete subclass
		CompactRowType. The <quote>compact</quote> means that the data is stored in the rows
		in a compact form, one field value after another, without alignment.
		Perhaps some day there will be an AlignedRowType, allowing to read the
		values more efficiently. Or perhaps some day there will be a
		ZippedRowType that would store the data in the compressed format.
		</para>

		<para>
		Naturally, RowType is a Mtarget, since it inherits
		from Type, and CompactRowType inherits from it. 
		They are defined in <pre>type/RowType.h</pre> and
		<pre>type/CompactRowType.h</pre> but for the include purposes it's
		more customary to simply include <pre>type/AllTypes.h</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		You would never use the RowType constructor directly, it's called from
		the subclasses.  Even if you care
		only about the logical structure of a row but not representation, you still
		can't directly construct a RowType because it's an abstract class. But
		just construct any concrete subclass, say CompactRowType (since it's
		the only one available at the moment anyway), and then use its logical
		structure.
		Every subclass is expected to define a similar
		constructor:
		</para>

<pre>
RowType(const FieldVec &fields);
CompactRowType(const FieldVec &fields);
</pre>

		<para>
		The FieldVec is the definition of fields in the row type. It's defined
		as simple as:
		</para>

<pre>
typedef vector<Field> FieldVec;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>FieldVec</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Field</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		An important side note is that the field is defined within the RowType,
		so it's really RowType::FieldVec and RowType::Field, and you need to
		refer to them in your code by this qualified name. So, to create a row
		type, you create a vector of field definitions first and then construct
		the row type from it. You can throw away or modify that vector
		afterwards.
		</para>

		<para>
		As usual for Type, the constructor arguments might not be correct, and any
		errors will be remembered and returned with <pre>getErrors()</pre>. Don't use a
		type with errors (other than to read the error messages from it, and to
		destroy it), it might cause your program to crash.
		</para>

		<para>
		A Field consists of the basic information about it: the name, the type,
		and the array indication (remember, a Triceps field may contain an
		array). The array indication is either RowType::Field::AR_SCALAR for a
		scalar value or RowType::Field::AR_VARIABLE for a variable-sized array.
		The original plan was also to use the integer values for the
		fixed-sized array fields, but in reality the variable-sized array
		fields have turned out to be easier to implement and that was it. So
		don't use the integer values. Most probably they would work like the
		same variable-sized arrays but they haven't been tested, and something
		somewhere might crash. Use the symbolic enum AR_*.
		</para>

		<para>
		The normal Field constructor provides all this information:
		</para>

<pre>
Field(const string &name, Autoref<const Type> t, int arsz = AR_SCALAR);
</pre>

		<para>
		Or you can use the default constructor and later change the fields in
		the Field (or of course read them) as you please, they are all public:
		</para>

<pre>
string name_;
Autoref <const Type> type_;
int arsz_;
</pre>

		<para>
		Or you can assign them later in one fell swoop:
		</para>

<pre>
void assign(const string &name, Autoref<const Type> t, int arsz = AR_SCALAR);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>SimpleType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Note that even though theoretically you can define a field of any Type,
		in practice it has to be of a SimpleType, or the RowType constructor
		will return an error later. Why isn't it defined as an
		<pre>Autoref<SimpleType></pre> then? The grand plan for the future 
		is to allow some more
		interesting data structures in the rows, and this keeps the door open.
		In particular, the rows will be able to hold references to the other
		rows, just I haven't got to implementing it yet.
		</para>

		<para>
		Once again, a RowType constructor makes a copy of the FieldVec for its
		use, so you can modify or destroy the original FieldVec right away. You
		can get back the information about the fields in RowType:
		</para>

<pre>
const vector<Field> &fields() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		It returns a reference directly to the FieldVec contained in the row
		type, so you must never modify it! The const-ness gives a reminder
		about it.
		</para>

		<para>
		There are more row type constructors (but no default one). First, each
		subclass variety is supposed to be able to construct its variety by
		copying the logical structure of any RowType:
		</para>

<pre>
CompactRowType(const RowType &proto);
CompactRowType(const RowType *proto);
</pre>

		<para>
		The version with the pointer argument also works for passing an
		<pre>Autoref<RowType></pre> as the argument which gets automatically converted to
		a pointer (but be careful to not destroy the last reference until after the constructor
		returns). And it's really the more typically used one than the
		&amp;-reference version.
		</para>

		<para>
		The resulting type will have the same logical structure but possibly a
		different concrete representation than the original. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The second constructor variety is a factory method:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual RowType *newSameFormat(const FieldVec &fields) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		It combines the representation format from one row type and the
		arbitrary logical structure (the fields vector) from possibly another
		row type. Or course, until more of the concrete type representations become
		available, its use is largely theoretical. 
		</para>

		<para>
		And there is also a factory method that copies the current row type
		together with its concrete representation (it's really a convenience
		wrapper over <pre>newSameFormat()</pre>):
		</para>

<pre>
RowType *copy() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Let's get to some examples of constructing the row types. To reiterate,
		you don't construct the objects of RowType class itself, it's an
		abstract class. You construct the objects of the concrete subclass(es),
		specifically CompactRowType. Make a vector describing the fields and do
		the construction.
		</para>

		<para>
		You can make the vector by either starting with an empty one and adding
		the fields to it or allocating a vector of the right size in advance
		and  setting the fields in it:
		</para>

<pre>
RowType::FieldVec fields1;
fields1.push_back(RowType::Field("a", Type::r_int64)); // scalar by default
fields1.push_back(RowType::Field("b", Type::r_int32, RowType::Field::AR_SCALAR));
fields1.push_back(RowType::Field("c", Type::r_uint8, RowType::Field::AR_VARIABLE));

RowType::FieldVec fields2(2);
fields2[0].assign("a", Type::r_int64); // scalar by default
fields2[1].assign("b", Type::r_int32, RowType::Field::AR_VARIABLE);
</pre>

		<para>
		You can also reuse the same vector and clean/resize is as needed to
		create more types.
		</para>

		<para>
		If you're used to laying out the C structures placing the larger
		elements first for the more efficient alignment, know that this is not
		needed for the Triceps rows. The CompactRowType stores the row data
		unaligned, so any field order will result in the same size of the rows.
		And it can't make use of some fields happening to be aligned either.
		</para>

		<para>
		You can also find the simple types by their string names:
		</para>

<pre>
fields1.push_back(RowType::Field("d", Type::findSimpleType("uint8"), RowType::Field::AR_VARIABLE));
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Type</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		If the type name is incorrect and the type is not found,
		<pre>findSimpleType()</pre> will return NULL, which NULL will be caught later at
		the row type creation times. Note that there is no automatic look-up of
		the array types. You can't simply pass <quote>uint8[]</quote> to <pre>findSimpleType()</pre>.
		You have to break it up into the simple type name as such an the array
		indication, like is done in <pre>perl/Triceps/RowType.xs</pre>. This would
		probably a good thing to add to RowType::Field in the future.
		</para>

		<para>
		You can't use the type Type::r_void for the fields, it will be reported
		as an error.
		</para>

		<para>
		After the fields array is created, create the row type:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<RowType> rt1 = new CompactRowType(fields1);
if (rt1->getErrors()->hasError())
	throw Exception(rt1->getErrors(), true);
</pre>

		<para>
		Or using the inialization templates:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<RowType> rt1 = checkOrThrow(new CompactRowType(fields1));
</pre>

		<para>
		You could also use <pre>Autoref<CompactRowType></pre> but there isn't any point to
		it, since all the methods of CompactRowType are virtuals inherited from
		RowType.
		</para>

		<para>
		Don't forget to check that the constructed type has no errors, and bail
		out if so. Throwing an Exception is a convenient way to abort with a
		nice error message, and the template <pre>checkOrThrow()</pre> takes care of wrapping
		all the details.
		</para>

		<para>
		The RowType and its subclasses are immutable after construction, so
		they can be shared between threads all you want. Depending on your
		approach to the threads, it might be more efficient to create a 
		separate copy of the row type for each thread. This way when the
		references to the row types are created and deleted, the reference
		count can stay in the cache of one CPU and thus be more efficient.
		The thread support of the Triceps library does use this approach
		and creates the copies whenever the row types are imported from a
		nexus.
		</para>

		<para>
		There are multiple equivalent ways to create a copy:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<RowType> rt2 = rt1->copy();
Autoref<RowType> rt3 = rt1->newSameFormat(rt1->fields());
Autoref<RowType> rt4 = new CompactRowType(rt1);
</pre>

		<para>
		Checking the errors after the copy creation is optional if the
		original type was correct.
		</para>

		<para>
		If you want to extend a type with more fields, make a copy
		of its fields and extend it:
		</para>

<pre>
RowType::FieldVec fields3 = rt1->fields();
fields3.push_back(RowType::Field("z", Type::r_string));
Autoref<RowType> rt3 = checkOrThrow(new CompactRowType(fields3));
</pre>

		<para>
		That's about it for the RowType construction. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The information about the contents of a RowType can be read back:
		</para>

<pre>
int fieldCount() const;
const vector<Field> &fields() const;
int findIdx(const string &fname) const;
const Field *find(const string &fname) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		<pre>fields()</pre> had already been described. <pre>fieldCount()</pre> returns the count of
		fields. <pre>findIdx()</pre> finds the index of the field by name, so that it can
		then be looked up in the result of <pre>fields()</pre>. Or -1 if there is no such
		field. <pre>find()</pre> directly returns the pointer to the field by name,
		combining these two actions. (Or it returns NULL if there is no such
		field).
		</para>

		<para>
		The rest of the RowType methods have to do with the manipulation of the
		rows. They are described in 
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_row" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>
	</sect1>
