<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_tabtype">
		<title>TableType reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>TableType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The TableType describes the type of a table, defined in
		<pre>type/TableType.h</pre>. It inherits being an Mtarget from the Type,
		and can be shared between the threads after it has been initialized.
		However like RowType, it can benefit from creating a separate copy
		for each thread, to keep the reference count changes local to one
		CPU (see the method <pre>deepCopy()</pre> below).
		</para>

		<para>
		In the &Cpp; API it's built very similarly to the current
		Perl API, by constructing a bare object, then adding information to it,
		and finally initializing it. The Perl API will eventually change to
		something more Perl-like, the &Cpp; API will stay this way.
		</para>

		<para>
		The creation goes like this:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>initializeOrThrow</primary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
Autoref<TableType> tt = initializeOrThrow( (new TableType(rt1))
	->addSubIndex("primary", it
	)->addSubIndex("secondary", itcopy
	)
);
</pre>

		<para>
		In reality the index types would also be constructed as a part of this
		long statement but for clarity they were assumed to be pre-created
		as <pre>it</pre> and <pre>itcopy</pre>. 
		</para>
		
		<para>
		After a table type has been initialized, nothing can be added to it any
		more. Just as in the Perl API, the <pre>addSubIndex()</pre> adds not its argument
		index type object but its deep copy (see more about the copy varieties in 
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_copy" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;).
		When the table type gets initialized, these index types get tied to it.
		</para>

		<para>
		Note that the operator <pre>new</pre> has to be in parenthesis to get the
		priorities right. It's kind of annoying, so the better-looking
		equivalent way to do it is to use the static method <pre>make()</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<TableType> tt = initializeOrThrow(TableType::make(rt1)
	->addSubIndex("primary", it
	)->addSubIndex("secondary", itcopy
	)
);
</pre>

		<para>
		And here is a more complete example, with making of all the
		components in one chain:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<TableType> tt = initializeOrThrow(TableType::make(rt1)
	->addSubIndex("primary", HashedIndexType::make(
		NameSet::make()->add("a")->add("e"))
		->setAggregator(new MyAggregatorType("onPrimary", NULL))
		->addSubIndex("level2", new FifoIndexType)
	)
);
</pre>

		<para>
		The construction-related methods are:
		</para>

<pre>
TableType(Onceref<RowType> rt);
static TableType *make(Onceref<RowType> rt);
TableType *addSubIndex(const string &name, IndexType *index);
void initialize();
</pre>

		<para>
		The method <pre>initialize()</pre> is called by the <pre>initializeOrThrow()</pre> template,
		which then checks for errors and throws an Exception if it finds any.
		But you can call it manually instead if you wish.
		</para>

		<para>
		The working of the <pre>addSubIndex()</pre> is such that it doesn't put its
		<pre>this</pre> object into any kind of Autoref. Because of that it's able to
		pass that pointer right through to its result for chaining. It doesn't
		check anything and can't throw any exceptions. So the TableType object
		created by the constructor gets through the chain of <pre>addSubIndex()</pre>
		without having any counted references to it created, its reference
		count stays at 0. Only when the result of the chain is assigned to an
		Autoref, the first reference gets created. Obviously, this chain must
		not be interrupted by any exceptions or the memory will leak. Any
		detected errors must be collected in the embedded error objects, that
		will be read after initialization.
		</para>

		<para>
		The result of initialization is void for a good reason: if you call
		<pre>initialize()</pre> manually, you can't include it into this chain, and the
		void result forces the non-chained call. Before the initialization is
		called, the TableType object must be properly held in a counted
		reference.  For example:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<TableType> tt = TableType::make(rt1)
	->addSubIndex("primary", it
	)->addSubIndex("secondary", itcopy
	);
tt->initialize();
if (tt->getErrors()->hasError())
	throw Exception(tt->getErrors());
</pre>

		<para>
		But <pre>initializeOrThrow()</pre> is smart enough to do things correctly
		within the chained call format.
		It saves the TableType in an Autoref, then calls <pre>initialize()</pre>,
		and on success returns that Autoref, never corrupting the references.
		It involves a little more overhead but the TableType construction
		usually happens only once at the start-up time, and thus a minor
		difference in efficiency doesn't matter.
		</para>

		<para>
		It's safe to call <pre>initialize()</pre> multiple times, the repeated calls will
		simply have no effect.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Exception</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The sub-indexes may be added only while the table type is not
		initialized, afterwards it will throw an Exception.
		</para>

		<para>
		The methods to examine the contents of the table type are:
		</para>

<pre>
bool isInitialized() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the table type has been initialized.
		</para>

<pre>
const RowType *rowType() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the row type of the table type. Since the table type is not
		expected to be destroyed immediately, it's OK to return a plain
		pointer.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexType *findSubIndex(const string &name) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Find the index by name. Returns NULL if not found.  This looks only for
		the top-level indexes, to find the nested indexes, the similar calls
		have to be continued on the further levels. At the moment there is no
		ready method to resolve a whole index path in &Cpp;, however the
		same method in IndexType has a special feature that allows to
		do it by simple chaining:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<IndexType> it = tt->findSubIndex("level1")->findSubIndex("level2");
if (it.isNull()) {
	// not found
}
</pre>

		<para>
		That special feature is that <pre>findSubIndex()</pre> in IndexType works
		even on a NULL reference, simply returning NULL. So if 
		<pre>findSubIndex("level1")</pre> returns NULL,
		<pre>findSubIndex("level2")</pre> will simply propagate that NULL.
		The downside compared with the path-resolving method in Perl
		is that this chain doesn't tell you, which of the indexes in the
		path were not found.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexType *findSubIndexById(IndexType::IndexId it) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds the first index type of a particular kind (or NULL if none
		found). The ids are like IndexType::IT_HASHED, IndexType::IT_FIFO,
		IndexType::IT_SORTED.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexType *getFirstLeaf() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Finds the first leaf index type. This call does search through the
		whole depth of the index tree for the first leaf index type.
		</para>

<pre>
const IndexTypeVec &getSubIndexes() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the vector with all the top-level index type references. The
		vector is read-only, you must not change it. 
		</para>

<pre>
TableType *copy() const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>IndexType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>AggregatorType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Copy the table type, including all its contents of IndexTypes
		and AggregatorTypes, because they get tied to no more than one
		TableType. However the RowTypes stay shared.
		The copied table type is always uninitialized and thus can
		be further extended by defining more indexes and aggregators.
		</para>

		<para>
		In case if the table type collected errors, the errors aren't copied,
		and in general you should not copy such a table type. The errors
		will be detected again when you try to initialize the copy.
		</para>

<pre>
TableType *deepCopy(HoldRowTypes *holder) const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>HoldRowTypes</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Nexus</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Copy the whole strucutre all the way down, up to and including the
		row types. This is used for exporting the TableTypes to the other
		threads through a Nexus. It keeps the reference counts localized to
		each thread, preventing the thrashing of them between CPUs as the
		references are created and destroyed.
		</para>

		<para>
		The HoldRowTypes object is what takes care of sharing the underlying
		row types. To copy a bunch of objects with sharing, you create a
		HoldRowTypes, copy the bunch, destroy the HoldRowTypes,
		as described in more detail in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_copy" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		The Perl API contains one more copy method, <pre>copyFundamental()</pre>.
		It's not directly available in the &Cpp; API yet but the same task can be
		done manually.
		</para>

		<para>
		Ultimately, the TableType is used to construct the tables. The factory
		method is:
		</para>

<pre>
Onceref<Table> makeTable(Unit *unit, const string &name) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		This creates a table with the given name in a given unit. 
		If the table type is not initialized or the initialization
		returned an error, will return NULL.
		</para>

		<para>
		Finally, there is a call that you don't need to use:
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandleType *rhType() const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandleType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Like everything else, the RowHandles have a type. But this type is very
		much internal, and it knows very little about the row handles. All it
		knows is how much memory to allocate when constructing a new RowHandle.
		The rest of the knowledge about the RowHandles is placed inside the
		Table. So, a Table (yes, a Table, <b>not</b> a TableType) acts among
		the other things as a type for its RowHandles. 
		</para>
	</sect1>

