<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_nameset">
		<title>NameSet reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>NameSet</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>HashedIndexType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		NameSet is a helper class used as an argument for construction of
		other classes, most notably HashedIndexType. It's an Mtarget.
		</para>

		<para>
		NameSet is fundamentally a reference-counted vector of strings that
		allows to construct them with a chain of calls. It's used to
		construct such things as field list for the index key. 
		Properly, the names in the set should be different
		but NameSet itself doesn't check for that.
		The order of values in it usually matters. So its class name is slightly
		misleading: it's not really a set, it's a vector, but the name has been
		applied historically. And in the future it might include the set
		functionality too, by adding a quick look up of index by name.
		</para>

		<para>
		It's defined in <pre>type/NameSet.h</pre> as
		</para>

<pre>
class NameSet : public Mtarget, public vector<string> { ... }
</pre>

		<para>
		The typical usage is like this:
		</para>

<pre>
HashedIndexType::make(NameSet::make()->add("a")->add("e"))
</pre>

		<para>
		The factory method <pre>make()</pre> gives the
		more convenient operator priority than <pre>new()</pre>.
		The varieties of constructors and <pre>make()</pre> are:
		</para>

<pre>
NameSet();
NameSet(const vector<string> *other);
NameSet(const vector<string> &other);
static NameSet *make();
static NameSet *make(const vector<string> *other);
static NameSet *make(const vector<string> &other);
</pre>

		<para>
		This approach to the copy constructors allows to
		construct from a plain vector, and since NameSet is its
		subclass, that works as a real copy constructor too. 
		The constructor from a pointer makes the use of Autorefs more
		convenient, such as:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<NameSet> ns1 = NameSet::make()->add("a")->add("b");
Autoref<NameSet> ns2 = NameSet::make(ns1)->add("c");
</pre>

		<para>
		All the vector methods are directly accessible, plus the ones
		added in NameSet.
		</para>

<pre>
NameSet *add(const string &s);
</pre>

		<para>
		The method for the chained construction, adds a name to the vector
		and returns back the same NameSet object.
		</para>

<pre>
bool equals(const NameSet *other) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Comparison for equality. Returns true if both the name vectors
		are equal.
		</para>
	</sect1>
