<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_idxtype">
		<title>IndexType reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>IndexType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Very much like the Perl API, the IndexType is an abstract class, in
		which you can't create the objects directly, you have to create the
		objects with its concrete sub-classes. It has the methods common for
		all the index types, it is defined in <pre>type/IndexType.h</pre>
		and like all types it's an Mtarget.
		</para>

		<para>
		The index type id, defined as enum IndexType::IndexId, allows to find
		out the subclass of the actual object and cast it if desired.
		The supported index types are:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			IT_HASHED,
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			IT_FIFO,
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			IT_SORTED. 
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		There is
		also the semi-hidden type IT_ROOT: you can't create it directly but
		every table type creates one implicitly, as the root of its index tree.
		And the value IT_LAST is defined past the last actual type, so if you ever
		need to iterate through the types, you can do it as
		</para>

<pre>
for (int i = 0; i < IndexType::IT_LAST; i++) { ... }
</pre>

		<para>
		The conversion between the index type id and name can be done with the
		methods:
		</para>

<pre>
static const char *indexIdString(int enval, const char *def = "???");
static int stringIndexId(const char *str);
</pre>

		<para>
		As usual with the contant-and-name conversions, if the numeric id <pre>enval</pre> is
		invalid, the string <pre>def</pre> is returned, by default <quote>???</quote>. If the string
		name <pre>str</pre> is unknown, -1 is returned.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexId getIndexId() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the type id of this index type. The id can't be changed, it gets
		hardcoded in the subclass constructor.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexType *addSubIndex(const string &name, Onceref<IndexType> index);
</pre>

		<para>
		Add a sub-index, in exactly the same way as adding an index type to
		the TableType. 
		</para>

		<para>
		In works like TableType in all the other ways as well:
		it adds a copy of the argument, not the argument
		itself, and it designed for chaining. For example:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<TableType> tt = initializeOrThrow( TableType::make(rt1)
	->addSubIndex("primary", HashedIndexType::make(
		NameSet::make()->add("b")->add("c"))
	)->addSubIndex("limit", FifoIndexType::make()
		->setLimit(2) // will policy-delete 2 rows
	)
); 
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Exception</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Not all index types allow sub-indexes but this method
		works silently for all of them. Any mistakes will be detected and
		reported at the initialization time. The sub-indexes may be added
		only until the index type is initialized. Any modification attempts
		after that will throw an Exception.
		</para>

<pre>
bool isLeaf() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns true if this index type has no sub-indexes. Of course, if this
		type is not initialized yet, more sub-types can be added to it to make
		it non-leaf later.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexType *findSubIndex(const string &name) const;
IndexType *findSubIndexById(IndexId it) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Find the sub-index by name or id, works in the same way as for
		TableType. A special feature is that it can be applied on a NULL object
		reference, like this:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<IndexType> it; // NULL by default
Autoref<IndexType> itsub = it->findSubIndex("xxx"); // doesn't crash, returns NULL
</pre>

		<para>
		The idea here is to allow the safe chaining of <pre>findSubIndex()</pre> for the
		look-ups of the nested types:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<IndexType> it = tt->findSubIndex("level1")->findSubIndex("level2");
if (it.isNull()) {
	// not found
}
</pre>

		<para>
		If any of the elements in the path are missing, the end result will be
		NULL, conveniently. But it won't tell you, which one was missing,
		inconveniently.
		</para>

<pre>
const IndexTypeVec &getSubIndexes() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns back the whole set of sub-indexes.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexType *getFirstLeaf() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the first leaf index type (if a leaf itself, will return
		itself).
		</para>

<pre>
const NameSet *getKey() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the key information from the index.
		It will work with any kind of index, but will return a NULL if the
		index doesn't support the key. There is no matching method to
		set it, setting the key is up to the subclasses.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexType *setAggregator(Onceref<AggregatorType> agg);
const AggregatorType *getAggregator() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Set or get an aggregator type for this index type. As usual, any
		setting can be done only until the index type is initialized. 
		Any modification attempts after that will throw an Exception.
		</para>

<pre>
bool isInitialized() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the index type has been initialized.
		The index types are initialized as a part of the table type
		initialization, there is no method to initialize an index
		type directly.
		</para>

<pre>
TableType *getTabtype() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the table type, to which this index type is tied. The
		tying-together happens at the initialization time, so for an
		initialized index type this method will return NULL.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexType *copy(bool flat = false) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Create an un-initialized copy of this index. If <pre>flat</pre> is <pre>false</pre> then
		the copy is done with all the sub-index and
		aggregator types also copied, but the row types shared. This method is used by
		<pre>addSubIndex()</pre> to copy its argument before adding. By the way, the usual
		copy constructor could theoretically be used on the index types but
		usually doesn't make a whole lot of a sense because the sub-types and
		such will end up shared by reference.
		</para>

		<para>
		If <pre>flat</pre> is true, the copy is flat, with the sub-index types and aggregator
		types simply not included. It's the &Cpp; analog of the Perl method
		<pre>flatCopy()</pre>. This allows to re-create the partial index hierarchies,
		recursively flat-copying the parts that need to be included.
		</para>

<pre>
IndexType *deepCopy(HoldRowTypes *holder) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Create a deep copy, up to and including the row types. See the
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_tabtype" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		and
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_copy" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;
		for the detailed explanation. When you deep-copy a table type,
		the <pre>holder</pre> argument propagates recurively to all the
		index types in it.
		</para>

		<para>
		There are great many more methods on the IndexType, that are used to
		maintain the index trees, but you don't need to look at them unless you
		are interested in the inner workings of the Triceps tables.
		</para>
	</sect1>
