<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_hashidx">
		<title>HashedIndexType reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>HashedIndexType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The HashedIndexType is defined in <pre>type/HashedIndexType.h</pre>. It also
		allows to specify its only argument, the selection of the key fields,
		in the constructor, or set it later with a chainable call:
		</para>

<pre>
HashedIndexType(NameSet *key = NULL);
static HashedIndexType *make(NameSet *key = NULL);
HashedIndexType *setKey(NameSet *key);
</pre>

		<para>
		One way or the other, the key has to be set, or a missing key will be
		detected as an error at the initialization time. Obviously, all the
		conditions described in the Perl API apply: the key fields must be
		present in the table's row type, and so on.
		</para>

		<para>
		The key can be read back using the parent class method
		<pre>IndexType::getKey()</pre>. The value returned there is a
		<pre>const NameSet*</pre>, telling you that the key NameSet must not be
		changed afterward.
		</para>

		<para>
		The check for <pre>equals()</pre> requires that the key fields are the same
		(not the exact same NameSet object, but its contents being the same).
		The check for <pre>match()</pre> is more tricky and depends on whether
		the index type has been initialized. The match check of initialized types
		is correct, while for the uninitialized types it's simplified.
		This may lead to slightly surprising effects when the two indexes match
		inside the initialized table types but their uninitialized copies
		don't.  However the comparison of the uninitialized index types is
		probably not that usable anyway.
		</para>

		<para>
		The simplified <pre>match()</pre> check is the same as <pre>equals()</pre>:
		the list of key fields must be the same.
		However this has a tricky effect: if two table types have matching row
		types with different field names, and the same Hashed indexes differing
		only in the key field names (following the difference in the row
		types), these table types will be considered non-matching because their
		hashed indexes are non-matching.
		</para>

		<para>
		After the indexes are initialized, they can do a better match check.
		They can find their table types, and from there the
		row types. And then compare if the keys refer to the matching fields or
		not, even if their names are different. The condition then becomes that
		the key fields are matching in the row type, even if their names are not.
		</para>

	</sect1>
