<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_sortidx">
		<title>SortedIndexType reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>SortedIndexType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The SortedIndexType is defined in <pre>type/SortedIndexType.h</pre>, and provides
		a way to define any custom sorting criteria. That is done by defining
		your condition class, derived from SortedIndexCondition, and passing it
		to the SortedIndexType. Because of this the index type itself is
		simple, all the complex things are in the condition:
		</para>

<pre>
SortedIndexType(Onceref<SortedIndexCondition> sc);
static SortedIndexType *make(Onceref<SortedIndexCondition> sc);
SortedIndexCondition *getCondition() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		A few example of the sort conditions are discussed below, they can also
		be found in <pre>type/test/t_xSortedIndex.cpp</pre>.  More examples
		are available in <pre>type/test/t_TableType.cpp</pre> and in
		<pre>perl/Triceps/PerlSortCondition.*</pre>.  SortedIndexCondition
		provides a set of virtual methods that can be re-defined in the
		subclass to create a custom condition. Indeed, some of them must be
		re-defined, since they are pure virtual.
		</para>

		<para>
		The following basic example defines only
		the absolute minimum of methods. It sorts by an int32 field, whose
		index (starting as usual from 0) is specified in the constructor:
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>SortedIndexCondition</primary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
class Int32SortCondition : public SortedIndexCondition
{
public:
	// @param idx - index of field to use for comparison (starting from 0)
	Int32SortCondition(int idx) :
		idx_(idx)
	{ }

	Int32SortCondition(const Int32SortCondition *other, Table *t) :
		SortedIndexCondition(other, t),
		idx_(other->idx_)
	{ }

	virtual SortedIndexCondition *copy() const
	{
		return new Int32SortCondition(*this);
	}

	virtual TreeIndexType::Less *tableCopy(Table *t) const
	{
		return new Int32SortCondition(this, t);
	}

	virtual void initialize(Erref &errors, TableType *tabtype, SortedIndexType *indtype)
	{
		SortedIndexCondition::initialize(errors, tabtype, indtype);
		if (idx_ < 0)
			errors.f("The index must not be negative.");
		if (rt_->fieldCount() <= idx_)
			errors.f("The row type must contain at least %d fields.", idx_+1);

		if (!errors->hasError()) { // can be checked only if index is within range
			const RowType::Field &fld = rt_->fields()[idx_];
			if (fld.type_->getTypeId() != Type::TT_INT32)
				errors.f("The field at index %d must be an int32.", idx_);
			if (fld.arsz_ != RowType::Field::AR_SCALAR)
				errors.f("The field at index %d must not be an array.", idx_);
		}
	}

	virtual bool equals(const SortedIndexCondition *sc) const
	{
		// the cast is safe to do because the caller has checked the typeid
		Int32SortCondition *other = (Int32SortCondition *)sc;
		return idx_ == other->idx_;
	}

	virtual bool match(const SortedIndexCondition *sc) const
	{
		return equals(sc);
	}

	virtual void printTo(string &res, const string &indent = "", const string &subindent = "  ") const
	{
		res.append(strprintf("Int32Sort(%d)", idx_));
	}

	virtual bool operator() (const RowHandle *rh1, const RowHandle *rh2) const
	{
		const Row *row1 = rh1->getRow();
		const Row *row2 = rh2->getRow();
		{
			bool v1 = rt_->isFieldNull(row1, idx_);
			bool v2 = rt_->isFieldNull(row2, idx_);
			if (v1 > v2) // isNull at true goes first, so the direction is opposite
				return true;
			if (v1 < v2)
				return false;
		}
		{
			int32_t v1 = rt_->getInt32(row1, idx_);
			int32_t v2 = rt_->getInt32(row2, idx_);
			return (v1 < v2);
		}
	}

	int idx_;
};

...

Autoref<IndexType> it = new SortedIndexType(new Int32SortCondition(1));
</pre>

		<para>
		There are four kinds of constructors for a sort condition:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			One used to create the SortedIndexType in the first place, specifying
			the condition argument, such as Int32SortCondition(int idx) here.
			</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			<para>
			The copy constructor, used to copy the sort condition when its
			index gets copied. It should copy all the elements
			that could be modified by someone else but can share the references
			for the reference-counted elements that are unchangeable.
			Feel free to just use the default compiler-created
			copy constructor, as Int32SortCondition did, unless you really
			need it to do something more smart.
			</para>
			</listitem>

			<indexterm>
				<primary>RowType</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			The deep-copy constructor, used when SortedIndexType gets deep-copied,
			including the copying of the RowTypes and other
			referenced objects that are more efficient to not share between
			different threads.  See the discussion of the deep-copying in
			<xref linkend="sc_cpp_tabtype" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
			Most of the sort conditions would not have any row types in them,
			nor anything deeper to copy than in the normal copy constructor,
			so they don't need to bother. The base class provides the default <pre>deepCopy()</pre>
			method that simply reverts to calling <pre>copy()</pre>, so no separate constructor
			is used.  If you need to define it, the typical prototype for the
			deep-copy constructor will be:
			</para>
<pre>
MySortCondition(const MySortCondition &other, HoldRowTypes *holder);
</pre>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			<para>
			The table-copy constructor. The need for this one is driven by the
			error reporting from the sort condition. For most of the sort condition
			classes defined directly in &Cpp; it doesn't matter, they just can't
			experience any errors. But when the interpreted code is involved,
			the possibility of errors arises and something has to be done
			about them, and thus the infrastructure has to accomodate.
			</para>

			<indexterm>
				<primary>Table</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
			When the comparison operator
			runs, throwing an Exception from the middle of the STL map logic
			is not a good idea. I've actually looked into the GCC implementation,
			and it would leak memory and be unhappy in this situation. This
			means that the sort condition has to report the error back to the
			Table in some other way. Which means that it has to have a link
			back to the table, and that link gets provided in the field
			<pre>table_</pre>. But that means that the sort condition instance
			gets tied to a table. And normally a sort condition belongs to
			an index type which belongs to a table type which can be shared
			by multiple tables. This dilemma is solved by making a copy
			of the sort condition for each created table. 
			</para>

			<para>
			This copying
			and setting of the Table pointer gets handled by the sort
			condition method tableCopy()
			which in turn calls the table-copy constructor. Most of the work is
			done by the base class, you just need to pass through the arguments
			and copy your extra fields, as shown in the example.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		There are three kinds of copy methods for a sort condition:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			<pre>copy()</pre> copies the sort condition by calling the copy constructor,
			as shown above.  In particular, the
			SortedIndexType constructor makes a private copy of the condition, and
			remembers that copy, not the original.
			</para>
			</listitem>

			<indexterm>
				<primary>RowType</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			<pre>deepCopy()</pre> copies the sort condition all the way deep, as described in 
			<xref linkend="sc_cpp_tabtype" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;,
			by calling the deep-copy constructor. Most of the sort conditions don't
			need to bother since they don't have any RowTypes in them, the base
			class implements this method by calling <pre>copy()</pre>. If you need one, the
			typical implementation looks like:
			</para>

<pre>
IndexType *MySortCondition::deepCopy(HoldRowTypes *holder) const
{
	return new MySortCondition(*this, holder);
}
</pre>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			<para>
			<pre>tableCopy()</pre> creates a per-table instance of the copy condition,
			by calling the table-copy constructor.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		The method <pre>initialize()</pre> is called at the table type initialization
		time. The argument <pre>errors</pre> is an already allocated Errors object to
		return the error messages in, <pre>tabtype</pre> is the table type where the
		initialization is happening, and <pre>indtype</pre> is the index type that owns
		this condition. Also the field <pre>rt_</pre> gets magically initialized to the
		table's row type reference before the sort condition initialization is
		called. This method is expected to do all the initialization of the
		internal state, check for all the errors, and return these errors if
		found.
		</para>

		<para>
		To be more systematic, the following useful fields are defined in the
		sort condition base class:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<const RowType> rt_;
Table *table_;
intptr_t rhOffset_;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandle</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		<pre>rt_</pre> is set to NULL on construction and the gets properly set when the
		SortedIndexType is initialized, before it calls the initialization of the
		sort condition. <pre>table_</pre> is also NULL to start with and gets set
		in <pre>tableCopy()</pre>, as described above. <pre>table_</pre> can be used by the
		comparison operator to report the fatal errors back to the table,
		as described in more detail below.
		<pre>rhOffset_</pre> is used by the more advanced sort conditions that
		want to cache some per-row information in the RowHandle, I'll show
		another example of that. It's the offset of that cached data in the
		RowHandle.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>equals()</pre> and <pre>match()</pre> compare two conditions for equality and match.
		Before they get called, the caller checks that both conditions are of
		the same type (i.e. have the same &Cpp; typeid), so it's safe to cast the
		second condition's pointer to our type. The easiest way to define
		<pre>match()</pre> is to make it the same as <pre>equals()</pre>. These methods may be called
		on both uninitialized and initialized conditions; if not initialized
		then the field <pre>rt_</pre> will be NULL.
		</para>

		<para>
		<pre>printTo()</pre> appends the printout of this index's description to a string.
		For the simple single-line printouts it just appends to the result
		string. The multi-line prints have to handle the indenting correctly,
		as is described in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_types" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		Finally, the <pre>operator()</pre> implements the comparison for <quote>Less</quote>: it gets
		two row handles and returns true if the first one contains a row that
		is <quote>less</quote> (i.e. goes before in the sorting order) than the second one.
		The reason for why it's done like this is that the SortedIndexCondition
		is really a Less comparator class for the STL tree that had grown a few
		extra methods.
		</para>

		<para>
		This example shows how to compare a value consisting of multiple
		elements. Even though this sort condition sorts by only one field, it
		first compares separately for NULL in that field, and then for the
		actual value. For each element you must:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			find the values of the element in both rows;
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			compare for <quote>&lt;</quote>, and if so, return true;
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			compare for <quote>&gt;</quote>, and if so, return false;
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			otherwise (if they are equal), fall through to the next element.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		The last element doesn't have to go through the whole procedure, it can
		just return the result of <quote>&lt;</quote>. And in this case the comparison for NULL
		wants the NULL value go before all the non-NULL values, so the result
		of true must go before false, and the comparison signs are reversed.
		It's real important that the second comparison, normally for <quote>&gt;</quote>, can
		not be skipped (except for the last element). If you skip it, you will
		make a mess of the data and will spend a lot of time trying to figure
		out, what is going on.
		</para>

		<para>
		That's it for the basics, the minimal subset of the methods that has to
		be defined. Now let's look at some more advances subjects.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>sticky error</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		What if <pre>operator()</pre> needs to to report an error? It has to set
		the sticky error in the table and return false:
		</para>

<pre>
Erref err;
err.f("error message");
table_->setStickyError(err);
return false;
</pre>

		<para>
		One more method that can be supported in the sort condition is <pre>getKey()</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual const NameSet *getKey() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		The default implementation just returns NULL, thus saying that the
		key is not available.
		The SortedIndexType's <pre>getKey()</pre> is really just a wrapper for the
		SortedIndexCondition's <pre>getKey()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		To show <pre>getKey()</pre> and a bit more
		techniques, so I've done a fairly big extension of the previous
		example. Now it can compare multiple fields, and the fields are
		specified by names. The only part missing from it being a general
		OrderedIndexType is the support of all the field types, not just int32.
		</para>

<pre>
class MultiInt32SortCondition : public SortedIndexCondition
{
public:
	// @param key - the key fields specification
	MultiInt32SortCondition(NameSet *key):
		key_(key)
	{ }

	MultiInt32SortCondition(const MultiInt32SortCondition *other, Table *t) :
		SortedIndexCondition(other, t),
		idxs_(other->idxs_),
		key_(other->key_)
	{ }

	virtual SortedIndexCondition *copy() const
	{
		return new MultiInt32SortCondition(*this);
	}

	virtual TreeIndexType::Less *tableCopy(Table *t) const
	{
		return new MultiInt32SortCondition(this, t);
	}

	virtual void initialize(Erref &errors, TableType *tabtype, SortedIndexType *indtype)
	{
		SortedIndexCondition::initialize(errors, tabtype, indtype);
		idxs_.clear();

		for (int i = 0; i < key_->size(); i++) {
			const string &s = (*key_)[i];
			int n = rt_->findIdx(s);
			if (n < 0) {
				errors.f("No such field '%s'.", s.c_str());
				continue;
			}
			const RowType::Field &fld = rt_->fields()[n];
			if (fld.type_->getTypeId() != Type::TT_INT32) {
				errors.f("The field '%s' must be an int32.", s.c_str());
				continue;
			}
			if (fld.arsz_ != RowType::Field::AR_SCALAR) {
				errors.f("The field '%s' must not be an array.", s.c_str());
				continue;
			}
			idxs_.push_back(n);
		}
	}

	virtual bool equals(const SortedIndexCondition *sc) const
	{
		// the cast is safe to do because the caller has checked the typeid
		MultiInt32SortCondition *other = (MultiInt32SortCondition *)sc;

		// names must be the same
		if (!key_->equals(other->key_))
			return false;

		// and if initialized, the indexs must be the same too
		if (!rt_.isNull()) {
			if (idxs_.size() != other->idxs_.size())
				return false;

			for (int i = 0; i < idxs_.size(); i++) {
				if (idxs_[i] != other->idxs_[i])
					return false;
			}
		}

		return true;
	}

	virtual bool match(const SortedIndexCondition *sc) const
	{
		MultiInt32SortCondition *other = (MultiInt32SortCondition *)sc;
		if (rt_.isNull()) {
			// not initialized, check by names
			return key_->equals(other->key_);
		} else {
			// initialized, check by indexes
			if (idxs_.size() != other->idxs_.size())
				return false;

			for (int i = 0; i < idxs_.size(); i++) {
				if (idxs_[i] != other->idxs_[i])
					return false;
			}
			return true;
		}
	}

	virtual void printTo(string &res, const string &indent = "", const string &subindent = "  ") const
	{
		res.append("MultiInt32Sort(");
		for (NameSet::iterator i = key_->begin(); i != key_->end(); ++i) {
			res.append(*i);
			res.append(", "); // extra comma after last field doesn't hurt
		}
		res.append(")");
	}

	virtual const NameSet *getKey() const
	{
		return key_;
	}

	virtual bool operator() (const RowHandle *rh1, const RowHandle *rh2) const
	{
		const Row *row1 = rh1->getRow();
		const Row *row2 = rh2->getRow();

		int sz = idxs_.size();
		for (int i = 0; i < sz; i++) {
			int idx = idxs_[i];
			{
				bool v1 = rt_->isFieldNull(row1, idx);
				bool v2 = rt_->isFieldNull(row2, idx);
				if (v1 > v2) // isNull at true goes first, so the direction is opposite
					return true;
				if (v1 < v2)
					return false;
			}
			{
				int32_t v1 = rt_->getInt32(row1, idx);
				int32_t v2 = rt_->getInt32(row2, idx);
				if (v1 < v2)
					return true;
				if (v1 > v2)
					return false;
			}
		}
		return false; // falls through on equality, which is not less
	}

	vector<int> idxs_;
	Autoref<NameSet> key_;
};
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>NameSet</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The key is specified as a NameSet in the constructor. Unlike the HashedIndexType, there
		is no changing the key later, it must be specified in the constructor,
		and must not be NULL. The same as with HashedIndexType, the original
		name set becomes referenced by this sort condition and all its copies.
		So don't change and don't even use the original condition any more
		after you've passed it to the sort condition. This sort condition doesn't
		care to copy the NameSet in the deep copy, just leaves the deep copy the
		same as the default.
		</para>

		<para>
		The initialization translates the field names to indexes (um, that's a
		confusing double usage of the word "index", here it's like "array
		indexes") in the row type, and checks that the fields are as expected.
		</para>

		<para>
		The equality and match checks follow the fashion of HashedIndexType:
		if not initialized, they rely on field names, if initialized, they
		take the field indexes into the consideration (for equality both the
		names and indexes must be equal, for matching, only the indexes need to
		be equal).
		</para>

		<para>
		The printing and copying is nothing particularly new and fancy.
		<pre>getKey()</pre> simply returns back the key. This feels a bit like an
		anti-climax, a whole big example for this little one-liner, but again,
		that's not the only thing that this example shows.
		</para>

		<para>
		The <quote>less</quote> comparison function now loops through all the fields in the
		key. It can't do the shortcuts in the int32 comparison part any more,
		so that has been expanded to the full condition. If the whole loop
		falls through without returning, it means that the key fields in both
		rows are equal, so it returns false.
		</para>

		<para>
		And an example, of its use, the key argument is created similarly
		to the hashed index:
		</para>


<pre>
Autoref<IndexType> it = new SortedIndexType(new MultiInt32SortCondition(
	NameSet::make()->add("b")->add("c")
));
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandle</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Now we get to another advanced feature that has been mentioned before
		in the description of the row handles but is not accessible from Perl.
		A row handle contains a chunk of memory for every index type in the
		table. It is called a <quote>row handle section</quote>. At the very least this
		chunk of memory contains the iterator in an index of that type, which
		allows to navigate through the table and to delete the row handles from
		the table efficiently.
		</para>

		<para>
		But an index type may request more memory (the same fixed amount for each
		row handle) to store some row-specific information. For example, the
		hashed index type stores the value of the hash in its section, and uses this
		value for the efficient comparisons.
		</para>

		<para>
		A sort condition may request and use memory in this section of a
		SortedIndexType. It is done by defining a few more virtual methods that
		handle the row section.
		</para>

		<para>
		I could have made an example of the Hashed index re-implementation
		through the Sorted interface, but it's kind of boring, since you could
		as well look directly at the source code of the HashedIndexType.
		Instead I want to show a different kind of index that doesn't use the
		data in the rows for comparison at all but keeps the rows in the order
		they were inserted. Like a more expensive variety of FIFO index type.
		It's also a bit of a preview of a future feature. It assigns a new
		auto-generated sequence number to each row handle, and uses that
		sequence number for ordering. Later you can find the row handle quickly
		if you know its sequence number. If a table contains multiple copies
		of a row, the sequence numbers allow you to tell, which copy you are
		dealing with. It comes handy for such things as results of joins
		without a natural primary key. Of course, the usefulness of this
		preview is limited by the fact that there is no place for the sequence
		numbers in the rowops, and thus there is no way to propagate the
		sequence numbers in the model. That would have to be addressed before
		it becomes a full feature.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>sequence number</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Now, you might ask, why not just add an extra field and put the
		sequence number in there? Sure, that would work too, and also solve the
		issue with the propagation in the rowops. However this means that as a
		row goes through a table, it gets copied to set the sequence number in
		it, which is less efficient. So ultimately keeping the sequence numbers
		<quote>on the side</quote> is more beneficial.
		</para>

		<para>
		The implementation is:
		</para>

<pre>
class SeqSortCondition : public SortedIndexCondition
{
protected:
	class SeqRhSection : public TreeIndexType::BasicRhSection
	{
	public:
		SeqRhSection(int64_t val) :
			seq_(val)
		{ }

		int64_t seq_; // the sequence number of this row handle
	};

public:
	SeqSortCondition() :
		seq_(0)
	{ }

	SeqSortCondition(const SeqSortCondition *other, Table *t) :
		SortedIndexCondition(other, t),
		seq_(other->seq_)
	{ }

	virtual SortedIndexCondition *copy() const
	{
		return new SeqSortCondition(*this);
	}

	virtual TreeIndexType::Less *tableCopy(Table *t) const
	{
		return new SeqSortCondition(this, t);
	}

	virtual void initialize(Erref &errors, TableType *tabtype, SortedIndexType *indtype)
	{
		SortedIndexCondition::initialize(errors, tabtype, indtype);
		seq_ = 0;
	}

	virtual bool equals(const SortedIndexCondition *sc) const
	{
		return true;
	}

	virtual bool match(const SortedIndexCondition *sc) const
	{
		return true;
	}

	virtual void printTo(string &res, const string &indent = "", const string &subindent = "  ") const
	{
		res.append("Sequenced");
	}

	virtual size_t sizeOfRhSection() const
	{
		return sizeof(SeqRhSection);
	}

	virtual void initRowHandleSection(RowHandle *rh) const
	{
		// initialize the Seq part, the general Sorted index
		// will initialize the iterator
	    SeqRhSection *rs = rh->get<SeqRhSection>(rhOffset_);
	    new(rs) SeqRhSection(seq_++);
	}
	
	virtual void clearRowHandleSection(RowHandle *rh) const
	{ 
	    // clear the iterator by calling its destructor
	    SeqRhSection *rs = rh->get<SeqRhSection>(rhOffset_);
	    rs->~SeqRhSection();
	}
	
	virtual void copyRowHandleSection(RowHandle *rh, const RowHandle *fromrh) const
	{
	    SeqRhSection *rs = rh->get<SeqRhSection>(rhOffset_);
	    SeqRhSection *fromrs = fromrh->get<SeqRhSection>(rhOffset_);
	    
	    // initialize the iterator by calling its copy constructor inside the placement,
		// the sequence number gets copied too
	    new(rs) SeqRhSection(*fromrs);
	}
	
	// Helper method to read the sequence from the row handle,
	// can also be used by the end-user. The row handle must as usual
	// belong to a table of this type.
	int64_t getSeq(const RowHandle *rh) const
	{
	    return rh->get<SeqRhSection>(rhOffset_)->seq_;
	}

	// Helper method to set the sequence in the row handle.
	// May be used only on the rows that are not in a table.
	void setSeq(const RowHandle *rh, int64_t val) const
	{
		if (rh->isInTable()) {
			throw Exception("Attempted to change the sequence on a row in table.", true);
		}
	    rh->get<SeqRhSection>(rhOffset_)->seq_ = val;
	}

	virtual bool operator() (const RowHandle *rh1, const RowHandle *rh2) const
	{
		return getSeq(rh1) < getSeq(rh2);
	}

	mutable int64_t seq_; // the next sequence number to assign
};

...
Autoref<IndexType> it = new SortedIndexType(new SeqSortCondition());
...
</pre>

		<para>
		The nested class SeqRhSection defines the structure of the
		section that a SortedIndexType with a SeqSortCondition allocates in the RowHandle.
		The section class for a sort condition must always inherit from
		TreeIndexType::BasicRhSection, to get the general SortedIndexType
		parts from it, such as the iterator. Any
		extra fields are owned by the sort condition.
		</para>

		<para>
		The SeqSortCondition contains the sequence number generator seq_ (not
		to be confused with the same-named field seq_ in SeqRhSection), that
		gets initialized to 0, and will be incremented from there. Since each
		table will get its own copy of the condition, each of them will be counting
		independently. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The <pre>equals()</pre> and <pre>match()</pre> always return true because there is nothing
		configurable in this sort condition.
		</para>

		<para>
		The new features start at <pre>sizeOfRhSection()</pre>. The size of each row
		handle in a table type is the same, and is computed by asking every
		index type in it at initialization time and adding up the totals (plus
		alignment and some fixed amount of basic data). <pre>sizeOfRhSection()</pre> does
		its part by telling the caller the size of SeqRhSection.
		</para>

		<para>
		Then each row handle section must provide the ways to construct and
		destruct it. Naturally, to save space, a section must have no virtual
		table, so like for the rows, a separate method in the index type acts
		as its virtual destructor. And there is no such thing as a virtual
		constructor in &Cpp;, which gets simulated through more methods in the
		index type. The SortedIndexType delegates most of this work to the sort
		condition in it. The basic constructor is <pre>initRowHandleSection()</pre>, the
		copy constructor is <pre>copyRowHandleSection()</pre>, and the destructor is
		<pre>clearRowHandleSection()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		Each of them gets the location of this index type's section in the row
		handle using:
		</para>

<pre>
SeqRhSection *rs = rh->get<SeqRhSection>(rhOffset_);
</pre>

		<para>
		The field <pre>rhOffset_</pre> gets initialized by the SortedIndexType machinery
		before either of these methods gets ever called. Here <pre>rs</pre> points to the
		raw bytes, on which the placement constructors and the explicit
		destructor are called.
		</para>

		<para>
		The methods <pre>getSeq()</pre> and <pre>setSeq()</pre> are not virtual, they are unique to
		this SeqSortCondition. They allow to read the sequence from a row
		handle or set the sequence in it. Naturally, the sequence number may be
		changed only when the row handle is not in the table yet, or it would
		mess up the indexing horribly. It's OK to throw the exceptions from
		<pre>setSeq()</pre> and <pre>getSeq()</pre> since they are called directly from the user code
		and won't confuse any Triceps code along the way.
		</para>

		<para>
		If you want to find a row handle in the table by its sequence number,
		you start with creating a new row handle (which can even use an empty
		row). That new row handle will have a new sequence number assigned to
		it, but it doesn't matter, because next you call <pre>setSeq()</pre> and overwrite
		it with your desired number. Then you use this row handle to call
		<pre>find()</pre> or <pre>delete()</pre> on the table as usual. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The creation goes like this:
		</para>

<pre>
Rhref rh1(table, r1);
sc->setSeq(rh1, desired_number);
</pre>

		<para>
		The class Rhref, a row handle reference, is similar in spirit to Rowref,
		and is described in detail in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_rowhandle" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		Or to read the number, you do:
		</para>

<pre>
int64_t seq = sc->getSeq(rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		Here <pre>sc</pre> is the exact initialized sort condition from the actual table
		type (not from the exact table, since you can't get the sort condition from a table,
		but the table type is good enough). If you use a wrong or uninitialized
		sort condition, the <pre>rhOffset_</pre> in it will likely be wrong, and
		will cause all kinds of memory corruption. You can get the sort
		condition from a table type like this:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<SortedIndexType> ixt = dynamic_cast<SortedIndexType *>(tt->findSubIndex("primary"));
Autoref<SeqSortCondition> sc = dynamic_cast<SeqSortCondition *>(ixt->getCondition());
</pre>

		<para>
		You don't have to use the dynamic cast but it's safer, and since you'd
		normally do it once at the model setup time and then just keep using
		the value, there is no noticeable performance penalty for it.
		</para>

	</sect1>

