<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_gadget">
		<title>Gadget reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Gadget</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The Gadget is unique to the &Cpp; API, it has no parallels in Perl.
		It had also become somewhat obsolete in the recent times but still
		clinging to life for now.
		</para>

		<para>
		Gadget is a base class, a single-threaded Starget, defined in 
		<pre>sched/Gadget.h</pre>, its object being a
		something with an output label. And the details of what this something
		is, are determined by the subclass. Presumably, it also has some kind
		of inputs but it's up to the subclass. The Gadget itself defines only
		the output label. To make a concrete example, a table is a gadget, and
		every aggregator in the table is also a gadget. However the <quote>pre</quote> and
		<quote>dump</quote> labels of the table are not gadgets, they are just extra labels
		strapped on the side.
		</para>

		<para>
		The reasons for the Gadget creation are mostly historic by now.
		At some point it seemed important to have the ability to associate a
		particular enqueueing mode with each output label. Most tables might be
		using <pre>EM_CALL</pre> but some, ones in a loop, would use <pre>EM_FORK</pre>, and those
		that don't need to produce the streaming output would use <pre>EM_IGNORE</pre>.
		This approach didn't work out as well as it seemed at first, and now is
		outright deprecated: the tables have <pre>EM_CALL</pre> hardcoded everywhere, and there are the
		newer and better ways to handle the loops. The whole Gadget thing
		should be removed at some point but for now I'll just describe it as
		it is.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>EnqMode</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		As the result of that history, the enqueueing mode constants are
		defined in the Gadget class, enum EnqMode: <pre>EM_SCHEDULE</pre>, <pre>EM_FORK</pre>,
		<pre>EM_CALL</pre>, <pre>EM_IGNORE</pre>.
		</para>

<pre>
static const char *emString(int enval, const char *def = "???");
static int stringEm(const char *str);
</pre>

		<para>
		Convert from the enqueueing mode constant to string, and back.
		</para>

<pre>
Gadget(Unit *unit, EnqMode mode, const string &name, const_Onceref<RowType> rt = (const RowType*)NULL);
</pre>

		<para>
		The Gadget constructor is protected, since Gadget is intended to be
		used only as a base class, and never instantiated directly. The
		row type can be left undefined if it isn't known yet and
		initialized later. The output label will be created as soon as the row type
		is known. The
		enqueueing mode may also be changed later, so initially it can be set
		to anything. All this is intended only to split the initialization in a
		more convenient way, once the Gadget components are set, they must not
		be changed any more.
		</para>

		<para>
		The output label of the Gadget is a DummyLabel, and it shares the name
		with the Gadget. So if you want to differentiate that label with a
		suffix in the name, you have to give the suffixed name to the whole
		Gadget. For example, the Table constructor does:
		</para>

<pre>
Gadget(unit, Gadget::EM_CALL, name + ".out", rowt),
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Unit</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A Gadget keeps a reference to both its output label and its unit. This
		means that the unit won't disappears from under a Gadget, but to avoid
		the circular references, the Unit must not have references to the
		Gadgets (having references to their output labels is fine).
		</para>

<pre>
void setEnqMode(EnqMode mode);
void setRowType(const_Onceref<RowType> rt);
</pre>

		<para>
		The protected methods to finish the initialization. Once the values are
		set, they must not be changed any more. Calling <pre>setRowType()</pre> creates
		the output label.
		</para>

<pre>
EnqMode getEnqMode() const;
const string &getName() const;
Unit *getUnit() const;
Label *getLabel() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the gadget's information. The label will be returned only
		after it's initialized (i.e. the row type is known), before then
		<pre>getLabel()</pre> would return NULL. And yes, it's <pre>getLabel()</pre>, <b>not</b>
		<pre>getOutputLabel()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The rest of the methods are for convenience of sending the rows to the
		output label. They are protected, since they are intended for the
		Gadget subclasses (which in turn may decide to make them public).
		</para>

<pre>
void send(const Row *row, Rowop::Opcode opcode) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Construct a Rowop from the given row and opcode, and enqueue it to the
		output label according to the gadget's enqueueing method. This is the
		most typical use.
		</para>

<pre>
void sendDelayed(Tray *dest, const Row *row, Rowop::Opcode opcode) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Create a Rowop and put it into the <pre>dest</pre> tray. The rowop will have the
		enqueueing mode populated according to the Gadget's setting. This
		method is used when the whole set of the rowops needs to be generated
		before any of them can be enqueued, such as when a Table computes its
		aggregators. After the delayed tray is fully generated, it can be
		enqueued with <pre>Unit::enqueueDelayedTray()</pre>, which will consult each
		rowop's enqueueing method and process it accordingly. Again, this stuff
		exists for the historic reasons, and will likely be removed somewhere
		soon. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
