<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_table">
		<title>Table reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Table</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Gadget</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The Table is defined in <pre>table/Table.h</pre>. It inherits from Gadget, with
		the table's output label being the gadget's output label. Naturally,
		it's an Starget and usable from one thread only.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>TableType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Its constructor is not public, and it's created from the TableType
		with its  method <pre>makeTable()</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<Table> t = tabType->makeTable(unit, "t");
</pre>

		<para>
		The arguments are the unit where the table will belong and the name of
		the table.
		</para>

		<para>
		Yeah, it's kind of weird that in Perl the method <pre>makeTable()</pre> is defined
		on Unit, and in &Cpp; on TableType. But if I remember correctly, it has
		to do with avoiding the circular dependency in the &Cpp; header files. 
		</para>

		<para>
		For the reference, that TableType method is:
		</para>

<pre>
Onceref<Table> makeTable(Unit *unit, const string &name) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		The table has a large number of methods, grouped into multiple subsets.
		</para>

<pre>
const string &getName() const;
Unit *getUnit() const;
Label *getLabel() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		These methods are inherited from the Gadget. The only special thing to
		remember is that <pre>getLabel()</pre> returns the table's output label.
		Technically, <pre>getName()</pre> has an overriding implementation in the Table,
		to return the table's proper name while its output label and the underlying
		gadget have the suffix <quote>.out</quote> appended to their name.
		</para>

<pre>
const TableType *getType() const;
const RowType *getRowType() const;
const RowHandleType *getRhType() const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandleType</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Get back the type of the table, of its rows, and of its row handles.
		There is not much direct use for the RowHandleType, the Table uses it
		internally to construct the RowHandles.
		</para>

<pre>
Label *getInputLabel() const;
Label *getPreLabel() const;
Label *getDumpLabel() const;
Label *getAggregatorLabel(const string &agname) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the assorted labels (remember, <pre>getLabel()</pre> inherited from Gadget
		is used for the output label). The aggregator label getter takes the name of
		the aggregator (as was defined in the TableType) as an argument.
		</para>

<pre>
FnReturn *fnReturn() const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>FnReturn</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Get the FnReturn of this table's outputs. It gets created and
		remembered on the first call, and the subsequent calls return the same
		object.  It has a few labels with the fixed names: <quote>out</quote>, <quote>pre</quote> and
		<quote>dump</quote>, and a label for each aggregator with the aggregator's name. It
		could throw an Exception if you name an aggregator to conflict with one
		of the fixed labels, which you should not. The FnReturn's name will be
		<quote><i>tableName</i>.fret</quote>.
		</para>

		<para>
		Next go the operations on the table (and of course the table may also
		be modified by sending the rowops to its input label).
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandle *makeRowHandle(const Row *row) const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandle</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Rhref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Create a row handle for a row. Remember, the row handles are
		reference-counted, and also have the special kind of references with
		Rhref. So the returned pointer should be stored in an Rhref. The row
		handle created will not be inserted into the table yet.
		</para>

<pre>
bool insert(RowHandle *rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		Insert a row handle into the table. This invokes all the row
		replacement policies along the way. If the handle is already in the
		table, does nothing and returns false. May also return false if a
		replacement policy refuses the row, but in practice there are no such
		refusing policies yet. Otherwise returns true.
		</para>

		<para>
		It may throw an Exception. It may throw directly if the row handle
		doesn't belong to this table or propagate the exception up from the
		functions it calls: since the
		execution involves calling the output labels and such, an exception
		might be thrown from there.
		</para>

<pre>
bool insertRow(const Row *row);
</pre>

		<para>
		The version that combines the row handle construction and insertion.
		Unlike Perl, in &Cpp; this method is named differently instead of
		overloading. The comments about the replacement policies and return
		code, and about exceptions apply here too.
		</para>

<pre>
void remove(RowHandle *rh);
</pre>

		<para>
		Remove a row handle from the table. If the handle is not in the table,
		silently does nothing. May throw an Exception.
		</para>

<pre>
bool deleteRow(const Row *row);
</pre>

		<para>
		Find a matching row and delete it (internally this involves creating
		a new RowHandle for the argument row and finding it in the first leaf
		index by value, and disposing of that temporary row handle afterwards). 
		Returns true if the row was found and removed, false if not found. May
		throw an Exception.
		</para>

<pre>
void clear(size_t limit = 0);
</pre>

		<para>
		Clear the table by removing all the rows from it. The removed rows are
		sent as usual to the <quote>pre</quote> and <quote>out</quote> labels. If the limit is not 0, no
		more than that number of the rows will be removed. The rows are removed
		in the usual order of the first leaf index.
		</para>

		<para>
		Next go the iteration methods. The rule of thumb is that for them a
		NULL row handle pointer means <quote>end of iteration</quote> or <quote>not found</quote> (or
		sometimes <quote>bad arguments</quote>). And they can handle silently the NULL row handles
		on the input, just returning NULL on the output.
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandle *begin() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the first row handle in the default order of the first leaf index.
		If the table is empty, returns NULL.
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandle *beginIdx(IndexType *ixt) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the first handle in the order of a particular index. The index type
		must belong to this table's type. For an incorrect index type it
		returns NULL (perhaps in the future this will be changed to an
		exception).
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandle *next(const RowHandle *cur) const;
RowHandle *nextIdx(IndexType *ixt, const RowHandle *cur) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the next row handle in the order of the default or specific index.
		Returns NULL after the last handle. It's safe to pass the current row
		handle as NULL, the result will be NULL, as well as on any other error.
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandle *firstOfGroupIdx(IndexType *ixt, const RowHandle *cur) const;
RowHandle *lastOfGroupIdx(IndexType *ixt, const RowHandle *cur) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the first or last row handle in the same group as the current row
		according to a non-leaf index. The NULL current handle will cause NULL
		returned. See the details in the description of the Perl API.
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandle *nextGroupIdx(IndexType *ixt, const RowHandle *cur) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the first row handle of the next group. The return will be NULL if
		the current group was the last one, or if the current handle is NULL.
		</para>

		<para>
		The iteration loops may look as:
		</para>

<pre>
for (RowHandle *iter = t->begin(); iter != NULL; iter = t->next(iter)) {
	...
}

for (Rhref iter(t, t->beginIdx(level3)); !iter->isNull();
		iter = t->nextIdx(level3, iter)) {
	...
}
</pre>

		<para>
		Note that if the table does not change during the iteration (or at the
		very least if the row handle at the iterator is not being affected by
		the changes), the iterator doesn't have to be kept in an Rhref.
		A pointer to RowHandle is perfectly adequate and more efficient since
		it doesn't modify the reference counts. However you must be perfectly
		sure that the table will not be changed by any of the code in any
		labels called from the iteration loop.
		</para>

		<para>
		Unlike Perl, there are no methods on RowHandle that produce the next
		RowHandle in the table, all the <pre>next*()</pre> methods are defined on the Table.
		It's possible to define them on Rhref, and will probably be done in the future.
		</para>

		<para>
		Next go the size operations:
		</para>

<pre>
size_t size() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the number of rows currently in the table.
		</para>

<pre>
size_t groupSizeIdx(IndexType *ixt, const RowHandle *what) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the size of the group where the handle belongs according to a
		non-leaf index. If any arguments are wrong, returns 0. The row handle
		doesn't have to be in the table. If it isn't in the table, the method
		will find the group where the row would belong if it were inserted and
		return its current size.
		</para>

<pre>
size_t groupSizeRowIdx(IndexType *ixt, const Row *what) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		A convenience version that makes a row handle from a row, finds the
		group size and disposes of the handle.
		</para>

		<para>
		Next go the finding methods:
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandle *find(const RowHandle *what) const;
RowHandle *findIdx(IndexType *ixt, const RowHandle *what) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Find the handle of a matching row according to the default (first leaf)
		or the specific index, or return NULL if not found.
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandle *findRow(const Row *what) const;
RowHandle *findRowIdx(IndexType *ixt, const Row *what) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		The convenience versions that create a temporary row handle and then
		perform the search.
		</para>

		<sect2 id="sc_cpp_table_dump">
		<title>Data dump</title>

		<para>
		The dump API of the table sends the whole contents of the table to
		the <quote>dump</quote> label, thus making any labels connected to it perform an
		implicit iteration over the table.
		</para>

<pre>
void clear(size_t limit = 0); 
</pre>

		<para>
		Deletes the rows from the table.
		If <pre>limit</pre> is 0, the whole table gets cleared. If it's greater
		than 0, no more than this number of rows will be deleted. 
		The deletion happens in the usual order of the first
		leaf index, and the rowops are sent to the table's output label as
		usual. It's really the same thing as running a loop over all the row
		handles and removing them.
		</para>

<pre>
void dumpAll(Rowop::Opcode op = Rowop::OP_INSERT) const;
void dumpAllIdx(IndexType *ixt, Rowop::Opcode op = Rowop::OP_INSERT) const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>opcode</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The dump can go in the order of default or specific index. The opcode
		argument is used for the rowops sent on the dump label. Using the
		argument index type of NULL makes <pre>dumpAllIdx()</pre> use the default index
		and work just like <pre>DumpAll()</pre>. In the future there probably will also be
		methods that dump only a group of records.
		</para>

		<para>
		As usual, the general logic of the methods matches the Perl API unless
		said otherwise. Please refer to the Perl API description for the
		details and examples.
		</para>

		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="sc_cpp_table_sticky">
		<title>Sticky errors</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>sticky error</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The table
		internals contain a few places where the errors can't just throw an
		Exception because it will mess up the logic big time, most specifically
		the comparator functions for the indexes. The Triceps built-in indexes
		can't encounter any errors in the comparators but the user-defined
		ones, such as the Perl Sorted Index, can. Previously there was no way
		to report these errors other than print the error message and then
		either continue pretending that nothing happened or abort the program.
		</para>

		<para>
		The sticky errors provide a way out of this sticky situation. When an
		index comparator encounters an error, it reports it as a sticky error
		in the table and then returns false. The table logic then unrolls like
		nothing happened for a while, but before returning from the
		user-initiated method it will find this sticky error and throw an
		Exception at a safe time. Obviously, the incorrect comparison means
		that the table enters some messed-up state, so all the further
		operations on the table will keep finding this sticky error and throw
		an Exception right away, before doing anything. The sticky error can't
		be unstuck. The only way out of it is to just discard the table and
		move on.
		</para>

<pre>
void setStickyError(Erref err);
</pre>

		<para>
		Set the sticky error from a location where an exception can not be
		thrown, such as from the comparators in the indexes. Only the first
		error sticks, all the others are ignored since (a) the table will be
		dead and throwing this error in exceptions from this point on anyway
		and (b) the comparator is likely to report the same error repeatedly
		and there is no point in seeing multiple copies.
		</para>

<pre>
Errors *getStickyError() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the table's sticky error. Normally there is no point in doing this
		manually, but just in case.
		</para>

<pre>
void checkStickyError() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		If the sticky error has been set, throws an Exception with it. 
		</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

