<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_rowhandle">
		<title>RowHandle and Rhref reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>RowHandle</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		RowHandle is a mostly opaque class. It's defined in <pre>table/RowHandle.h</pre>
		but you never need to include that file directly: when you include
		<pre>table/Table.h</pre>, that takes care of it. If you look at the class
		definition, there are two public sections. The first one is really public,
		the second one is really for the internal use, I just didn't want to mess
		too much with the lists of friend classes. The really-public part is
		quite small:
		</para>

<pre>
const Row *getRow() const;
bool isInTable() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		The meaning of these methods is the same as in Perl, get the row contained
		in the handle, and check whether this handle has been inserted into its table.
		</para>

		<para>
		The constructor of RowHandle is private. It's constructed with a factory method
		in the Table, but normally a better approach is to use the wrapper constructor
		of Rhref, as described below. For the record, that Table factory method is:
		</para>

<pre>
RowHandle *makeRowHandle(const Row *row) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		There is also a side API that allows the indexes and aggregators to place their sections into
		the RowHandles. It's not a part of the RowHandle class as such, which is quite
		dumb and only knows how to carry the bytes of the data. The smart part of the
		RowHandle construction is contained in the API between the Table and its indexes
		and aggregators, and is outlined in 
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_sortidx" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Rhref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The row handles have the requirements very similar to the rows. They
		get created by the million, so the efficiency is important. In addition, they
		may contain the user data that has to be properly destroyed, the index and aggregator
		state mentioned above. For example, when an
		additive Perl aggregator stores its last state, it's stored in a row
		handle.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Table</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		So the row handle references are handled similarly to the rows. They don't have a virtual
		destructor but rely on the Table that owns them to destroy them right.
		The special reference type for them is Rhref, defined in <pre>mem/Rhref.h</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		It follows in the exact same mold as Rowref, only uses the Table
		instead of a RowType:
		</para>

<pre>
Rhref(Table *t, RowHandle *r = NULL);
void assign(Table *t, RowHandle *r);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Rowref</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The rest of comparisons, assignments etc. work the same as with Rowref.
		</para>

		<para>
		The RowHandle pointer may be NULL, creating an Rhref to a yet unknown
		handle in a known table. The Table pointer may be NULL too (of course,
		only if the RowHandle is NULL), creating a completely NULL reference.
		As usual in the &Cpp; API, these rules are not checked in the functions, 
		so if you assign the incorrect NULLs, the program will crash.
		</para>

		<para>
		As with Rowrefs, if the Table is not NULL, a RowHandle can be assigned
		into the Rowref through the assignment operator, but if the Table was not
		set, or if assigning a row handle from another table, the <pre>assign()</pre>
		method must be used to set both.
		</para>

		<para>
		An important point is that an Rhref contains an Autoref to the Table,
		safely holding the table in place while the Rhref is alive, it's the same
		as the relation between the Rowref and RowType.
		</para>

		<para>
		To find out the table of a Rhref, use:
		</para>

<pre>
Table *t = rhr.getTable();
</pre>

		<para>
		Why is the value returned a simple pointer to the table and not an
		Autoref or Onceref? Basically, because it's the cheapest way and
		because the row handle is not likely to go anywhere. Nobody is likely
		to construct a RowHandle only to get the table from it and have it
		immediately destroyed. And even if someone does something of the sort
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<Table> t = Rhref(t_orig, rh).getTable();
</pre>

		<para>
		then the table itself is likely to not go anywhere, there is still
		likely to be another reference to the table that will still hold it in
		place. If there isn't then of course all bets are off, and it will end
		up with a dead reference to corrupted memory. Just exercise a little
		care, and everything will be fine. The same reasoning was used for the
		argument of the RowHandle constructor being also a table pointer, not
		an Autoref or Onceref.
		</para>

		<para>
		An Rhref constructor may also be conveniently used to construct a RowHandle for a
		Row or directly from the field data:
		</para>

<pre>
Rhref(Table *t, Row *row);
Rhref(Table *t, FdataVec &data);
</pre>

		<para>
		In fact, this is the recommended way to construct a RowHandle, immediately
		holding it in a reference, instead of doing all the intermediate calls
		manually.
		</para>

	</sect1>
