<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_unit">
		<title>Unit reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Unit</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The Unit is declared in <pre>sched/Unit.h</pre>. It represents an
		execution unit that controls the execution order of a sequential
		part of a model.
		An unit is an Mtarget but in reality
		it may be used in one thread only. The multithreading support in the
		references is needed to build the multithreaded applications but
		each Unit in the application belongs to one thread (possibly sharing 
		it with other Units).
		</para>

<pre>
Unit(const string &name);
</pre>

		<para>
		Constructs an execution unit. 
		</para>

<pre>
const string &getName() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the name.
		</para>

<pre>
void schedule(Onceref<Rowop> rop);
void scheduleTray(const_Onceref<Tray> tray);
void fork(Onceref<Rowop> rop);
void forkTray(const_Onceref<Tray> tray);
void call(Onceref<Rowop> rop);
void callTray(const_Onceref<Tray> tray);

void enqueue(int em, Onceref<Rowop> rop);
void enqueueTray(int em, const_Onceref<Tray> tray);
</pre>

		<para>
		Schedule, fork or call a rowop or tray, like in Perl. Unlike Perl, the
		methods with a tray argument have different names. And the enqueueing
		mode is always an integer constant. These constants are defined in the
		enum Gadget::EnqMode (the Gadget class is described in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_gadget" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;), and is
		one of <pre>Gadget::EM_SCHEDULE</pre>, <pre>Gadget::EM_FORK</pre>, <pre>Gadget::EM_CALL</pre> and
		<pre>Gadget::EM_IGNORE</pre>. 
		</para>

<pre>
void enqueueDelayedTray(const_Onceref<Tray> tray);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Gadget</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Rowop</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Table</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Enqueue (schedule, fork or call) the rowops from a tray built by
		Gadget's method <pre>sendDelayed()</pre>.  The Rowop has a semi-undocumented
		field to store the enqueuing mode for that particular Rowop, that
		gets populated by <pre>Gadget::sendDelayed()</pre>.
		The <pre>enqueueDelayedTray()</pre> uses the value from this field
		to determine the enqueueing method individually for each Rowop.
		The whole arraggement is largely obsolete: it used to be used for
		the aggregators in a Table, mixing the outputs from multiple
		aggregators with potentially different enqueueing methods in one
		tray. But now everything just uses <pre>EM_CALL</pre> and there
		is no need for this any more.
		</para>

<pre>
bool empty() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether all the Unit's frames are empty.
		</para>

<pre>
bool isFrameEmpty() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the current inner frame is empty.
		</para>

<pre>
bool isInOuterFrame() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the unit's current inner frame is the same as its outer
		frame, which means that the unit is not in the middle of a call.
		</para>

<pre>
void callNext();
void drainFrame();
</pre>

		<para>
		Execute the next rowop from the current (inner) frame, or all the
		rowops on the current frame. The semantics is the same as in the Perl
		code.
		</para>

<pre>
void setMark(Onceref<FrameMark> mark);
</pre>

		<para>
		Set a mark on the current frame, same as in Perl.
		</para>

<pre>
void loopAt(FrameMark *mark, Onceref<Rowop> rop);
void loopTrayAt(FrameMark *mark, const_Onceref<Tray> tray);
</pre>

		<para>
		Enqueue a rowop or a tray at the marked frame.
		</para>

<pre>
void callAsChained(const Label *label, Rowop *rop, const Label *chainedFrom);
</pre>

		<para>
		This method was introduced in Triceps version 2, and hasn't propagated to
		Perl yet. I'm not even sure that I want it visible in Perl, since it's
		kind of low-level. It executes a label call, assuming that it was
		chained from another label (before version 2 the functionality itself had
		obviously existed but was not visible in the API).
		</para>

		<para>
		The row types of all the arguments must be matching, or the method
		would likely crash. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The label will be called with rowop, just as if this label was chained
		from another label. Since the chaining might be multi-level, the
		<pre>chainedFrom</pre> label is not necessarily the one in the rowop,
		it can itself be chained from the label in the rowop, directly or
		indirectly.
		</para>

		<para>
		All the tracing for the chained calls is automatically invoked.
		Keeping the consistency of the
		tracing is up to you: if you use the <pre>chainedFrom</pre> argument label that
		hasn't actually been called through the chain, the trace will look surprising.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>streaming function</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>FnReturn</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>FnBinding</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		This method is used in Triceps in such places as calling a label in
		FnBinding through an FnReturn. You can use it directly as
		well, just be very careful. 
		</para>

<pre>
void clearLabels();
</pre>

		<para>
		Clear all the unit's labels, same semantics as when called from Perl.
		</para>

<pre>
void rememberLabel(Label *lab);
</pre>

		<para>
		The method that connects a label to the unit. Normally you don't need
		to call it manually, the label constructor calls it (and that's why
		it's not in the Perl API). The only real reason to use this method
		manually is if you've disconnected a label manually from the unit, and
		want to reconnect it back (and I'm not sure if anyone would ever want
		that). Calling this method repeatedly with the same label and unit will
		have no effect. Remembering the same label in multiple units is not a
		good idea.
		</para>

<pre>
void  forgetLabel(Label *lab);
</pre>

		<para>
		Make the unit forget a label, so on <pre>clearLabels()</pre> that label won't be
		cleared. This is another dangerous low-level method, since only the
		unit will forget about the label but the label will still keep the
		pointer to the unit, unless it's cleared. Because of the danger, it's
		also not in the Perl API. The reason to use it would be if you want to
		disassemble and discard a part of the unit without disturbing the rest
		of it. However a safer alternative is to just create multiple units in
		one thread and discard by a whole unit.
		</para>

<pre>
RowType *getEmptyRowType() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		A convenience method to get a reference to a row type with no fields.
		Such row type is useful for creation of pseudo-labels that have the
		user-defined clearing handlers that clear some user data.
		</para>

		<para>
		Each unit has its own instance of an empty row type. The separate instances
		(instead of having a single global one) are purely for the conveniece of memory management
		in the threads, they are all equivalent. You could also create
		your own empty row type.
		</para>

<pre>
void setMaxStackDepth(int v);
int maxStackDepth() const;
void setMaxRecursionDepth(int v);
int maxRecursionDepth() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Set and get the maximal unit stack depth and recursion depth, works the
		same as in Perl.
		</para>

<pre>
int getStackDepth() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Returns the current depth of the execution stack.
		It isn't of any use for the model logic as such but comes handy
		for debugging, to check in the loops that you haven't accidentally
		created a stack growing with iterations. When the unit is not
		running, the stack depth is 1, since the outermost frame always
		stays on the stack. When a rowop is being executed, the stack
		depth is at least 2.
		</para>

<pre>
void clearLabels();
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>UnitClearingTrigger</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Clear all the labels in the unit, then drop the references from unit to them.
		Normally should be called only when the unit is about to be destroyed,
		and is called automatically when the unit gets destroyed. However
		in case of cyclic references to the unit, may need to be called
		manually or through a UnitClearingTrigger object to break these
		cycles. For more information, see
		<xref linkend="sc_ref_cycles" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		The Unit has a few helper classes: the tracers and the clearing triggers.
		</para>

		<para>
		The tracer classes inherit from the nested virtual class Unit::Tracer.
		They will be described in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_unit_tracer" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		The Unit class contains the definition of the enums of the tracers
		and provides a way to set the tracer in the unit.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>tracing</primary>
		</indexterm>
<pre>
enum TracerWhen {
	// The values go starting from 0 in before-after pairs
	TW_BEFORE, // before calling the label's execution as such
	TW_AFTER, // after all the execution is done
	TW_BEFORE_CHAINED, // after execution, before calling the chained labels (if they are present)
	TW_AFTER_CHAINED, // after calling the chained labels (if they were present)
	TW_BEFORE_DRAIN, // before draining the label's frame if it's not empty
	TW_AFTER_DRAIN, // after draining the label's frame if was not empty
};
</pre>

		<para>
		This enum describes the point of the tracer invocation.
		The meaning of the values is described in detail in
		<xref linkend="sc_sched_tracing" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

<pre>
static const char *tracerWhenString(int when, const char *def = "???");
static int stringTracerWhen(const char *when);
</pre>

		<para>
		The usual conversions between the integer constants and their
		string representations.
		<pre>def</pre> is as usual the default placeholder that will be used
		for an invalid value. And the conversion from string would return a -1
		on an invalid value.
		</para>

<pre>
static const char *tracerWhenHumanString(int when, const char *def = "???");
static int humanStringTracerWhen(const char *when);
</pre>

		<para>
		The same kind of conversion as above, only the strings are more
		human-readable.  Basically, the same thing, only in the lowercase
		words. For example, TW_BEFORE_CHAINED would become "before-chained".
		This conversion is used by the provided tracer classes in their traces.
		</para>

<pre>
static bool tracerWhenIsBefore(int when);
static bool tracerWhenIsAfter(int when);
</pre>

		<para>
		Check a TracerWhen value for whether it represents a point before or after
		calling a label. Right now all the valid values fall into one or the
		other classification.
		But more trace points that are neither <quote>before</quote> or <quote>after</quote> could get added
		in the future, so a good practice is to check explicitly for both
		conditions rather than a simple if/else with one condition.
		</para>

<pre>
void setTracer(Onceref<Tracer> tracer);
Onceref<Tracer> getTracer() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Set and get back the tracer object for the Unit. <pre>NULL</pre> means
		that no tracer is set. It's possible to use the same tracer object
		for multiple units, as long as these units are in the same threads;
		that will combine the traces from these units into one trace.
		If you really want, it's even possible to use the same tracer object
		for the units in different threads but for that you must define
		your own tracer class that does the proper synchronization. None
		of the pre-defined tracers have the synchronization, since using
		them from multiple threads is usually not a good idea.
		</para>

		<para>
		The clearing trigger objects are constructed with:
		</para>
		
<pre>
UnitClearingTrigger(Unit *unit);
</pre>

		<para>
		The trigger is an Mtarget, so the typical use would be:
		</para>

<pre>
{
  Autoref<UnitClearingTrigger> ctrig = new UnitClearingTrigger(myunit);
  ...
}
</pre>

		<para>
		At the block exit when the Autoref will get destroyed, it will destroy the trigger,
		which would in turn cause the clearing of the unit. Of course, you can
		also place the Autoref into another object, and then the destruction of
		that object would cause the clearing, instead of the end of the block.
		</para>
	</sect1>
