<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_unit_tracer">
		<title>Unit Tracer reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Unit</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>tracing</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Unlike Perl, in &Cpp; the tracer is defined by inheriting from the class
		Unit::Tracer. The base class inherits from the Mtarget, and in the subclass
		you need at the minimum to define your virtual method:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual void execute(Unit *unit, const Label *label, const Label
	*fromLabel, Rowop *rop, TracerWhen when);
</pre>

		<para>
		It gets called at the exactly same points as the Perl tracer (the &Cpp;
		part of the UnitTracerPerl forwards the calls to the Perl level). The
		arguments are also the same as described in the Perl docs:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<pre>unit</pre> is the unit being traced.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<pre>label</pre> is the current label being traced.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<pre>fromLabel</pre> is the parent label in the chaining (would be
		<pre>NULL</pre> if the current label is called directly, without
		chaining from anything).
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<pre>rop</pre> is the current row operation.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<pre>when</pre> is a constant showing the point when the
		tracer is being called. It's value may be one of
		<pre>Unit::TW_BEFORE</pre>, 
		<pre>Unit::TW_AFTER</pre>, 
		<pre>Unit::TW_BEFORE_DRAIN</pre>,
		<pre>Unit::TW_AFTER_DRAIN</pre>,
		<pre>Unit::TW_BEFORE_CHAINED</pre>, 
		<pre>Unit::TW_AFTER_CHAINED</pre>; 
		the prefix <pre>TW</pre> stands for <quote>tracer when</quote>.
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		Here is a simple example of a tracer:
		</para>

<!-- cpp/sched/test/t_Unit.cpp -->
<pre>
class SampleTracer : public Unit::Tracer
{           
public: 
	virtual void execute(Unit *unit, const Label *label,
		const Label *fromLabel, Rowop *rop, Unit::TracerWhen when)
	{   
		printf("trace %s label '%s' %c\n", Unit::tracerWhenHumanString(when),
			label->getName().c_str(), Unit::tracerWhenIsBefore(when)? '{' : '}');
	}
};
</pre>

		<para>
		The Unit methods shown are documented in
		<xref linkend="sc_cpp_unit" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

		<para>
		The SampleTracer above was just printing the trace right away. Usually
		a better idea is to save the trace in the tracer object and return it
		on demand. Unit::Tracer provides the means to do that:
		an Erref object is used as a buffer, where the data can be added
		efficiently line-by-line, and later read back. The buffer is defined
		protected, so that the subclasses can access it but the end users can't:
		</para>
		
<pre>
protected:
	Erref buffer_; // buffer for collecting the trace
</pre>

		<para>
		On each call the tracer's <pre>execute()</pre> would build a string,
		and append it to the buffer:
		</para>

<pre>
buffer_->appendMsg(false, traceString);
</pre>


		<para>
		The public interface for the buffer is:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual Erref getBuffer();
virtual void clearBuffer();
</pre>

		<para>
		These methods are virtual to let the subclasses define their own
		version if they want. The methods do exactly what their names say.
		<pre>getBuffer()</pre> returns the reference
		to the buffer in <pre>buffer_</pre>, after which the end user has
		the full access to it.
		</para>

		<para>
		The pattern of reading the buffer contents works like this:
		</para>

<pre>
string tlog = trace->getBuffer()->print();
trace->clearBuffer();
</pre>

		<para>
		The log string can then be printed, or used in any other way.
		</para>

		<para>
		The clearing of the buffer is done by discarding the old one and
		allocating a new one. An interesting consequence is that if you
		call <pre>getBuffer()</pre>, save the reference, then call
		<pre>clearBuffer()</pre>, the original buffer is still available
		at your saved reference and won't be changed any more, for example:
		</para>
		
<pre>
Erref buf = trace->getBuffer();
trace->clearBuffer();
string tlog = buf->print();
</pre>

		<para>
		Of course, if a tracer subclass defines its own version of virtual methods,
		it may change this semantics.
		</para>

		<para>
		It can be quite useful to include the row being processed into the trace,
		as the Perl examples show in 
		<xref linkend="sc_sched_tracing" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		The &Cpp; part of Triceps doesn't provide a ready row printer yet
		but Unit::Tracer provides a way for you to use your own row printer.
		Even two ways. One is to re-define the public method <pre>printRow()</pre>:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual void printRow(string &res, const RowType *rt, const Row *row);
</pre>

		<para>
		The job of this method is to append the information from the row <pre>row</pre> of the type
		<pre>rt</pre> to the result string <pre>res</pre>. <i>Append</i>, not replace.
		</para>

		<para>
		The second way is by providing a pointer to a simple C-style function of the type:
		</para>

<pre>
typedef void RowPrinter(string &res, const RowType *rt, const Row *row);
</pre>

		<para>
		The arguments and functionality are exactly the same as for the 
		method <pre>printRow()</pre>. The base class implementation of
		<pre>printRow()</pre> works by calling this function pointer of it's
		not NULL.  This pointer can be given to the Tracer constructor:
		</para>

<pre>
Tracer(RowPrinter *rp = NULL);
</pre>

		<para>
		In general, the subclasses should also take this argument and pass it
		through to the parent class.  This allows the separation of the tracer
		itself and of the row printing: the user becomes capable of specifying
		any row printer.
		Since the default row printer is NULL, the row contents doesn't get printed
		by default.
		</para>

		<para>
		Triceps provides a couple of stock tracer classes:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>StringTracer</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
				Collects the trace in a buffer, identifying the objects
				as addresses. This is not exactly easy to read normally but may come
				useful if you want to analyze a core dump.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>StringNameTracer</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
				Similar but prints the object identification as
				names. More convenient but prone to the duplicate names used for
				different objects.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>
		Everything but the constructors of these classes follows the general
		Tracer interface.  The constructors are:
		</para>

<pre>
StringTracer(bool verbose = false, RowPrinter *rp = NULL);
StringNameTracer(bool verbose = false, RowPrinter *rp = NULL);
</pre>

		<para>
		The <pre>verbose</pre> flag enables the tracing at all points,
		if it's set to <pre>false</pre> then only the <pre>TW_BEFORE</pre>
		points are traced. The argument <pre>rp</pre> lets the end user supply
		a row printer function.
		</para>

		<para>
		The tracing does not have to be used just for tracing. It can also be
		used as a breakpoint: check in your tracer for an
		arbitrary condition and stop if it has been met.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is only one tracer per unit at a time. However if you want, you
		can implement the chaining in your own tracer (particularly useful if
		it's a breakpoint tracer): accept a reference to another tracer
		object, and after doing your own part, call that object's <pre>execute()</pre>
		method.
		</para>

		<para>
		Even though the Tracer class inherits from Mtarget, none of its methods
		have the synchronization in them. Thus each object must be used in only
		one thread. If you really want to use your tracer object from multiple
		threads, define your own subclass and re-implement all the virtual methods
		in it with synchronization.
		</para>
	</sect1>
