<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_label">
		<title>Label reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>label</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		In &Cpp; the custom labels are defined by defining your own class that
		inherits from Label (which is defined in <pre>sched/Label.h</pre>). 
		Like this small example from a unit test:
		</para>

<!-- sched/test/t_Unit.cpp -->
<pre>
class ForkingLabel : public Label
{
public:
	ForkingLabel(Unit *unit, Onceref<RowType> rtype, const string &name,
			Onceref<Label> next) :
		Label(unit, rtype, name),
		next_(next)
	{ }

	virtual void execute(Rowop *arg) const
	{
		unit_->fork(next_->adopt(arg));
	}

	Autoref<Label> next_;
};
</pre>

		<para>
		The subclass needs to define its own execution method:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual void execute(Rowop *arg) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		The base class takes care of all the general execution mechanics,
		chaining etc. All you need to do in this method is perform your
		user-defined actions. By the way, this method is protected and should
		never be called directly. The labels must always be called through a
		unit, which will then execute them in the correct way.
		</para>

		<para>
		The subclass may (though doesn't have to) also define the custom clearing method:
		</para>

<pre>
virtual void clearSubclass();
</pre>

		<para>
		Currently this method is called by the public method <pre>clear()</pre>
		after the label is marked as cleared but before clearing of the chain
		(though this order may change in the future).
		</para>

		<para>
		The base class constructor is also protected, 
		it's always constructed from a subclass.
		You can not instantiate the base Label class because it contains an
		abstract <pre>execute()</pre> method. 
		</para>


<pre>
Label(Unit *unit, const_Onceref<RowType> rtype, const string &name);
</pre>

		<para>
		The arguments are similar to the Perl version, only the Unit is passed
		as an argument to the Label constructor. 
		</para>

		<para>
		The constructed label keeps a reference to its row type, and a pointer
		(not reference, to avoid the circular references!) to the unit. The unit
		automatically keeps a reference to the label, so there is no need to call
		<pre>Unit::rememberLabel()</pre> manually. On the other hand, if you do not want
		the label to be remembered by its unit (though why?), the only way to achieve
		that is to call <pre>Unit::forgetLabel()</pre> after its construction.
		</para>

		<para>
		Now, the public methods of Label.
		</para>

<pre>
const string &getName() const;
const RowType *getType() const;
Unit *getUnitPtr() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Read back the information from the constructor.
		The method <pre>getUnitPtr()</pre> is named this way and not <pre>getUnit()</pre> to
		emphasize that the Label has only a pointer to the Unit, not a
		reference. After the label gets cleared, <pre>getUnitPtr()</pre> will return
		NULL.The reason is that after that the label doesn't know any more
		whether the unit still exists or has been deleted, and doesn't want to
		return a pointer to a potentially freed memory.
		</para>

<pre>
const string &getUnitName() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		A convenience method for the special case of getting the label's unit
		name. It's used in many error message. You can't just say
		<pre>label->getUnitPtr()->getName()</pre> because <pre>getUnitPtr()</pre> might return a
		NULL if the label has been already cleared. <pre>getUnitName()</pre> takes care of it and returns a special string
		"[label cleared]" if the label has been cleared.
		</para>

<pre>
void clear();
</pre>

		<para>
		Clears the label. After that the label stops working. Note that
		clearing a label doesn't disconnect it from its unit. Well, the label
		won't tell you its unit any more (the pointer will be reset to NULL) but the unit will still have a
		reference to the label! Use the unit's method <pre>forgetLabel()</pre> to
		disconnect it (but that won't clear the label itself, so you have to
		call both <pre>unit->forgetLabel()</pre> and <pre>label->clear()</pre>). Of course, if you
		call <pre>unit->clearLabels()</pre>, that would take care of everything.
		</para>

		<para>
		Clearing cleans the chaining list of this label but doesn't call
		recursively <pre>clear()</pre> on the formerly chained labels. If you need that,
		you have to do it yourself.
		</para>

<pre>
bool isCleared() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Check if the label has been cleared.
		</para>

<pre>
void setNonReentrant();
bool isNonReentrant() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Mark the label as non-reentrant, and check this flag. There is no way
		to unset this flag. The meaning of it is described in
		<xref linkend="sc_sched_recursion" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		</para>

<pre>
Erref chain(Onceref<Label> lab, bool front = false);
</pre>

		<para>
		Chain another label to this one (so when this label is executed, the
		chained labels will also be executed in order). This label will keep a
		reference of the chained label. The circular chainings are forbidden
		and will throw an Exception.
		If the argument <pre>front</pre> is <pre>false</pre> (default), the chaining 
		will be done at the back of the chain, if <pre>true</pre> then at the front,
		same as the method <pre>chainFront()</pre> in the Perl API.
		In the &Cpp; API both kinds of chainings are done with the same method.
		</para>

<pre>
typedef vector<Autoref<Label> > ChainedVec;
const ChainedVec &getChain() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the information about the chained labels. This returns a
		reference to the internal vector, so if the chainings are changed
		afterwards, the changes will be visible in the vector.
		</para>

<pre>
bool hasChained() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		A quick check, whether there is anything chained.
		</para>

<pre>
void clearChained();
</pre>

		<para>
		Clear the chaining list of this label. (But doesn't call <pre>clear()</pre> on
		these labels!)
		</para>

<pre>
Rowop *adopt(Rowop *from) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		A convenient factory method for adopting the rowops. Treat it similarly to a
		constructor: the returned Rowop will be newly constructed and have the
		reference count of 0; the returned pointer must be stored in an Autoref (or
		Onceref). This method by itself doesn't check whether the original
		Rowop has a matching type, it simply makes a copy with the label
		reference replaced. It's up to you to make sure that the labels are
		correct.
		</para>

		<para>
		A special subclass of the Label is DummyLabel: it's a label that does
		nothing. It's <pre>execute()</pre> method is empty. It's constructed very
		similarly to the normal Label:
		</para>

<pre>
DummyLabel(Unit *unit, const_Onceref<RowType> rtype, const string &name);
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>DummyLabel</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		The dummy labels are convenient for chaining the other labels to them. 
		</para>
	</sect1>

