<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_tray">
		<title>Tray reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>tray</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A Tray in &Cpp;, defined in <pre>shed/Tray.h</pre>, is simply a deque of Rowop
		references, plus an Starget, so that it can be reference-counted like the
		rest of Triceps classes:
		</para>

<pre>
class Tray : public Starget, public deque< Autoref<Rowop> >
</pre>

		<para>
		All it really defines is the constructors:
		</para>

<pre>
Tray();
Tray(const Tray &orig);
</pre>

		<para>
		The operations on the Tray are just the usual deque operations.
		</para>

		<para>
		Yes, you can copy the trays by constructing a new one from an old one:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<Tray> t1 = new Tray;
t1->push_back(op1);

Autoref<Tray> t3 = new Tray(*t1);
</pre>

		<para>
		Afterwards <pre>t3</pre> will contain references to the same rowops as <pre>t1</pre> (but
		will be a different Tray than <pre>t1</pre>!).
		</para>

		<para>
		The assignments (<pre>operator=</pre>) happen to just work out of the box because
		the <pre>operator=</pre> implementation in Starget does the smart thing and avoids
		the corruption of the reference counter. So you can do things like
		</para>

<pre>
*t3 = *t1;
</pre>

		<para>
		It's worth noting once more that unlike Rows and Rowops, the Trays
		are mutable. If you have multiple references to the same Tray,
		modifying the Tray will make the new contents visible through all
		the references!
		</para>

		<para>
		An important difference from the Perl API is that in &Cpp; the Tray is
		not associated with a Unit. It's constructed simply by calling its
		constructor, and there is no Unit involved. It's possible to create a
		tray that contains a mix of rowops for different units. If you combine
		the &Cpp; and Perl code, and then create such mixes in the &Cpp; part, the
		Perl part of your code won't be happy.
		</para>

		<para>
		And there is actually a way to create the mixed-unit trays even in the
		Perl code, in the tray of FnBinding. But this situation would be caught
		when trying to get the tray from FnBinding into the Perl level, and the workaround 
		for handling them is to use the method <pre>FnBinding:callTray()</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		The reason why Perl associates the trays with a unit is to make the
		check of enqueueing a tray easy: just check that the tray belongs to
		the right unit, and it's all guaranteed to be right. At the &Cpp; level
		no such checks are made. If you enqueue the rowops on labels belonging
		to a wrong unit, they will be enqueued quietly, will attempt to
		execute, and from there everything will likely go very wrong. So be
		disciplined. And maybe I'll think of a better way for keeping the unit
		consistency in the future. 
		</para>

	</sect1>
