<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_fnreturn">
		<title>FnReturn reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>FnReturn</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		FnReturn, defined in <pre>sched/FnReturn.h</pre>, is generally constructed
		similarly to the RowSetType:
		</para>

<pre>
ret = initializeOrThrow(FnReturn::make(unit, name)
	->addLabel("lb1", rt1)
	->addFromLabel("lb2", lbX)
);
</pre>

		<para>
		Or of course piece-meal. As it gets built, it actually builds a
		RowSetType inside itself.
		</para>

<pre>
FnReturn(Unit *unit, const string &name);
static FnReturn *make(Unit *unit, const string &name);
</pre>

		<para>
		The constructor and convenience wrapper. The unit will be remembered
		only as a pointer, not reference, to avoid the reference loops. However
		this pointer will be used to construct the internal labels. So until
		the FnReturn is fully initialized, you better make sure that the Unit
		object has a reference and doesn't get freed. FnReturn is an Starget,
		and must be used in only one thread.
		</para>

<pre>
const string &getName() const;
Unit *getUnitPtr() const;
const string &getUnitName() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the information from the constructor. Just like for the Label class,
		it reminds you that the Unit is only available as a pointer, not a
		reference, here.  The FnReturn also has a concept of clearing: it has
		the special labels inside, and once any of these labels gets cleared,
		the FnReturn is also cleared by setting the unit pointer to NULL and
		forgetting the FnContext (see more on that below).  So after the
		FnReturn is cleared, <pre>getUnitPtr()</pre> will return NULL. And again similarly
		to the Label, there is a convenience function to get the unit name for
		informational printouts. When FnReturn is cleared, it returns the constant string
		<quote>[fn return cleared]</quote>.
		</para>

<pre>
FnReturn *addFromLabel(const string &lname, Autoref<Label>from, bool front = true);
</pre>

		<para>
		Add a label to the return by chaining it off another label. <pre>lname</pre> is
		the name within the return. The full name of the label will be
		<quote>return_name.label_name</quote>. The label names within a return must be unique
		and not empty, or it will be returned as an initialization error. The
		label type will be copied (actually, referenced) from the <pre>from</pre> label,
		and the new label will be automatically chained off it. If the argument
		<pre>front</pre> is <pre>false</pre>, the chaining will be done at the
		back of the chain, if <pre>true</pre> (default) then at the front.
		The front chaining is convenient if you want to pass both
		the original request and the result into the return. Usually you
		would define the result computation and then define the return.
		With the chaining at the back, this would lead to the computation
		chained off the input label first and the return going after it.
		This would lead to the result coming out before the argument,
		and special contortions would be needed to avoid it. With chaining
		at the front, the return will go in the chain before the computation,
		even if the return was defined last.
		The labels can
		be added only until the return is initialized, or it will throw an
		Exception.
		</para>

<pre>
FnReturn *addLabel(const string &lname, const_Autoref<RowType>rtype);
</pre>

		<para>
		Add a new independent label to the return. Works very similarly to
		<pre>addFromLabel()</pre>, only uses the explicit row type and doesn't chain to
		anything. The label can be later found with <pre>getLabel()</pre> and either
		chained off something or used to send the rows to it explicitly. The
		labels can be added only until the return is initialized.
		</para>

<pre>
class FnContext: public Starget
{
public:
	virtual ~FnContext();
	virtual void onPush(const FnReturn *fret) = 0;
	virtual void onPop(const FnReturn *fret) = 0;
};
FnReturn *setContext(Onceref<FnContext> ctx);
</pre>

		<para>
		Set the context with handlers for the pushing and popping of the
		bindings in the FnReturn. FnContext is a top-level class, not nested
		in FnReturn.  
		I.e. <b>not</b> Triceps::FnReturn::FnContext but Triceps::FnContext. 
		Triceps generally tries to follow the &Cpp;
		tradition of using the virtual methods for the callbacks, with the user
		then subclassing the base class and replacing the callback methods.
		However subclassing FnReturn is extremely inconvenient, because it gets
		connected to the other objects in a quite complicated way. So the
		solution is to make a separate context class for the callbacks, and
		then connect it.  
		The callbacks will be called just before the
		binding is pushed or popped, but after the check for the correctness of
		the push or pop. They can be used to adjust the state of the streaming
		function by pushing or popping its stack of local variables, like was
		shown in the Perl examples in
		<xref linkend="sc_strf_more_recursion" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle pageabbrev"/>&xrsp;.
		The context may be set only until the return is initialized.
		</para>

<pre>
template<class C> C *contextIn() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get back the context. Since the context will be a subclass of
		FnContext, this also handles the correct type casting. Use it like:
		</para>

<pre>
Autoref<MyFnCtx> ctx = fret1->contextIn<MyFnCtx>();
</pre>

		<para>
		The type is converted using the <pre>static_cast</pre>, and you need to know the
		correct type in advance, or your program will break in some horrible
		ways. If the context has not been set, it will return a NULL.
		</para>

<pre>
void initialize();
</pre>

		<para>
		Initialize the FnReturn. Very similar to the Type classes, it will
		collect the errors in an Errors object that has to be checked
		afterwards, and an FnReturn with errors must not be used. The
		initialization can be called repeatedly with no ill effects. After
		initialization the structure of the return (labels and context) can not
		be changed any more.
		</para>

<pre>
Erref getErrors() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the errors that were detected during construction and initialization. 
		Normally called after initialization but can
		also be called at any stage, as the errors are collected all the way
		through the object construction.
		</para>

<pre>
bool isInitialized() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Check whether the return is initialized.
		</para>

<pre>
RowSetType *getType() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the type of the return, which gets built internally by the return.
		The names of the row types in the set will be the same as the names of
		labels in the return, and their order will also be the same. This call
		can be made only after initialization, or it will throw an Exception.
		</para>

<pre>
int size() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the number of labels in the return. Can be called at any time.
		</para>

<pre>
const RowSetType::NameVec &getLabelNames() const;
const RowSetType::RowTypeVec &getRowTypes() const;
const string *getLabelName(int idx) const;
RowType *getRowType(const string &name) const;
RowType *getRowType(int idx) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the piecemeal information about the label names and types. These
		are really the convenience wrappers around the RowSetType. Note that
		they return pointers to be able to return NULL on the argument that is
		out of range. A somewhat special feature is that even though the row
		set type can be read only after initialization (after it becomes frozen
		and can not be messed with any more), these wrappers work at any time,
		even when the return is being built.
		</para>

<pre>
bool equals(const FnReturn *t) const;
bool match(const FnReturn *t) const;
bool equals(const FnBinding *t) const;
bool match(const FnBinding *t) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Convenience wrappers that compare the equality or match of the
		underlying row set types.
		</para>

<pre>
Label *getLabel(const string &name) const;
int findLabel(const string &name) const;
Label *getLabel(int idx) const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the label by name or index, or the index of the label by name.
		Return a NULL pointer or -1 index on an invalid argument.
		</para>

<pre>
typedef vector<Autoref<RetLabel> > ReturnVec;
const ReturnVec &getLabels() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the whole set of labels. FnReturn::RetLabel is a special private
		label type with undisclosed internals. You need to treat these labels
		as being a plain Label.
		</para>

<pre>
void push(Onceref<FnBinding> bind);
</pre>

		<para>
		Push a binding on the return stack. The return must be initialized, and
		the binding must be of a matching type, or an Exception will be thrown.
		The reference to the binding will be kept in the FnReturn until it's popped.
		</para>

<pre>
void pushUnchecked(Onceref<FnBinding> bind);
</pre>

		<para>
		Similar to <pre>push()</pre>, only the type of the binding is not checked. 
		This method is not available in Perl, it's
		an optimization for the automatically generated code that does all the
		type checks up front at the generation time. The manually written code
		probably should not be using it.
		</para>

<pre>
void pop(Onceref<FnBinding> bind);
</pre>

		<para>
		Pop a binding from the return stack. The binding argument specifies,
		which binding is expected to be popped. It's not strictly necessary 
		(use the <pre>pop()</pre> without arguments to skip it) but
		allows to catch any mess-ups with the return stack early. If the stack
		is empty or the top binding is not the same as the argument, throws an
		Exception.
		</para>

<pre>
void pop();
</pre>

		<para>
		The unchecked version. It still checks and throws if the stack is
		empty. This method may come handy occasionally, but in general the
		checked version should be preferred. Pretty much the only reason to use
		it would be if you try to restore after a major error and want to pop
		everything from all your FnReturns untill their stacks become empty.
		But there is much trouble with this kind of restoration.
		</para>

<pre>
int bindingStackSize() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the current size of the return stack (AKA the stack of bindings). Useful
		for debugging.
		</para>

<pre>
typedef vector<Autoref<FnBinding> > BindingVec;
const BindingVec &bindingStack() const;
</pre>

		<para>
		Get the current return stack. Useful for debugging. 
		</para>

<pre>
bool isFaceted() const;
</pre>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>Facet</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		Returns <pre>true</pre> if this FnReturn object is a part of a Facet.
		</para>
	</sect1>
