<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5CR3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % userents SYSTEM "file:///ENTS/user.ent" >
%userents;
]>

<!--
(C) Copyright 2011-2014 Sergey A. Babkin.
This file is a part of Triceps.
See the file COPYRIGHT for the copyright notice and license information
-->

	<sect1 id="sc_cpp_autofn">
		<title>ScopeFnBind and AutoFnBind reference</title>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>ScopeFnBind</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		A couple more of helper classes are defined in <pre>sched/FnReturn.h</pre>.
		</para>

		<para>
		ScopeFnBind does a scoped pushing and popping of a binding on an
		FnReturn. Its only method is the constructor:
		</para>

<pre>
ScopeFnBind(Onceref<FnReturn> ret, Onceref<FnBinding> binding);
</pre>

		<para>
		It's used as:
		</para>

<pre>
{
    ScopeFnBind autobind(ret, binding);
    ...
}
</pre>

		<para>
		It will pop the binding at the end of the block. An unpleasant feature
		is that if the return stack get messed up, it will throw an Exception
		from a destructor, which is a big no-no in &Cpp;. However since normally
		in the &Cpp; code the Triceps Exception is essentially an abort, this
		works good enough. If you make the Exception catchable, such as when
		calling the &Cpp; code from an interpreter, you better make very sure
		that the stack can not get corrupted, or do not use ScopeFnBind.
		</para>

		<indexterm>
			<primary>AutoFnBind</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
		AutoFnBind is a further extension of the scoped binding. It does three
		additional things: 
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			It allows to push multiple bindings on multiple
			returns as a group, popping them all on destruction. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			It's a
			reference-counted Starget object, which allows the scope to be more
			than one block. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			It also has a more controllable way of dealing with the
			exceptions. 
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		This last two properties allow it to be used from the Perl
		code, making the scope of a Perl block, not &Cpp; block, and to pass the
		exceptions properly back to Perl.
		</para>

<pre>
AutoFnBind();
AutoFnBind *make();
</pre>

		<para>
		The constructor just creates an empty object which then gets filled
		with bindings.
		</para>

<pre>
AutoFnBind *add(Onceref<FnReturn> ret, Autoref<FnBinding> binding);
</pre>

		<para>
		Add a binding, in a chainable fashion. The simple-minded way of using the
		AutoFnBind is:
		</para>

<pre>
{
    Autoref<AutoFnBind> bind = AutoFnBind::make()
        ->add(ret1, binding1)
        ->add(ret2, binding2);
    ...
}
</pre>

		<para>
		However if any of these <pre>add()</pre>s throw an Exception, this will leave an
		orphaned AutoFnBind object, since the throwing would happen before it
		had a chance to do the reference-counting. So the safer way to use it
		is:
		</para>

<pre>
{
    Autoref<AutoFnBind> bind = new AutoFnBind;
    bind
        ->add(ret1, binding1)
        ->add(ret2, binding2);
    ...
}
</pre>

		<para>
		Then the AutoFnBind will be reference-counted first, and if an <pre>add()</pre>
		throws later, this will cause a controlled destruction of the Autoref
		and of AutoFnBind.
		</para>

		<para>
		But it's not the end of the story yet. The throws on destruction are
		still a possibility. To catch them, use an explicit clearing before
		the end of the block:
		</para>

<pre>
void clear();
</pre>

		<para>
		Pops all the bindings. If any Exceptions get thrown, they can get
		caught nicely. It tries to be real smart, going through all the
		bindings in the backwards order and popping each one of them. If a
		<pre>pop()</pre> throws an exception, its information will be collected but
		<pre>clear()</pre> will then continue going through the whole list. At the end of
		the run it will make sure that it doesn't have any references to
		anything any more, and then will re-throw any collected errors as a
		single Exception. This cleans up the things as much as possible and as
		much as can be handled, but the end result will still not be
		particularly clean: the returns that got their stacks corrupted will
		still have their stacks corrupted, and some very serious
		application-level cleaning will be needed to continue. Probably a
		better choice would be to destroy everything and restart from scratch.
		But at least it allows to get safely to this point of restarting from
		scratch.
		</para>

		<para>
		So, the full correct sequence will be:
		</para>

<pre>
{
	Autoref<AutoFnBind> bind = new AutoFnBind;
	bind
		->add(ret1, binding1)
		->add(ret2, binding2);
	...
	bind->clear();
}
</pre>

		<para>
		Or if any code in <quote>...</quote> can throw anything, then something like this snippet(whis 
		is not actually tested, so use with caution):
		</para>

<pre>
{
	Autoref<AutoFnBind> bind = new AutoFnBind;
	bind
		->add(ret1, binding1)
		->add(ret2, binding2);
	try {
	...
	} catch (Triceps::Exception e) {
		try {
			bind->clear();
		} catch (Triceps::Exception ee) {
			e->getErrors()->append("Unbinding errors triggered by the last error:", ee->getErrors());
		}
		throw;
	} catch (exception e) {
		bind->clear(); // might use a try/catch around it as well
		throw;
	}
}
</pre>

		<para>
		It tries to be nice if the exception thrown from <quote>...</quote> was a Triceps
		one, and add nicely any errors from the binding clearing to it.
		</para>

		<para>
		Finally, a little about how the Perl AutoFnBind translates to the &Cpp;
		AutoFnBind:
		</para>

		<para>
		The Perl constructor creates the &Cpp;-level object and adds the bindings
		to it. If any of them throw, it destroys everything nicely and
		translates the Exception to Perl. Otherwise it saves a reference to the
		AutoFnBind in a wrapper object that gets returned to Perl.
		</para>

		<para>
		The Perl destructor then first clears the AutoFnBind and catches if
		there is any Exception. However there is just no way to return a Perl
		exception from a Perl destructor, so it simply prints the error on stderr
		and calls <pre>exit(1)</pre>. If no exception was thrown, the AutoFnBind gets
		destroyed nicely by removing the last reference.
		</para>

		<para>
		For the nicer handling, there is a Perl-level method <pre>clear()</pre> that does
		the clearing and translates the exception to Perl.
		</para>
	</sect1>
