<chapter><?dbhtml filename="features.html"?>
<chapterinfo>
<releaseinfo role="meta">
$Id: features.xml,v 1.21 2003/11/25 10:20:24 borisz Exp $
</releaseinfo>
</chapterinfo>
<title>Overview of Features</title>
 <sect1><?dbhtml filename="mvcc.html"?>
  <title>Model/View/Content/Controller approach to design</title>
  <para>
   PageKit follows a Model/View/Content/Controller design pattern, which
   is an adaption of the Model/View/Controller pattern used in many other
   web frameworks, including Java's Webmacro and Struts.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The Model is the user provided classes, which encapsulate the
     business logic behind the web site
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     View is set of PageKit Templates, or XSLT files that generate
     PageKit Templates
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Content is set of XML Files
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Controller is PageKit
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
This approach parallels the division of the job responsibilities of a large web development team.
The programmers can focus on the Model, the designers on the View, and the content
administrators on the (you guessed it!) Content. PageKit provides the Controller which glues
everything together. 
  </para>
  <para>
This way everybody can focus on what they do best, whether it is programming, design, or
content. Since the interfaces are simple and well-defined they can easily work together without
interfering with each other. 
  </para>
  <sect2>
   <title>Model</title>
   <para>
    The Model is provided by Perl classes which implement the business logic that is custom to the
    site.  These class files should be located in the <filename>Model/</filename> directory.  Each URL is translated into a class and method automatically. 
   </para>
   <para>
It includes support for <ulink url="http://search.cpan.org/doc/MARKSTOS/Data-FormValidator-1.6/lib/Data/FormValidator.pm">Data::FormValidator</ulink>, making the tedious task of input validation easier.
To validate a form, you simply specify required fields and constraints. If there is an error, you
can return to the input form, and the invalid fields automatically get highlighted in red.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>View</title>
   <para>
    The View is defined by a set of PageKit Templates making up pages and their
    components located in the <filename>View/</filename> directory. These
    templates can be in HTML, WML, XML, or any text based format.
   </para>
   <para>
    Alternatively, you can provide a set of XSLT files that will generate PageKit Templates.
   </para>
   <para>
    PageKit Template is based on <ulink url="http://kobesearch.cpan.org/search?dist=HTML-Template">HTML::Template</ulink>.
There are different sets of tags, depending on
where the data is being pulled from.
   </para>
   <para>
The <link linkend="model.tags">Model Tags</link>,
&lt;MODEL_VAR&gt;, &lt;MODEL_LOOP&gt;, and &lt;MODEL_IF&gt;,
are filled with data by the Model.
   </para>
   <para>
The <link linkend="content.tags">Content Tags</link>,
&lt;CONTENT_VAR&gt; and &lt;CONTENT_LOOP&gt;, contain
XPath queries to the Content XML data.
   </para>
   <para>
The <link linkend="pagekit.tags">PageKit Tags</link> are set internally by the Controller.
   </para>
   <para>
It is easy to implement <link linkend="features.multiple.views">multiple views</link>, such as a printable version of a web page or a
co-branded site. To create a new view, simply create a directory containing template files for
the view. You only have to create templates for pages and components that you wish to
override. That is all views inherit from the default set of templates.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Content</title>
   <para>
Content is stored in an XML files.  It is accessed either through XPath queries from
PageKit Template using <ulink url="http://kobesearch.cpan.org/search?dist=HTML-Template-XPath">HTML::Template::XPath</ulink> or by applying XSLT stylesheets to transform the XML into a
PageKit Template.
   </para>
   <para>
     Language localization couldn't be easier. Simply use the
     <literal>xml:lang</literal> attribute in the tags you wish
     to localize. For example, to have a title available in both English and Spanish use:
   </para>
   <informalexample>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
  <title xml:lang="en">Title in English</title>
  <title xml:lang="es">Titulo en Español</title>]]>
    </programlisting>
   </informalexample>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Controller</title>
   <para>
     The Controller is the glue that holds everything together. To deliver a page it calls the
     appropriate code in the Model, generates the PageKit Template from the Content if
     necessary, then fills in the tags in the PageKit Template.
   </para>
   <para>
It makes the tedious task of authentication/authorization easy, with support for cookie based
logins and session inactivity timeouts. After a login or registration, the user is redirected to the
protected page they originally requested, if applicable.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1><?dbhtml filename="model.html"?>
 <title>Model of OO Perl Classes</title>
  <para>
   Model is simply a set of OO Perl Classes whose methods get
   exposed to the client through URIs.
  </para>
   <sect2 id="model.base">
    <title>Base Model Class</title>
    <para>
You should implement one base Model class which derives from
<literal>Apache::PageKit::Model</literal>.  You must specify the
class in the <link linkend="config.global.model_base_class">model_base_class</link> option.
    </para>
    <para>
     In this class, you should implement the <link linkend="model.api.extensions">PageKit Extensions</link>, and any methods that are common
across your Derived Model Classes.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="model.dispatch">
    <title>Derived Model Class</title>
    <para>
     The Derived Model Classes derive from your Base Model Class, and
     should contain methods for the dynamic pages on your site.
     You must specify the prefix of these classes in the <link linkend="config.global.model_dispatch_prefix">model_dispatch_prefix</link> option of <filename>Config/Config.xml</filename>.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
    <title>Inheritance Hierarchy</title>
    <para>This figure illustrations how model classes derive from each other
     and the level of specialization of each class.</para>
    <informalexample>
     <programlisting>
              +---------------------------------------+
              |         Apache::PageKit::Model        |                Common
              | Model code that provides an interface |       &lt;------- across
              | to PageKit and is common to all sites |                all sites
              +---------------------------------------+
                                   |
              +---------------------------------------+
              |           MyPageKit::Common           |                Specialized
              | Model code that is particular to the  |       &lt;------- For Site, common
              | site, but common across all pages     |                across site
              +---------------------------------------+
                      /           |           \
  +----------------------------+     +----------------------------+
  | MyPageKit::YourClass1      |     | MyPageKit::YourClassN      |    Specialized
  | Model code that is for a   | ... | Model code that is for a   | &lt;- for set of
  | group of pages on the site |     | group of pages on the site |    Pages on site
  +----------------------------+     +----------------------------+
     </programlisting>
    </informalexample>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1><?dbhtml filename="xslt_xpathtemplate.html"?>
  <title>XSLT and HTML::Template::XPath</title>
  <para>
   PageKit Templates use HTML::Template::XPath to include Content from the XML
   files.  In addition,
   PageKit Templates themselves can be generated from the XML using XSLT
   stylesheets.  Currently the only supported XSLT processer is
   <ulink url="http://kobesearch.cpan.org/search?dist=XML-LibXSLT">XML::LibXSLT</ulink> which uses Gnome libxslt library.
  </para>
  <para>
   You should use HTML::Template::XPath when you would like to separate
   some Content from the View, but do not want to go the full route
   of using XSLT.
  </para>
  <para>
   On the other hand, if you are starting from scratch, have existing XML
   and XSLT files, or have complicated transformation needs, then XSLT
   is probably the way to go.
  </para>
  <sect2>
   <title>XSLT</title>
   <para>
    To use XSLT, you must place the Content XML files in the <filename>Content/</filename> directory,
    and the View XSLT files in the <filename>View/</filename> directory.
    You must specify the XSLT template that you would like to use using the
    <literal>xml-stylesheet</literal> processing instruction by placing
    the following on the top of your XML file:
   </para>
   <informalexample>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
     <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="my_xslt_file.xsl"?>]]>
    </programlisting>
   </informalexample>
   <para>
    Note that the XSLT file specified in the href attribute is relative to
    the <filename>View/<replaceable>pkit_view</replaceable>/</filename> or the <filename>View/Default/</filename> directory.
   </para>
   <para>
    All of the input request parameters are available to the XSLT file by
    using the <literal>xsl:param</literal> tag in the top level of the file.
   </para>
   <para>
    The output of XSL Transformation should be a PageKit Template or a
    HTML/XML/WML file (which is a special case of a PageKit Template file, namely one without any PageKit tags).  Note that the Data from the Model gets
    filled in after the XSL transformation.  This is done for performance
    reasons - the XSL tranformation can be cached, even if the data from
    the model is updated.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>HTML::Template::XPath</title>
   <para>
    Using HTML::Template::XPath is easy with PageKit, it is build into the
    PageKit Template by using
    &lt;CONTENT_VAR&gt; and &lt;CONTENT_LOOP&gt; tags, which contain
    XPath queries to the Content XML data.
   </para>
   <para>
    The Content XML file defaults to <filename>Content/<replaceable>page_id</replaceable>.xml</filename> or can be specified using XPath's <emphasis role="bold">document()</emphasis> function.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Language Localization</title>
   <para>
   One of the main advantages of separating out the Content
   from the View is that it
   is easy to implement multiple languages while sharing the same
   look-and-feel.  You may use the <literal>xml:lang</literal>
   to label which languages tags are in.
   </para>
   <para>
   The preferred language of the user is determined as follows.
   </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The default language preference is set to the
     <literal>Accept-Language</literal> incoming HTTP header.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     This default value can be overridden by setting the
     <literal><link linkend="request.pkit_lang">pkit_lang</link></literal>
     request parameter.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <sect2>
   <title>Applying to Content: HTML::Template::XPath</title>
   <para>
    HTML::Template::XPath supports language localization through the use of the
    <literal>xml:lang</literal> attribute.  In PageKit 1.01 and above, the
    algorithm for
    selecting the node(s) for the selected languages is as follows:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      First it attempts to use the XPath function <literal>lang</literal>
      to return the node or the set of nodes whose <literal>xml:lang</literal>
      attribute(s) are the same as the preferred language.  If the node
      has no <literal>xml:lang</literal>, then the value of the
      <literal>xml:lang</literal> attribute on the nearest ancestor is used.
      If the node and the its ancestors have no <literal>xml:lang</literal>
      attribute, then the <literal><link linkend="config.global.default_lang">default_lang</link></literal>
      language is used.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If no nodes are found in the preferred language, then
      it returns the node(s) which are in the
      <literal><link linkend="config.global.default_lang">default_lang</link></literal>
      language.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   The algorithm in PageKit 1.00 is slightly different from the above,
   but follows the same basic idea.
  </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Applying to Content: XSLT</title>
   <para>
    As of release 1.00 there is no support for Language Localization using
    XSLT.  However I plan to offer support in one of the two following ways:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Different source XML files, <filename>foo.en</filename>,
      <filename>foo.de</filename>, <filename>foo.es</filename>, and so on.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      PageKit will set the <literal>&lt;xsl:param name="pkit_lang"&gt;</literal>
      tag in the XSLT stylesheet.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Comments, suggestions, and patches welcome!
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Applying to Model</title>
   <para>
    To use the language settings from the Model, simply use the
    <literal><link linkend="model.api.pkit_lang">pkit_lang</link></literal> method.
   </para>
   <para>
    This can be useful for selecting content from the database based on language.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
  <title>Character set translation</title>
   <para>
    By default, PageKit attempts to output using <link linkend="config.global.default_output_charset">default_output_charset</link>.
    PageKit will attempt to translate the PageKit Templates and output passed
    to <link linkend="model.api.output_convert">output_convert</link> from
    <link linkend="config.global.default_input_charset">default_input_charset</link> to
    <link linkend="config.global.default_output_charset">default_output_charset</link>.
   </para>
   <para>
    Note: This also applies also to the message catalog if any. So write your message catalog files in
    <link linkend="config.global.default_input_charset">default_input_charset</link>.
   </para>
   <para>
    PageKit attempts to translate the output to a character set that is specified in the <literal>Accept-Charset</literal> header. If this is not possible,
    PageKit delivers the page in the <link linkend="config.global.default_output_charset">default_output_charset</link>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Caching</title>
  <para>
   Currently PageKit supports on-disk caching of compiled PageKit Templates.
   Future versions should also include in-memory caching and caching
   of Model output.
  </para>
  <para>
   XSL transformations are also cached, taking into account any input
   request parameters that are used in <literal>xsl:param</literal> tags
   contained in the top-level the XSLT file.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1><?dbhtml filename="component.html"?>
  <title>Component based architecture</title>
  <para>
   Components are similar to Server Side Includes (SSIs), in that the
   include PageKit Templates inside other PageKit Templates.  However, the
   can also have code associated with them that fills in the 
   <link linkend="model.tags">Model Tags</link>, including
   &lt;MODEL_VAR&gt;, &lt;MODEL_LOOP&gt;, and &lt;MODEL_IF&gt;.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <link linkend="pkit.component">PKIT_COMPONENT</link> tag specifies
   where the component should be included.  The Component can either
   be a PageKit Template file, or a PageKit Template generated from the
   <filename>Content/<replaceable>component_id</replaceable>.xml</filename>
   XML file.
  </para>
  <para>
   The following example illustration how absolute and relative paths
   work:
  </para>
  <informalexample>
   <programlisting>
    # absolute path - includes View/<replaceable>pkit_view</replaceable>/foo/bar.tmpl
    # or output generated from Content/foo/bar.xml
    &lt;PKIT_COMPONENT NAME="/foo/bar"&gt;
    # relative path, includes the bar.tmpl or bar.xml in the directory
    # of the enclosing PageKit Template/XML File.
    &lt;PKIT_COMPONENT NAME="bar"&gt;
   </programlisting>
  </informalexample>
 </sect1>
 <sect1><?dbhtml filename="session.html"?>
  <title>Sessions</title>
  <para>
   PageKit uses a subclass of <ulink url="http://kobesearch.cpan.org/search?dist=Apache-SessionX">Apache::SessionX</ulink> to provide sessions.
   It sets a cookie named <literal>pkit_session_id</literal> with an
   expiration of <literal><link linkend="config.global.session_expires">session_expires</link></literal>, if applicable.
  </para>
  <para>
   To access the session, use
  <informalexample>
   <programlisting>
    # gets hash tied to Session
    my $session = $model->session;
    # gets session value
    my $count = $session->{'count'};
    $count++;
    # sets session value
    $session->{'count'} = $count;
   </programlisting>
  </informalexample>
   PageKit takes care of opening and closing sessions.  Note that sessions
   are only created when something is written to session hash.
  </para>
  <warning>
   <title>Warning!</title>
   <para>Because of the way Apache::SessionX works, the session only gets saved
    if top level element in the tied hash gets changed.
   </para>
   <informalexample>
    <programlisting>
    # session will not be saved, if 'foo' was already in $session.
    my $session = $model->session;
    $session->{'foo'}->{'bar'} = 1;

    # session will be saved
    my $session = $model->session;
    $session->{'foo'}->{'bar'} = 1;
    # since 'baz' is top level element and is assigned, session will be saved
    $session->{'baz'} = 1;
    </programlisting>
   </informalexample>
  </warning>
  <para>
   To store information during a request, use the
   <literal><link linkend="model.api.pnotes">pnotes</link></literal> method.
  </para>
  <para>
   As of PageKit 1.05, there is support for associating sessions with
   authentication.  The associated session ID may be specified by the second
   argument returned my <link linkend="model.api.pkit_auth_session_key">pkit_auth_session_key</link>.  When a user logs in, their current session may be merged with the session
   stored with their user ID.  To override the default behavior, use the
    <link linkend="model.api.pkit_merge_sessions">pkit_merge_sessions</link> hook.
  </para>
  <para>
   As of PageKit 1.08, there is support for page based sessions.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1><?dbhtml filename="authentication.html"?>
  <title>Authentication</title>
  <para>
   When a user logins in, the <literal><link linkend="request.pkit_login">pkit_login</link></literal> request parameter must be set to a true value.  In addition, if you want
the user to be redirected to another page, set the <literal><link linkend="request.pkit_done">pkit_done</link></literal> parameter.  To do this, place
the following hidden fields in your login form page:
  <informalexample>
   <programlisting>
    &lt;!-- Login Page --&gt;
    #  will get set by pagekit to the page the user is requesting
    &lt;input type="hidden" name="pkit_done"&gt;
    &lt;input type="hidden" name="pkit_login" value="1"&gt;
   </programlisting>
  </informalexample>
  </para>
  <para>
   If <literal><link linkend="request.pkit_login">pkit_login</link></literal> is set to a true value, then PageKit calls <literal><link linkend="model.api.pkit_auth_credential">pkit_auth_credential</link></literal> method.  If this method returns a session key, then PageKit redirects to the page specified
by <literal><link linkend="request.pkit_done">pkit_done</link></literal>,
setting the cookie <literal>pkit_id</literal> to the session_key.
  </para>
  <para>
   While the user is logged in, PageKit checks the session_key by using
   the <literal><link linkend="model.api.pkit_auth_session_key">pkit_auth_session_key</link></literal> method.  If the <literal><link linkend="request.pkit_logout">pkit_logout</link></literal> request parameter is set, then the user is
logged out.
  </para>
  <para>
PageKit access to pages based on the <literal><link linkend="config.page.require_login">require_login</link></literal> attribute.
If <literal><link linkend="config.page.require_login">require_login</link></literal>
is set to <emphasis>recent</emphasis>, then PageKit requires that session is currently active in the last
<literal><link linkend="config.global.recent_login_timeout">recent_login_timeout</link></literal>
seconds.
  </para>
  <para>
  Note, that the pages <literal><link linkend="config.global.default_page">default_page</link></literal>,
  <literal><link linkend="config.global.verify_page">verify_page</link></literal> and
  <literal><link linkend="config.global.login_page">login_page</link></literal> can not be protected in any way.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1><?dbhtml filename="validation.html"?>
  <title>Form Validation</title>
   <para>
  PageKit uses <ulink url="http://search.cpan.org/doc/MARKSTOS/Data-FormValidator-1.5/lib/Data/FormValidator.pm">Data::FormValidator</ulink> to provide easy form validation.  Highlights
fields in red that user filled incorrectly by using the
<link linkend="pkit.errorfont">PKIT_ERRORFONT</link> tag.  In addition,
error message(s) are displayed using the <link linkend="pkit.messages">PKIT_MESSAGES</link> tag.
To use, pass an input profile to the
<literal><link linkend="model.api.pkit_validate_input">pkit_validate_input</link></literal> method.
  </para>
  <para>
   In addition, you may implement your own custom error handling by using <literal><link linkend="model.api.pkit_set_errorfont">pkit_set_errorfont</link></literal> to set the <link linkend="pkit.errorfont">PKIT_ERRORFONT</link> tags.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1><?dbhtml filename="fillinform.html"?>
  <title>Sticky HTML Forms</title>
  <para>
   PageKit uses <ulink url="http://kobesearch.cpan.org/search?dist=HTML-FillInForm">HTML::FillInForm</ulink> to fill in HTML Forms with the request parameters.  You
   can turn this feature off by setting <literal><link linkend="config.page.fill_in_form">fill_in_form</link></literal> to <emphasis>no</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>
   One useful application is if you have set up error handling and if an user
   submits an HTML form without filling out
   a required field, PageKit will re-display the HTML form with all the form 
   elements containing the submitted info.
  </para>
  <para>
   In additon to filling in request parameters, you may fill in the HTML
   fields from the model by using the <literal><link linkend="model.api.fillinform">fillinform</link></literal> method.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="features.multiple.views"><?dbhtml filename="multipleview.html"?>
  <title>Multiple Views</title>
  <para>
   Any page can have multiple views, by using the <literal><link linkend="request.pkit_view">pkit_view</link></literal> request parameter.
One example is Printable pages.  Another
is having the same web site branded differently for different companies.
Another is having different Media outputs such as HTML, XML and WML, by
using the <link linked="config.global.content_type">content_type</link>
configuration options.
  </para>
  <para>
   To create a new view, create a <filename>View/<replaceable>pkit_view</replaceable></filename> directory and place the PageKit Templates and XSLT files for
the pages and components that you wish to apply the view to.  Note that if
PageKit doesn't find a template or XSLT file in the <filename>View/<replaceable>pkit_view</replaceable></filename> directory it looks in the
<filename>View/Default</filename> directory.  That is, the files <filename>View/<replaceable>pkit_view</replaceable></filename> "override" the files
in <filename>View/Default</filename> directory.
  </para>
  <para>
   To association a media output such as XML, WML, or PDF with a view, use
   the View <link linkend="config.view.content_type">content_type</link> attribute.
   Note that in order for PDF output to work, you must install the Apache XML
   FOP processor, available from
   <ulink url="http://xml.apache.org/fop/">http://xml.apache.org/fop/</ulink>, and
   configure <link linkend="config.global.fop_command">fop_command</link> to point
   to the FOP processor.
  </para>
  <para>
   You may set the <literal><link linkend="request.pkit_view">pkit_view</link></literal> request parameter in the request URI or by using
   <literal>$model->input(pkit_view => <replaceable>pkit_view</replaceable>);</literal> in your model code.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="features.editing"><?dbhtml filename="editing.html"?>
  <title>On-line Editing tools</title>
  <para>
   PageKit supports a set of simple on-line editing tools.  To enable,
   set <literal><link linkend="config.server.can_edit">can_edit</link></literal> in your
   server config.  You will also need to call in your Model code:
  </para>
      <informalexample>
       <programlisting>
  $model->output(pkit_admin => 1);
       </programlisting>
      </informalexample>
 </sect1>
 <sect1><?dbhtml filename="errorreport.html"?>
  <title>Error Reporting</title>
  <para>
   PageKit uses Apache::ErrorReport to report errors.
   It reports warnings and fatal errors to screen or e-mail. Includes detailed information including error message, call
stack, uri, host, remote host, remote user, referrer, and Apache handler.
  </para>
  <para>
   To use, place the following in the your <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file:
  <informalexample>
   <programlisting>
  PerlModule Apache::ErrorReport
  PerlSetVar ErrorReportHandler display
   </programlisting>
  </informalexample>
  </para>
  <para>
If <literal>ErrorReportHandler</literal> is set to <emphasis role="bold">display</emphasis>, errors will be displayed on the screen for easy debugging. This should be
used in a development environment only.
  </para>
  <para>
If <literal>ErrorReportHandler</literal> is set to <emphasis role="bold">email</emphasis>, errors will be e-mailed to the site adminstrator as specified in the Apache
<literal>ServerAdmin</literal> configuration directive. This should be used on a production site.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
