Base:        https://www.eyrie.org/~eagle/
RSS-Base:    https://www.eyrie.org/~eagle/
Title:       Changes to Russ Allbery's Web Pages
Description: Recent changes to Russ Allbery's web pages.
Language:    en-us
Output:      *:thread:changes.th *:rss:changes.rss
Thread-Prefix:
 \rss[changes.rss][Changes to Russ Allbery's Web Pages]
 .
 \heading[Recent Changes][indent]
 .
 \h1[Recent Changes]
 .
 \quote(broken)[
     Put up in a place
     where it's easy to see
     the cryptic admonishment
     T.T.T.
     When you feel how depressingly
     slowly you climb,
     it's well to remember that
     Things Take Time.
 ][Piet Hein][]
 .
 This page lists all recent changes to my web site except for new
 \link[journal/][journal entries], along with a brief description.  Some
 of this information will be repeated in my journal, but more minor
 changes will only be noted here.  An \class(feed)[\link[changes.rss]
 [\image[journal/feed.png][]] \link[changes.rss][RSS feed]] of this
 information is also available.
 .
 Also see changes from \link[changes/2020.html][2020],
 \link[changes/2019.html][2019], \link[changes/2018.html][2018],
 \link[changes/2017.html][2017], \link[changes/2016.html][2016],
 \link[changes/2015.html][2015], \link[changes/2014.html][2014],
 \link[changes/2013.html][2013], \link[changes/2012.html][2012],
 \link[changes/2011.html][2011], \link[changes/2010.html][2010],
 \link[changes/2009.html][2009], and \link[changes/2008.html][2008].

Date: 2021-08-30 22:30
Title: Test UTF-8 entry
Link: /
Description:
 Test entry — with UTF-8 dash.

Date: 2021-08-30 21:25
Title: kstart 4.3
Link: software/kstart/
Description:
 Add support for kafs by continuing with -t behavior if kafs is present.
 Use libkeyutils if available to isolate a command's keyring from the
 invoking program if running a specific command with -t.  Use a better
 exit status when a command is killed with a signal.  Use explicit_bzero
 to clear the password for k5start -s.  Other portability fixes and
 updates.

Date: 2021-08-18 21:30
Title: Review: The Past is Red
Link: reviews/books/1-250-30112-2.html
Description: Review of The Past is Red by Catherynne M. Valente.

Date: 2021-08-16 20:58
Title: Review: Black Sun
Link: reviews/books/1-5344-3769-X.html
Description: Review of Black Sun by Rebecca Roanhorse.

Date: 2021-08-15 19:21
Title: Review: The Galaxy, and the Ground Within
Link: reviews/books/0-06-293605-0.html
Description: Review of The Galaxy, and the Ground Within by Becky Chambers.

Date: 2021-08-08 19:39
Title: Review: The Last Battle
Link: reviews/books/0-02-044210-6.html
Description: Review of The Last Battle by C.S. Lewis.

Date: 2021-08-07 17:24
Title: Broken link cleanup
Link: /
Description:
 Another periodic cleanup of broken links.

Date: 2021-08-01 21:12
Title: Review: Piranesi
Link: reviews/books/1-63557-564-8.html
Description: Review of Piranesi by Susanna Clarke.

Date: 2021-07-31 21:26
Title: Review: Fugitive Telemetry
Link: reviews/books/1-250-76538-2.html
Description: Review of Fugitive Telemetry by Martha Wells.

Date: 2021-07-24 08:23
Title: Add finalists for the World Fantasy Award
Link: reviews/awards.html
Description:
 Add the finalists for the 2021 World Fantasy Award for best novel.

Date: 2021-07-24 08:22
Title: Broken link cleanup
Link: /
Description:
 Another periodic cleanup of broken links.

Date: 2021-07-03 17:21
Title: Add Clarke Award nominees and Locus Award Winners
Link: reviews/awards.html
Description:
 Add the nominees for the 2021 Arthur C. Clarke Award, and the winners of
 the 2021 Locus Awards (Network Effect by Martha Wells for best SF novel,
 The City We Became by N.K. Jemisin for best fantasy novel, and Elatsoe by
 Darcie Little Badger for best first novel).

Date: 2021-06-27 19:55
Title: control-archive 1.9.1
Link: software/control-archive/
Description:
 A data-only release that updates the Big Eight control signing key and
 removes some obsolete information about net.*.

Date: 2021-06-27 15:23
Title: Added web page for Big Eight control information
Link: big-8/
Description:
 New web page summarizing control information for the Big Eight
 hierarchies with links to the control message signing keys and the PGP
 Moose key.

Date: 2021-06-20 20:57
Title: Review: Demon Lord of Karanda
Link: reviews/books/0-345-36331-0.html
Description: Review of Demon Lord of Karanda by David Eddings.

Date: 2021-06-19 21:03
Title: Review: The Magician's Nephew
Link: reviews/books/0-02-044230-0.html
Description: Review of The Magician's Nephew by C.S. Lewis.

Date: 2021-06-06 21:56
Title: Review: Stoneskin
Link: reviews/books/stoneskin.html
Description: Review of Stoneskin by K.B. Spangler.

Date: 2021-06-05 20:18
Title: Add winner of 2021 Nebula Award for best novel
Link: reviews/awards.html
Description:
 Add the winner of the 2021 Nebula Award for best novel (Network Effect by
 Martha Wells).

Date: 2021-06-05 19:37
Title: Broken link cleanup
Link: /
Description:
 Another periodic cleanup of broken links.

Date: 2021-05-31 21:14
Title: Review: The Horse and His Boy
Link: reviews/books/0-02-044200-9.html
Description: Review of The Horse and His Boy by C.S. Lewis.

Date: 2021-05-30 22:40
Title: Review: The Relentless Moon
Link: reviews/books/1-250-23648-7.html
Description: Review of The Relentless Moon by Mary Robinette Kowal.

Date: 2021-05-29 22:53
Title: Review: The Silver Chair
Link: reviews/books/0-02-044250-5.html
Description: Review of The Silver Chair by C.S. Lewis.

Date: 2021-05-29 20:51
Title: Broken link cleanup
Link: /
Description:
 Another periodic cleanup of broken links.

Date: 2021-05-15 21:16
Title: Review: A Desolation Called Peace
Link: reviews/books/1-250-18648-X.html
Description: Review of A Desolation Called Peace by Arkady Martine.

Date: 2021-05-02 20:03
Title: Review: The Voyage of the Dawn Treader
Link: reviews/books/0-02-044260-2.html
Description: Review of The Voyage of the Dawn Treader by C.S. Lewis.

Date: 2021-04-27 20:10
Title: Review: Beyond Shame
Link: reviews/books/beyond-shame.html
Description: Review of Beyond Shame by Kit Rocha.

Date: 2021-04-24 22:15
Title: Review: Learning React
Link: reviews/books/1-4920-5172-1.html
Description: Review of Learning React by Alex Banks & Eve Porcello.

Date: 2021-04-24 22:12
Title: Add nominees for the 2021 Hugo Award
Link: reviews/awards.html
Description:
 Add the nominees for the 2021 Hugo Award for best novel.

Date: 2021-04-10 19:24
Title: Broken link cleanup
Link: /
Description:
 Another periodic cleanup of broken links.

Date: 2021-04-05 18:59
Title: Add 2021 winner of the BSFA award
Link: reviews/awards.html
Description:
 Add 2021 winner of the BSFA award for best novel (The City We Became, by
 N.K. Jemisin).

Date: 2021-04-05 18:56
Title: Add 2021 winner of the Philip K. Dick Award
Link: reviews/awards.html
Description:
 Add 2021 winner of the Philip K. Dick Award for best novel (The Road out
 of Winter, by Alison Stine).

Date: 2021-04-03 19:21
Title: Review: Prince Caspian
Link: reviews/books/0-02-044240-8.html
Description: Review of Prince Caspian by C.S. Lewis.

Date: 2021-03-30 22:53
Title: Review: Paladin's Strength
Link: reviews/books/paladins-strength.html
Description: Review of Paladin's Strength by T. Kingfisher.

Date: 2021-03-29 10:11
Title: Add series information to Paladin's Grace
Link: reviews/books/paladins-grace.html
Description:
 Paladin's Grace by T. Kingfisher is the first of a series.  Add the
 series information and a mention of the sequel.

Date: 2021-03-28 21:55
Title: Review: JavaScript: The Definitive Guide
Link: reviews/books/1-4919-5202-4.html
Description: Review of JavaScript: The Definitive Guide by David Flanagan.

Date: 2021-03-28 17:07
Title: Add sample INN init script and systemd unit file
Link: software/inn/
Description:
 In the documentation pages for INN CURRENT, 2.6, and 2.5, add the sample
 init script and systemd unit.

Date: 2021-03-28 09:21
Title: Pod::Thread 2.00
Link: software/pod-thread/
Description:
 Handle the navbar and table of contents internally in the module rather
 than via a pre-scanning pass.  Honor CVS Id strings found anywhere in the
 document.  Don't title-case words in section titles in the navbar that
 contain an underscore.

Date: 2021-03-21 19:58
Title: cvs2xhtml 1.15
Link: software/web/
Description:
 Convert to Python 3.  Update my email address.

Date: 2021-03-21 19:57
Title: cl2xhtml 1.12
Link: software/web/
Description:
 Convert to Python 3.  Update my email address.

Date: 2021-03-21 19:56
Title: faq2html 1.36
Link: software/web/
Description:
 Support formatting of dense bullet lists with line continuations but no
 blank lines between bullets.  Update my email address.

Date: 2021-03-21 19:03
Title: Remove DocKnot from my personal Debian repository list
Link: software/debian.html
Description: DocKnot has now been uploaded to Debian proper.

Date: 2021-03-21 18:57
Title: Add separate web pages for Pod::Thread
Link: software/pod-thread/
Description:
 As the first step in cleaning up my static site generator pages, and in
 prepration for uploading it to CPAN in its own right, move Pod::Thread to
 its own separate web pages.

Date: 2021-03-20 13:35
Title: pam-krb5 4.10
Link: software/pam-krb5/
Description:
 Fix use-after-free if krb5_cc_get_principal fails on the newly-created
 ticket cache.

Date: 2021-03-20 13:16
Title: rra-c-util 9.0
Link: software/rra-c-util/
Description:
 Rename SQLite Autoconf macros and their outputs from SQLITE to SQLITE3.
 Fix support for optional libraries.  Rename KRB5_CPPFLAGS_GCC to
 KRB5_CPPFLAGS_WARNINGS.  Stop defining AM_CONDITIONAL in Autoconf
 macros.  Check for working Kerberos headers as well as libraries.  Add C
 stubs for sd_notify and sd_notifyf and a preprocessor stub for
 sd_is_socket.  Fix portable/sd-daemon.h to include prerequisite headers.
 Fix RRA_PROG_PYTHON with Python 3.0 and older Python 2.x versions.  Fix
 problems with the util/fdflag test.  Use AS_ECHO where possible.  Fix
 perlcritic with YAML::XS.

Date: 2021-03-20 11:38
Title: Clean GnuPG key
Link: personal/contact.html
Description:
 Refresh the expiration on my signing key and re-export my key with the
 export-clean flag, which cleans up a bunch of duplicate and expired
 signatures.

Date: 2021-03-20 09:36
Title: Add nominees for 2021 Nebula Award for best novel
Link: reviews/awards.html
Description:
 Add the nominees for the 2021 Nebula Award for best novel.

Date: 2021-03-14 11:03
Title: New experimental Big Eight control message signing key
Link: journal/2021-03/001.html
Description:
 Published a new experimental signing key for Big Eight control messages
 that was generated with a modern GnuPG.

Date: 2021-03-13 09:17
Title: Add 2020 British Fantasy Award winner
Link: reviews/awards.html
Description:
 Add winner of the 2020 British Fantasy Robert Holdstock Award for best
 fantasy novel (The Bone Ships, by RJ Barker).

Date: 2021-03-01 19:36
Title: Review: The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe
Link: reviews/books/0-02-044220-3.html
Description: Review of The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe by C.S. Lewis.

Date: 2021-02-28 19:29
Title: Review: Architects of Memory
Link: reviews/books/1-250-21546-3.html
Description: Review of Architects of Memory by Karen Osborne.

Date: 2021-02-27 13:11
Title: DocKnot 4.01
Link: software/docknot/
Description:
 Add support for a global user configuration file.  Allow the distribution
 directory to be specified in it.  Add support for GnuPG signing of
 generated tarballs.  Fix docknot --help.  Remove the obsolete
 load_appdata_json helper.  Fix some documentation bugs left over from the
 4.00 release.

Date: 2021-02-21 20:06
Title: Review: Finder
Link: reviews/books/0-7564-1511-X.html
Description: Review of Finder by Suzanne Palmer.

Date: 2021-02-20 20:43
Title: Review: The Fated Sky
Link: reviews/books/0-7653-9893-1.html
Description: Review of The Fated Sky by Mary Robinette Kowal.

Date: 2021-02-17 21:19
Title: Review: Solutions and Other Problems
Link: reviews/books/1-9821-5694-5.html
Description: Review of Solutions and Other Problems by Allie Brosh.

Date: 2021-02-14 20:35
Title: Review: Spheres of Influence
Link: reviews/books/1-4516-3937-6.html
Description: Review of Spheres of Influence by Ryk E. Spoor.

Date: 2021-02-14 19:20
Title: Add winner of 2020 Mythopoeic Award
Link: reviews/mythopoeic.html
Description:
 Add the winner of the (delayed) 2020 Mythopoeic Fantasy Award for Adult
 Literature (Snow White Learns Witchcraft, by Theodora Goss).

Date: 2021-02-13 09:53
Title: Broken link cleanup
Link: /
Description:
 Another periodic cleanup of broken links.

Date: 2021-02-07 19:31
Title: Review: The Future of Another Timeline
Link: reviews/books/0-7653-9212-7.html
Description: Review of The Future of Another Timeline by Annalee Newitz.

Date: 2021-02-01 20:57
Title: Remove changes from December 2020
Link: changes.html
Description: Remove the changes from December 2020 from the recent changes
 page.

Date: 2021-01-30 15:12
Title: Broken link cleanup
Link: /
Description:
 Another periodic cleanup of broken links.

Date: 2021-01-28 22:23
Title: INN 2.6.4
Link: software/inn/
Description:
 Added support for systemd notifications and socket activation.  Adapt the
 length of the DH parameter during DHE key exchanges in nnrpd.  Return
 information about retired CNFS buffers from cnfsstat.  Externalize the
 CSS information from generated innreport reports.  Support storing wire
 format articles with sm.  Add a flag to rnews to disallow additional
 unpackers, a flag to save rejected articles, and a flag to log the
 message ID of duplicate articles.  Add a compile-time option to enable
 hardening flags.

Date: 2021-01-26 20:12
Title: Review: A Deadly Education
Link: reviews/books/0-593-12849-4.html
Description: Review of A Deadly Education by Naomi Novik.

Date: 2021-01-25 20:11
Title: Review: The City We Became
Link: reviews/books/0-316-50985-X.html
Description: Review of The City We Became by N.K. Jemisin.

Date: 2021-01-24 21:00
Title: Review: Laziness Does Not Exist
Link: reviews/books/1-9821-4013-5.html
Description: Review of Laziness Does Not Exist by Devon Price.

Date: 2021-01-18 20:00
Title: Review: The Secret Barrister
Link: reviews/books/1-5098-4115-6.html
Description: Review of The Secret Barrister by The Secret Barrister.

Date: 2021-01-04 22:13
Title: Update some blog roll links
Link: journal/
Description:
 Update URL to Nicola Griffith's blog, and switch Karl Schroeder's blog to
 https.

Date: 2021-01-03 18:49
Title: Review: The Once and Future Witches
Link: reviews/books/0-316-42202-9.html
Description: Review of The Once and Future Witches by Alix E. Harrow.

Date: 2021-01-01 19:01
Title: Update award winners
Link: reviews/awards.html
Description:
 Add links to all award pages that have good award web sites.  Add notes
 where the 2020 award was canceled or delayed.  Add the winner of the 2020
 Prix Aurora Award for best adult novel (The Gossamer Mage by Julie
 E. Czerneda) and the Sunburst award for adults (Gods of Jade and Shadow
 by Silvia Moreno-Garcia).

Date: 2021-01-01 13:53
Title: Rotate 2020 changes
Link: changes/2020.html
Description:
 Move all web site changes from 2020 to a separate page and remove all
 entries older than December of 2020 from the current changes page.

Date: 2021-01-01 11:12
Title: 2020 reading in review
Link: reviews/year/2020.html
Description:
 Add an overview of my 2020 reading, main book recommendations, and
 reading statistics.
